<?xml version="1.0"?>
<corpus>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/02/17/europe/macron-yellow-vests-antisemitism-intl/index.html" date="2019-02-17" labels="europe, Macron attacks yellow vests after philosopher abused at rally - CNN" title="Macron attacks yellow vests after philosopher abused at rally - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
French President Emmanuel Macron has condemned abuse by a group of "yellow vest" protesters, after a well-known philosopher was verbally attacked at a rally in Paris on Saturday.
Several gilets jaunes (or "yellow vest") protesters were filmed hurling abuse at philosopher and vocal Israel supporter Alain Finkielkraut as he ran into protesters during the 14th consecutive weekend of marches.
Insults including "dirty zionist," "f***ing Islamophobe" and "f*** your mother" were hurled at Finkelkraut, while less hostile activists walked him away from the demonstration and behind police lines.
French philosopher Alain Finkielkraut at the library of the French Academy.
"The son of Polish emigrants who became a French academician, Alain Finkielkraut is not only an eminent man of letters but a symbol of what the Republic allows everyone," Macron wrote on Twitter.
"The anti-Semitic insults he has been subjected to are the absolute negation of who we are and what makes us a great nation. We will not tolerate them," he added.
Read More
Les injures antisémites dont il a fait l'objet sont la négation absolue de ce que nous sommes et de ce qui fait de nous une grande nation. Nous ne les tolèrerons pas.
https://t.co/WSUTuJmQWX
— Emmanuel Macron (@EmmanuelMacron) 
February 16, 2019


Finkielkraut reacted in French weekly newspaper Le Journal Du Dimanche on Saturday, saying: "I felt absolute hatred, and unfortunately it wasn't the first time."
The Paris prosecutor's office has launched an investigation into "public abuse on the basis of origin, ethnicity, country, race or religion," an offense that carries a maximum sentence of one year in jail and a 45,000-euro ($51.000) fine.
Anti-Semitic acts in France increased by 69% in the first nine months of 2018, Prime Minister Edouard Philippe said in November.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/13/opinions/presidential-weekly-briefing-putin-private-meetings-vinograd/index.html" date="2019-01-13" labels="opinions, Trump's very private meetings are a huge favor to Putin (opinion) - CNN" title="Trump's very private meetings are a huge favor to Putin (opinion) - CNN" >
Samantha Vinograd is a CNN national security analyst. She served on President Obama's National Security Council from 2009-2013 and at the Treasury Department under President George W. Bush. Follow her 
@sam_vinograd
. The views expressed in this commentary are her own. View more
 opinion articles
 on CNN.
 (CNN)
Every week, I offer a glimpse of the kind of intelligence assessments that are likely to come across the desk of the President of the United States, modeled on the President's Daily Briefing, or PDB, which the director of national intelligence prepares for the President almost daily.
Here's this week's briefing
:
 Sam Vinograd
With new 
Washington Post reporting
 that President Donald Trump may have taken unprecedented, and 
potentially illegal
, measures to conceal the contents of private conversations with President Vladimir Putin, we are providing you with an update on several ongoing Russian threat streams. These include the growing counterintelligence risks posed by actions that aid and abet Russian intelligence operations.
The full panoply of Russian actions -- from election interference to the manipulation of those whom Putin considers high-value American assets -- pose an unusual and extraordinary threat to the national security and foreign policy of the United States. And Trump's efforts to keep meetings with Putin under wraps only exacerbate this threat.
Under his thumb 
Read More
Despite the President and his team's 
denials
  regarding allegations that he tried to conceal the contents of his meetings with Putin, reporting indicating that he went to 
extraordinary measures
 to do just that  will add to Putin's perception that he's in the driver's seat. More to the point, Putin will feel like he can manipulate any narrative about the meetings. He may even try to spread theories (whether warranted or not) that there was an intent to conceal evidence of a crime -- whether criminal or counterintelligence related -- because that undermines the credibility of the President himself. Absent our own records of the meeting, we have nothing we can use to counter any Russian misinformation about what happened.  
World leaders are talking, Mr. Trump -- are you listening? 
Even worse, giving the Russian government sensitive information that US officials do not have -- information on what was discussed in meetings between Putin and Trump -- also represents a major operational risk. The Russian government likely has more knowledge than our own administration does  on key bilateral policy discussions, including Israel, which 
Trump acknowledged
 that they discussed. 
It's also an intelligence win for Putin. Russian officials' access to this sensitive information represents a potential bribery point the Putin can use against Trump at a later date. Russia can threaten to release parts of presidential conversations if, for example, Trump threatens to do something that they don't like. In short, by concealing the contents of his meetings, the President is opening the door for Putin to manipulate him and use him as an asset.
Because the President has given Putin and his team a leg up on the US government, Putin may also try to benefit from any perceptions that the President prefers playing for the Russians more than he does for the US. Putin gets bonus points in this scenario because, by failing to treat his team with the same consideration that he treats Russia, Trump is implying a lack of confidence in his own institutions and officials. 
JUST WATCHED
NYT: FBI feared Trump was working on behalf of Russia
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
 
10:36
The Washington Post reporting comes on the heels of news that the FBI launched an unprecedented counterintelligence investigation into whether Trump posed a threat to national security -- a news story that will only embolden Putin further. The very fact that the FBI assessed that Putin was potentially willing to compromise a sitting president will probably bolster the vision of himself as a strong, skilled and fearless leader.  
Trump's responses to the reporting -- including insulting
 FBI officials
, 
Democrats
 and 
past US presidents
 -- rather than clearly stating that Russian intelligence operations against us are a threat that we should all take seriously, are music to Putin's ears because they advance Russia's mission to spread division in the US.
Putin will probably use his information warriors to spread the administration's responses on social media, because they appear to promote Russian objectives rather than US national security ones. We know that Russian troll farms 
have engaged
 in influence campaigns on social media in the past to spread inflammatory or divisive messages, so they likely have the ability to do so now.  
A czar is born
Putin is due to relinquish power in 2024, but if he has his way, he may continue ruling Russia long after that. Russia still pretends to be a democracy, and its constitution currently puts term limits on presidents. But the Russian Duma 
is considering
 constitutional amendments that, if passed, could allow Putin to extend his rein for as long as he likes. Putin is increasingly emulating a czar-like ruler for life, who does what he wants, when he wants. Domestically, we should expect Putin to continue his crackdown on opposition movements and minority groups while he continues to pursue a full suite of externally aggressive activities.
The world is his oyster
Bolstered by feelings of impunity, Putin is ramping up, not tamping down, his global interference efforts. Israeli officials 
have alluded
 to Russian interference in their upcoming elections. French authorities 
are probing
 potential Russian interference during the "gilets jaunes," or yellow vest protests, and US Director of National Intelligence Dan Coats
 publicly acknowledged 
 Russian efforts to interfere in our midterm elections. Whatever actions have been taken to date, it's clear that Putin thinks the world -- along with its elections -- is his oyster. 
He'll pack our bags for us
The administration's focus on bringing US troops back home, even if missions are not complete in key theaters like Syria, is a boon to Russian plans to expand its own sphere of influence. Putin will likely try to expedite a rapid US departure from Syria because it helps him paint the US as an unreliable partner, while concurrently giving him more room to operate in Syria itself. 
What really makes the Trump presidency scary
Without US troops on the ground or US funding that goes toward stabilization efforts in Syria, Putin can claim we don't have skin in the game -- whereas he has resources on the ground and the ability to convene key players, including Syrian strongman Bashar al-Assad, Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and Iran's Ayatollah Sayyid Ali Khamenei. We should also be on the lookout for indications of chemical weapons attacks as we prepare to leave. Russia used chemical weapons in the UK (though the Kremlin denies it), and the Kremlin has also
 repeatedly lied
 and said Assad hasn't used them in Syria. 
Nuking it
Conventional military threats from Putin will likely continue. Showcasing his biggest and baddest military toys helps broadcast both the strength of the Russian military, while 
highlighting Russian weapons
 like hypersonic missiles, which we 
are not adequately prepared
 to defend against. Factually speaking, he doesn't need expensive nuclear weapons to strategically threaten the United States. He is accomplishing that goal with relatively inexpensive cybersecurity attacks and information warfare. But a nuclear showdown gets him bonus points at home, while leading us to spend money just to keep up.
Stay up to date...
Sign up for our new 
newsletter
.
Join us on 
Twitter 
and 
Facebook
Our public narrative right now is a key component of neutralizing Russian threats. Claims that this administration
 has been tougher
 on Russia than any of its predecessors misses the underlying point -- Putin is not changing his behavior. In fact, he is consolidating power while Russia is escalating its activities and posing a direct threat to US strategic interests. 
If this public response narrative continues, it only serves Putin's interests, not ours. By failing to acknowledge that we have not successfully defended against Russia's attack or deterred its illegal activities, we look more focused on our own image than on keeping our country safe.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/11/25/opinions/paris-burning-macron-jeopardy-andelman/index.html" date="2018-11-25" labels="opinions, Emmanuel Macron's future could be put into jeopardy by Paris demonstrations (opinion) - CNN" title="Emmanuel Macron's future could be put into jeopardy by Paris demonstrations (opinion) - CNN" >
David A. Andelman, visiting scholar at the 
Center on National Security 
at Fordham Law School and director of its Red Lines Project, is a contributor to CNN, where his columns won the Deadline Club Award for Best Opinion Writing. Author of "
A Shattered Peace: Versailles 1919 and the Price We Pay Today,
" and translator of "
An Impossible Dream: Reagan Gorbachev and a World Without the Bomb
," he was formerly a foreign correspondent for The New York Times and Paris correspondent for CBS News. Follow him on Twitter 
@DavidAndelman
. The views expressed in this commentary are his own. View 
more opinion 
on CNN.
Paris (CNN)
From our apartment window across the Seine, we could see the smoke rising from the Champs-Élysées, where flames of the burning barricades mingled with the fumes of the tear gas grenades. The demonstrators, wearing the trademark yellow vests that gave their movement its name -- the "gilets jaunes" -- were prying paving stones from the avenue to hurl at the riot police, clad in black from head to toe, with gas masks and tall plastic shields.
Paris was burning. France was in revolt.  
It was a sharp contrast to the vast popular wave that swept President Emmanuel Macron into office with a stunning 
66% of the vote
 over his right-wing challenger Marine Le Pen 18 months ago and gave his newly formed party an 
overwhelming plurality of 300 seats
.
JUST WATCHED
Macron slams protests after violence erupts
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
 
02:15
Macron surged to power promising to bring peaceful revolution to France and drag it, kicking and screaming, into the 21st century.  Yet his ambitious programs of social and economic reform have stumbled in their reach, some say over-reach, since then. At home, this stemmed from policies aimed at deregulation -- freeing businesses to act more rationally, but spreading fear across the French working class that their lifetime sinecures might suddenly be in jeopardy. 
Even before his proposed reforms, his popularity began to 
plunge
 to half its sky-high numbers when he first took office. But since he has undertaken such an agenda, Macron's popularity has hit a
 new low
 -- 26%, which is below his predecessors François Hollande (48% ) and Nicolas Sarkozy (29%) at this point in their presidencies. Neither won re-election to a second term.
Read More
Now, Macron seems to have touched a third rail of French politics when he announced an 
increase in the national gasoline tax
. Gas prices in France had already reached a stunning height of $1.74 per liter in October. With the French minimum wage barely 
$1,322 per month
, (€1,160 after taxes) it's no wonder the French found themselves at a breaking point, even with inflation hovering at a manageable 2.2% annually.
France's Macron reshuffles cabinet amid scandals, plummeting popularity
This weekend's violent outbreaks in the heart of Paris and more peaceful protests across France were all part of a long tradition of demonstrations (the French call them "manifestations") -- with the forces of order dating back to the French Revolution more than two centuries ago. Ironically, in each case, while the demonstrators won some victories, often significant ones, some presidents emerged stronger than ever. In 1968, after a massive student-led protest, 
Charles De Gaulle
 won an unprecedented victory in the next parliamentary elections. François Mitterrand, president in the 1980s, went on to win a triumphant second seven-year term after the demonstrations I covered, ruling France for 14 years. 
Right now, though, Macron has to find a way to satisfy the forces still demanding change and those who fear it, a political requirement that his successful predecessors somehow managed to satisfy. As one of his top advisers told the 
French Sunday paper Journal de Dimanche
, "We're not changing direction, we simply have to put more people in the boat."
Still, having observed eight French presidents, some successful, others not, I am persuaded that it will take more than simply tinkering with the cargo. And any significant course correction in a French system half a millennium in the making is quite a task.
Emmanuel Macron is auditioning to be leader of the free world
This time, the 
revolution
 seems to have united rural and urban France, because all French are compelled by certain items: taxes, gas prices and, more broadly, inflation. Macron must somehow find a way to satisfy this broad body that his vaunted reforms will work to improve the lives of many rather than the privileges of a few.  
Though the demonstrations began more than a week ago, Saturday's actions in Paris were the most 
explosive and violent
. That must, of course, be taken in context. While they provide powerful visuals, few get badly hurt. Not a single person was shot on either side, though I could see the riot police generously using their nightsticks on protesters, and water cannons leveled those who had the poor sense to get too close. Ministry of Interior figures showed 24 people injured across France on Saturday, mainly "casseurs" -- breakers or hooligans, who the government blamed for most of the violent action.
Macron aides sought to point the finger at the extreme right, though Marine Le Pen 
turned the attacks right back
, asking why Interior Minister Christophe Castaner "let these people onto the Champs-Élysées."
Still, as political theater, it certainly poses a real challenge for Macron's self-styled revolutionary, though unabashedly pro-business, government and his clear interest in becoming the leader of a new post-Brexit Europe. 
For more opinion...
Sign up for our new 
newsletter
Join us on 
Twitter 
and 
Facebook
At 7:17 p.m., after a full day of the most vigorous pitched battles and just as the gendarmerie was managing to regain control of the Champs-Élysées, Macron 
tweeted
: "Thank you to our law enforcement for their courage and professionalism. Shame on those who attacked them. Shame on those who have abused other citizens and journalists. Shame on those who have tried to intimidate elected officials. No room for this violence in the Republic." 
Macron can certainly use all the support he can muster, at home and abroad, as he struggles to weather these indisputably serious social and economic storms. Two weeks ago, at the Arc de Triomphe at the head of the Champs-Élysées, Macron urged the leaders of scores of nations to eschew nationalism and embrace globalism. His views were widely praised, though 
not by Donald Trump
, whose 
response 
was of little help: "The problem is that Emmanuel suffers from a very low Approval Rating in France, 26%, and an unemployment rate of almost 10%.  He was just trying to get onto another subject." 
In his hour of perhaps greatest need, the last thing Macron needs is a casseur flinging even rhetorical paving stones from across the Atlantic.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/02/19/europe/anti-semitism-protest-france-intl/index.html" date="2019-02-19" labels="europe, France anti-Semitism: Protesters rally as attacks rise - CNN" title="France anti-Semitism: Protesters rally as attacks rise - CNN" >
 (CNN)
Protesters gathered Tuesday night in cities across France to march against anti-Semitism after a rise in such incidents in the country.
The marches came after around 80 graves were desecrated with swastikas overnight in a Jewish cemetery in eastern France, according to local officials. Photos showed tombstones spray-painted with blue and yellow Nazi symbols and other graffiti.
Graves were vandalized with swastikas at a Jewish cemetery in the French village of Quatzenheim.
French President Emmanuel Macron condemned the attack during his visit Tuesday to the cemetery in Quatzenheim, where he inspected the damage.
"We will take actions, we will use laws and we will punish," Macron told local communities leaders at the cemetery. 
"Those who did this are not worthy of the republic. ... France will punish them. I don't want what happened here to give ideas to others."
French President Emmanuel Macron at the Jewish cemetery in Quatzenheim, which was vandalized with Nazi symbols and other graffiti.
Read More
Macron later visited the Paris Holocaust Memorial on Tuesday evening.
The attack comes after anti-government gilets jaunes or "yellow vest" protesters 
hurled verbal abuse Saturday 
at philosopher and Israel supporter Alain Finkielkraut as he ran into the demonstrators on the 14th consecutive weekend of their marches.
It was also the second recent attack at a Jewish cemetery in France. Tombstones and a holocaust memorial 
outside Strasbourg were vandalized in December.
Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said he was shocked at the vandalism in Quatzenheim and called on leaders in France and Europe to "take a strong stand against anti-Semitism."
"It is a plague that endangers everyone, not just us, and it must be condemned wherever and whenever it rears its head," Netanyahu said.
People take part in a rally against anti-Semitism at Republique Square in Paris on February 19.
Anti-Semitic incidents on the rise
The country, which is home to the
 500,000 Jews -- the largest community in Europe
 -- has seen a 74% increase in anti-Semitic acts, according to 
French authorities
, with 311 incidents recorded in 2017, compared with 541 in 2018.
At least 11 people have been killed in anti-Semitic violence in France since 2016. Last March, 85-year-old Holocaust survivor Mireille Knoll was slain in her Paris apartment, an act of brutality that compelled thousands to protest in the capital. 
'I'm scared for the future of my baby here': French Jews live in fear amid rising anti-Semitic acts
In 2017, Sarah Halimi, 65, was also killed in her apartment in the city and thrown from her balcony in what was called an anti-Semitic attack.
In 2015, four people were killed and 15 others were held hostage at a
 kosher supermarket in Paris in a siege
 carried out by an associate of the Charlie Hebdo shooters. Three years earlier, three children and one teacher were slain at 
a Jewish school in Toulouse
. 
A 2018 
CNN survey of seven European countries 
-- Great Britain, Sweden, Germany, France, Poland, Hungary and Austria -- pointed to the prevalence of anti-Semitism in Europe. Anti-Semitic stereotypes proved widespread in France, where a quarter of respondents said Jews had too much influence in business and finance.
The study also revealed ignorance about the Holocaust, particularly among younger generations. One in five French people between 18 and 34 said they'd never heard of the Holocaust.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/08/politics/trump-france-protests/index.html" date="2018-12-08" labels="politics, Trump faults Paris climate agreement as protests in France continue - CNNPolitics" title="Trump faults Paris climate agreement as protests in France continue - CNNPolitics" >
Washington (CNN)
President Donald Trump blamed the Paris climate accord as demonstrations in France 
continued to protest 
over an increase in fuel tax and other grievances.
"The Paris Agreement isn't working out so well for Paris," Trump tweeted Saturday morning. "Protests and riots all over France. People do not want to pay large sums of money, much to third world countries (that are questionably run), in order to maybe protect the environment. Chanting 'We Want Trump!' Love France." 
The Paris Agreement isn't working out so well for Paris. Protests and riots all over France. People do not want to pay large sums of money, much to third world countries (that are questionably run), in order to maybe protect the environment. Chanting "We Want Trump!" Love France.
— Donald J. Trump (@realDonaldTrump) 
December 8, 2018


Trump's tweet comes as French police detained more than 
200 people in Paris 
and fired tear gas on protestors during a fourth weekend of demonstrations.
Who are the 'yellow vest' protesters causing chaos in France?
The demonstrations in Paris have erupted into the worst riots France has witnessed in decades and a political crisis for French President Emmanuel Macron. The movement began as a rebuke of the country's fuel price hikes and evolved to a broader protest against the cost of living pressures and anger at Macron's government.
In his tweet Saturday, Trump also reiterated that Paris protesters have been chanting "we want Trump" -- a 
claim that remains unfounded
.
Read More
Since taking office in May 2017, Macron has been a champion of the 2015 Paris climate agreement, reaffirming his commitment as Trump 
announced last year that 
he was withdrawing the United States from the accord.
Many of the protesters -- known as "gilets jaunes" or "yellow vests" -- 
are angry with Macron 
for extending the environmental policies implemented under his predecessor, former President François Hollande.
On Tuesday, French Prime Minister Edouard Philippe 
announced
 that the planned tax hike -- part of measures aiming to combat climate change -- would be delayed by six months, from January 1 to mid-2019, in hopes of subduing the protests.
"I am glad that my friend (Macron) and the protestors in Paris have agreed with the conclusion I reached two years ago," Trump tweeted later Tuesday. "The Paris Agreement is fatally flawed because it raises the price of energy for responsible countries while whitewashing some of the worst polluters...in the world."
The next day, Macron's office announced that the tax increases would not be introduced in 2019.
CNN's Maegan Vazquez, Saskya Vandoorne, Hilary Clarke, Sam Bradpiece and Peter Wilkinson contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/11/17/europe/macron-france-fuel-protests-intl/index.html" date="2018-11-17" labels="europe, Macron bears brunt of discontent as French fuel protests leave 1 dead, dozens injured - CNN" title="Macron bears brunt of discontent as French fuel protests leave 1 dead, dozens injured - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
A protester was accidentally run over and killed by a car during a demonstration over rising fuel prices, a top official in eastern France said Saturday. 
Mass demonstrations causing roadblocks across the country are part of the "gilets jaunes" or "yellow vests" movement, which opposes
 
mounting gas prices and eco-taxes on polluting forms of transport. 
The death occurred when a driver "panicked" and ran over someone after arriving at a blockade for an undeclared protest not far from the city of Lyon, Louis Laugier, the prefect of the Savoie region, said at a news conference.
A further 227 people were injured -- six severely -- in protests across the country, and 73 people were taken into police custody, the Interior Ministry said in a statement. Five police officers suffered slight injuries, and one was severely injured. Another five gendarmes were hurt as well. 
Protesters wearing yellow vests demonstrate on the Promenade des Anglais in Nice, southern France, on Saturday.
Speaking about the death, French Interior Minister Christophe Castaner said: "That's the reason why we were worried to have people (who are) not experienced organizing protests."
Read More
Ecology Minister François de Rugy called on citizens to "respect caution and safety recommendations" in order for protests to go ahead "without a new tragedy," in a tweet Saturday. He also offered his condolences to the family of the victim.
More than 1 million people were expected to turn out Saturday for demonstrations across the country. Partway through the day, the numbers were much lower than that.
About 280,000 people participated in more than 2,000 demonstrations, the Interior Ministry said.
"Honestly we're satisfied, even if it's true we are not hundreds of thousands people here, but still, people have come. The day is not over yet, and we're glad that there are no incidents here," Thierry Paul Valette, who helped organize a protest on the Champs Elysées in Paris, told CNN.
"We can't stand Macron's taxes any more. It's too much. We couldn't make ourselves heard through political parties or trade unions, so we had to do something."
People wearing yellow vests block the motorway in Antibes, southeastern France, on Saturday.
The protest was billed as likely to be one of the toughest tests yet of Emmanuel Macron's 18-month-old presidency.
Website 
blocage17novembre
 said protests were planned in all 95 of France's mainland departments, while a petition on change.org calling on the French government to lower the cost of fuel has gotten more than 850,000 signatures.
In addition to concerns over spiraling fuel prices, the protests also reflect long-running tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor.
Price hike
Diesel prices have surged 16% this year from an average 1.24 euros ($1.41) per liter to 1.48 euros ($1.69), even hitting 1.53 euros in October, according to UFIP, France's oil industry federation. 
The price hike is largely caused by a leap in the wholesale price of oil, with Brent crude oil -- a benchmark for worldwide oil purchases -- increasing by more than 20% in the first half of 2018 from around $60 a barrel to a peak of $86.07 in early October. 
A protest against rising fuel and oil prices takes place in Nice, southeastern France, on November 15.
French protesters are, however, not directing their anger at OPEC for reducing oil production, or at the US administration for implementing tariffs on Iran, crippling its oil exports. 
Macron is instead bearing the brunt of widespread French discontent
, with many protesters furious at the current leader's extension of environmental policies implemented under François Hollande's government. 
Notably, taxes were increased by 8 centimes last January on diesel, and by 4 centimes on petrol. Tax on diesel will also increase by another 6.4 centimes in 2019, and by 2.9 centimes for petrol. These rises follow many decades of under-taxation of diesel in France. 
Macron criticized
The growing resentment has also been a springboard for partisan political attacks, with opponents of Macron's centrist En Marche party attempting to energize their bases to fuel further revolt. 
"This government hasn't understood the anger of the French," Olivier Faure, head of the French Socialist Party, said Wednesday. 
"Macron has not heard the French," Laurent Wauquiez, leader of the center-right party Les Républicains, added in an interview for BFMTV and RMC radio. 
France's Macron reshuffles cabinet amid scandals, plummeting popularity
Meanwhile, Macron's former nemesis, Marine Le Pen, leader of France's far-right National Rally, said: "We were the first party to express our total support for this movement." 
Castaner hit back at Macron's opponents, branding the protests "political" and accusing Les Républicains of being behind them. 
"It's a political protest with the Republicans behind it, and it's irrational because the rising taxes have been compensated by the decline in the oil market," he told CNN's French affiliate BFMTV. "We hear the protests, we hear the anger, I know the situation, but we have to explain that it's essential that we exit fossil fuels."  
The minister said police would be present to break up any dangerous roadblocks. "I am asking for the roads to not be completely blocked," Castaner said. "Where there is a roadblock -- which means there's a risk for emergency services -- there will be police." 
Macron struck a more conciliatory tone in an interview Wednesday, saying: "I hear the anger, and it's a fundamental right in our society to be allowed to express it." 
He nevertheless admitted that he was "wary because many different people are trying to piggyback on this movement." 
Prime Minister Edouard Philippe also announced close to 500 million euros in aid to low-income motorists in a key concession Wednesday.
CNN's Eva Tapiero reported from Paris, while Matthew Robinson and Laura Smith-Spark wrote from London. CNN's Saskya Vandoorne and Hilary McGann contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/04/politics/donald-trump-paris-yellow-vests/index.html" date="2018-12-04" labels="politics, Trump retweets apparently false claim of Paris protesters chanting - CNNPolitics" title="Trump retweets apparently false claim of Paris protesters chanting - CNNPolitics" >
Washington (CNN)
President Donald Trump on Tuesday retweeted conservative activist Charlie Kirk, who claimed that protesters on the streets of Paris are chanting "we want Trump" but a corresponding video appears to show London.
No video was included in Kirk's tweet but one circulating among Trump-supporting social media accounts appears to be shot in Trafalgar Square in London. The police in the video are English, an English flag is visible during the start of the video, and the blue, double-decker bus in the shot appears to be 
operated by a company
 that does sightseeing tours of London. 
But Kirk, whom Trump retweeted, wrote: "There are riots in socialist France because of radical leftist fuel taxes. Media barely mentioning this. America is booming, Europe is burning. They want to cover up the middle class rebellion against cultural Marxism. 'We want Trump' being chanted through the streets of Paris." 
There are riots in socialist France because of radical leftist fuel taxes
Media barely mentioning this
America is booming, Europe is burning 
They want to cover up the middle class rebellion against cultural Marxism
"We want Trump" being chanted through the streets of Paris
— Charlie Kirk (@charliekirk11) 
December 4, 2018


The White House did not respond to a CNN request for comment.
In France, the rising cost of fuel has sparked protests that have evolved into broader demonstrations against French President Emmanuel Macron's government. Violent demonstrations by protesters, known as the "gilets jaunes" or "yellow vests," in Paris over the last few weeks has killed at least two people and injured more than 600. On Tuesday, the French government 
agreed to suspend planned fuel price
 hikes. 
Read More
CNN reporters and producers covering the unrest who have been on the streets of Paris with the protesters during the past couple of weeks have seen no evidence to suggest Kirk's assertion is true. 
Conservative radio show host Rush Limbaugh made a similar -- apparently unfounded -- claim on Monday. 
"You know what's been overheard in some of the cheering over there? I kid you not. I know friends who are there. There are some people wearing the yellow vests chanting, 'We want Trump' among the rioters in Paris,"
 Limbaugh said
. 
Trump's retweet came after a series of tweets regarding trade negotiations with China and as former President George H.W. Bush's body continues to lie in state at the US Capitol.
CNN's Abby Phillip, Richard Greene, Stephen Collinson, Euan McKirdy and Saskya Vandoorne contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/17/opinions/where-threat-to-free-expression-lies-maltby/index.html" date="2019-01-17" labels="opinions, Where the threat to free speech really lies (opinion) - CNN" title="Where the threat to free speech really lies (opinion) - CNN" >
Kate Maltby is a broadcaster and columnist in the United Kingdom on issues of culture and politics, and a theater critic for The Guardian. She is also completing a doctorate in Renaissance literature. The views expressed in this commentary are her own. View more 
opinion articles
 on CNN.
 (CNN)
Something nasty is happening on the grounds of London's Palace of Westminster. And I don't mean the latest horse-trading over Prime Minister Theresa May's Brexit legislation. 
No, the latest crisis to hit Britain's political culture manifests in a much more tangible form. In recent weeks, an upsurge of "anti-elitist" protest has seen the violent harassment of members of Parliament and commentators while they film interviews outside Parliament. The activity is focused on a public strip of park, known as "College Green," which lies just a few steps outside the main gates of the Houses of Parliament and is traditionally used for broadcast interviews. 
Kate Maltby
The result: Freedom of expression in the heart of British democracy is under threat. And the question that faces the British people is how we censor political expression that seeks to deny other people that same right to political expression. 
Last week, the anti-Brexit Conservative MP Anna Soubry was surrounded and jostled by men
 as she attempted
 to film a BBC interview. They then deliberately drowned out the interview with chants of "scum" and "Nazi." The left-wing activist Owen Jones, who is gay, 
has been subjected
 to similar attacks while broadcasting in public, with the addition of homophobic slurs like "rent boy" and even "tampon."  
The protesters, who
 have named themselves
 Yellow Vests UK after the French "gilets jaunes" movement, appear to particularly target women, racial minorities and gay men. They attack not only politicians, but also journalists whom they perceive as part of an aloof elite. Kay Burley, the most prominent female anchor for Sky News, 
has tweeted
 that she now requires a security escort to do her job at Westminster. "These people are not pro-Brexit. They are pro-intimidation," she said. 
Anna Soubry filmed being abused by far-right activists on the way to Parliament.
Read More
Why should any of this matter to any of us? There are two reasons -- two ways in which this latest attack on democratic values echoes a global trend. 
The first is that -- as in the White House, where President Donald Trump
 has tightened restrictions
 on the press corps, and 
as in much of the rest of the world 
-- populist attacks on "fake news" and journalistic "elites" are now directly restricting the capacity of journalists to do their jobs and report the news. In London, broadcasters 
are considering
 moving their political reports away from the public spaces around Westminster and into the security-fortified grounds of Parliament itself. It seems to be the only way to allow politicians to be interviewed without their words being drowned out -- and until then, a number of female MPs are known to be turning down interview requests due to fears for their safety. If that seems wimpish, bear in mind that their colleague Jo Cox was killed in broad daylight two years ago by an unstable far-right extremist, who shouted "Britain first" as he mowed her down.
But if the press corps retreats further into the physical confines of the Palace of Westminster, they'll no longer be as freely able to set up debate between politicians and ordinary members of the public. You need to have a hard-won security pass to access these areas -- younger, less established press outfits and civilian experts won't be able to enter with ease. No one is served if politicians refuse to engage outside the walls of Westminster. Ironically, the impact of these anti-elite protests may be to deepen the physical divide between political elites and the people -- not to bridge them.
What we don't get about the far right 
The second problem is the way these British "yellow vests" have managed to frame this story as a threat to their own freedom of expression. Note the use of the word "Nazi" to attack Soubry, a centrist politician who couldn't be less like a Nazi if she tried. Perhaps this particular insult simply stems from many British people's long suspicion of the EU as a German expansionist project -- and therefore Soubry, a pro-EU politician, as some kind of Germanic stooge. 
The London Times cartoonist Peter Brookes 
summed it up
 well this week when he published a cartoon showing a mob of swastika-clad, jackbooted brownshirts chanting "You Effing Nazi" while pointing at Soubry. But there's more to this than an ironic swap of political labels. 
One Twitter account 
challenging Soubry
 this weekend read: "@Anna_Soubry those nasty words you deem arrestable offences work both ways, i object to being called a yob and far right for loving my country, those words hurt me ! #cutsbothways #patriotismnotracism." Whatever liberals like myself think of these people's politics, it's clear that they have come to hear the words "Nazi" or "racist" as terms elites use to exclude them from the bounds of legitimate civic discourse. Now, they're finally turning that term back on the elites, in the hope it will work as effectively.
Free speech doesn't come in zones
Neither the British press nor American commentators have helped. MPs have asked Westminster's policing unit to be more proactive about policing their physical safety. And yet a headline from the Times simplified that situation as such: "Police stood by as protesters called me a Nazi, says Tory MP Anna Soubry." 
In turn, the usually sharp authors of the US law-oriented blog Popehat
 tweeted
 their freedom of speech concerns: "Yeah, I think it's a good thing that you can call a politician a Nazi, and a good thing if police don't try to stop it." This is part of a larger trend, thoroughly at play in the USA: far-right activists persuading commentators to present themselves as the victimized party, even as they attempt to shut down their own opponents' speech rights.
So, how should we react? In the first place, we start by enforcing pre-existing laws against physical harassment and verbal incitement to violence. But we also need to ask questions about what views are acceptable to voice in the public sphere -- and what it means to enforce that. The philosopher Karl Popper described a "paradox of tolerance," where speech is free right up until citizens call for an end to that free speech. Or, 
as he put it 
in 1945, "in order to maintain a tolerant society, the society must be intolerant of intolerance." 
Stay up to date...
Sign up for our new 
newsletter
.
Join us on 
Twitter 
and 
Facebook
 But even if we shun or refuse a platform to those who reject free speech themselves, no Western society is rightly going to criminalize any political expression that stops short of inciting violence. We do better to avoid patronizing those with anti-liberal views -- and to demonstrate that we apply Popper's approach evenhandedly. 
The BBC's Asian Network has held debates for British Muslims
 such as
 "What is the right punishment for blasphemy?" This should be as unacceptable as it would be to debate the merits of violence against MPs. If Western liberals want to convert populists, we should be as quick to condemn anti-liberalism from minorities as we are from white nationalists. We should be clear about the limits of tolerance, without dehumanizing those who still think differently. 
But when they start trying to interrupt live political programming, we can be clear about where the threat to freedom of expression really lies.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/11/europe/france-macron-yellow-vests-populism-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-11" labels="europe, Macron vowed to fight the populists. Now France's president is being engulfed by them - CNN" title="Macron vowed to fight the populists. Now France's president is being engulfed by them - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
When French President Emmanuel Macron won the presidential election in May 2017, beating Marine Le Pen, the leader of France's far-right National Front, the markets heaved a sigh of relief.
The populist wave that had led the United Kingdom to vote to leave the European Union and that propelled Donald Trump to the White House appeared to have been stopped -- at least in France.  
Macron embraced this victory and presented himself as the new leader of the free world: a champion of a newly unfashionable multilateralist, globalist vision. 
Having changed the French political landscape with his candidacy, which he ran on the independent ticket "En Marche," Macron promised to fix Europe, fight climate change, stand up to the US and take on the populists gaining ground elsewhere in the EU.
So it is perhaps surprising that he should have been so slow to see the populist threat growing from within. 
Read More
As the "gilets jaunes" or, "yellow vests" began appearing at roundabouts and toll booths around the country in early November, the government seemed deaf to the 
growing rumble of discontent
. The protests -- named for the yellow high-visibility jackets French motorists must carry in their vehicles -- began as a reaction to an eco-tax on gas but have since morphed into a much more political protest against Macron.
Even after some 282,000 people took the streets at the first mass yellow vest protest on November 17, it seemed that Macron had neither a clear strategy on what to do, nor even a grasp of the looming crisis.
Tax rises, yellow vests and a gold desk: Emmanuel Macron's humbling year
This reinforced the sense of a president out of touch with the common citizen, one insensitive to their plight. 
As one political analyst, Alexis Poulain, told me at the time: "Macron is the ultimate technocrat. He is at home in Davos. But here you have a man used to talking about millions of Euros, trying to listen to those counting in centimes. It cannot work."
Especially when those who count in centimes are suddenly calling the shots. 
After weeks of protests that turned violent, Macron eventually introduced some concessions. First, a cancellation of the tax increase that had sparked the movement. Then, a 10 billion Euro (approximately US $11.5 billion) package of social reforms, including an increase in the minimum wage, aimed at helping the purchasing power of those least well-off. 
But by then the damage was done.
The 
yellow vest movement
, having felt it was being ignored, now felt it was winning. So why stop? 
Last Saturday, on the first weekend of 2019, the numbers of yellow vest protestors demonstrating on the streets were back up from the week prior, a suggestion that the yellow vests aren't done yet.
But while the movement has stayed strong, it has changed in its focus and is now looking to change in its form. 
From a fiscal revolt, to a battle over spending power, the yellow vest movement is now calling for more power to be given to "the people" through mass popular votes or "referenda d'initiative citoyenne" (RIC). 
Emmanuel Macron was anointed as France's last great hope for reform. Is that all lost now?
Next week, in yet another concession toward 
the protesters
, Macron will send a letter to the public, outlining the themes of a big national debate. 
The topics of that debate will span from spending power to the functioning of the institutions and climate change initiatives.
But even before that debate begins, the government has already ruled out a U-turn on Macron's reform agenda or institutional reform. 
So, what can emerge if not dissatisfaction with the debate, argue some observers of French politics who warn of the dangers involved in the process itself.
By placing himself in a dialogue with "the people," they say, Macron -- having already destabilized France's representative democracy by the very nature of his candidacy -- risks now taking on a mob that could yet force the dissolution of parliament and a set of legislative elections.  
Meanwhile, some yellow vests have already decided to go into politics themselves, and are now preparing candidacy lists for the European elections this May. An Ipsos poll, ordered by Macron's party, showed those candidates could potentially win about 12% of the vote, mainly at the expense of the far-right and far-left.
Macron has long warned that he expects that poll to be decisive to the future of Europe. 
Le Pen's far-right party 
is currently leading voting intentions in France. Other European populists, many of them Eurosceptics, are also expected to do well in May's election.
Now, another populist force looks set to enter the European Parliament, becoming a new force and feature of the political landscape in France.
Far from putting an end to the populist wave, Macron appears to have overseen its expansion.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/02/07/europe/france-italy-ambassador-recalled-intl/index.html" date="2019-02-07" labels="europe, France recalls Italy ambassador over 'unprecedented' and 'repeated' criticism - CNN" title="France recalls Italy ambassador over 'unprecedented' and 'repeated' criticism - CNN" >
 (CNN)
France has recalled its ambassador from Italy for consultations over "unprecedented" and "repeated" criticism by Italian officials, the French foreign ministry said in a statement Thursday. 
"For several months, France has been the target of repeated criticism, baseless attacks and outrageous declarations that everyone knows about," it said.
"This is unprecedented since the end of the war. To have disagreements is one thing, to exploit the relationship for electoral aims is another."
In the statement, Paris said the criticisms "create a serious situation that questions the intentions of the Italian government with regards to its relationship to France."
The decision to recall the ambassador comes one day after a spokeswoman for the French foreign ministry said it was "unacceptable" that Italian Deputy Prime Minister Luigi di Maio met with France's 
yellow vest anti-government protesters. 
Leader of Italy's populist Five Star Movement Luigi Di Maio inflamed tensions between France and Italy after meeting French anti-government  protesters.
Read More
"This latest provocation is unacceptable between neighbors and EU partners," the foreign ministry spokeswoman said, adding that di Maio "must be careful not to undermine our bilateral relationship through repeated acts of interference."
Di Maio posted a picture of him in France with
 "gilets jaunes" 
leader Christophe Chalençon and European parliament election candidate Ingrid Levavasseur, and said that "the wind of change has crossed the Alps."
Oggi con 
@ale_dibattista
 abbiamo fatto un salto in Francia e abbiamo incontrato il leader dei gilet gialli Cristophe Chalençon e i candidati alle elezioni europee della lista RIC di Ingrid Levavasseur.
Il vento del cambiamento ha valicato le Alpi. 
pic.twitter.com/G8E0ypLalX
— Luigi Di Maio (@luigidimaio) 
February 5, 2019


The war of words between the two countries began last summer, when French President Emmanuel Macron warned that populism was "spreading like leprosy." Italian Interior Minister Matteo Salvini hit back in January, calling Macron a "very bad president" and saying that he was to blame for the yellow vest protests.
CNN's Gianluca Mezzofiore contributed to this story.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/03/16/europe/france-protest-yellow-vest/index.html" date="2019-03-16" labels="europe, Protests continue in France as demonstrators clash with police - CNN" title="Protests continue in France as demonstrators clash with police - CNN" >
 (CNN)
Sixty people, including 17 police officers and a fireman, were slightly injured on the 18th straight Saturday of yellow vest demonstrations in Paris.
Protests turned violent as police used water cannons and tear gas to disperse the crowd. Protesters threw rocks and set up barricades.
A spokesman for Paris police said 192 people were being held for questioning. The Paris prosecutor's office said 64 have been placed in custody.
Protesters torched a branch of the Tarneaud bank, a spokesperson for Paris firefighters said. Firefighters evacuated the building and put out the blaze.
Yellow vest protesters fan flames of anti-Semitism in France
On the Champs-Élysées, stores and restaurant windows were shattered and a newspaper stand was set on fire. Fouquet's, the restaurant where former President Nicolas Sarkozy celebrated his election in May 2007, was among the vandalized establishments.
Read More
The restaurant's windows were smashed, its awning burned and its insides wrecked. Protesters used spray paint to write "Sarkozy has broken everything" on the restaurant's outside wall.
Fouquet's restaurant on the Champs-Élysées in Paris was heavily damaged in the yellow vest protests Saturday.
"No doubt: they are calling for violence and are here to wreak havoc," French Interior Minister Christophe Castaner tweeted Saturday as the clashes unfolded. "Professionals of damage and disorder, equipped and masked, have infiltrated the protests. My instruction to the police: Respond very firmly to these unacceptable attacks."
The 
"gilets jaunes"
 or yellow vest protests began as a campaign against a gas tax hike, but have morphed into a broader rally against President Emmanuel Macron's government.
French Prime Minister Edouard Philippe, during an interview with CNN affiliate BFM on Saturday, said those who "excuse or encourage" the ongoing protests are "complicit." 
Philippe said authorities are working to ensure those responsible will be "put before the tribunal and be severely punished." 
"Our objective is one of total firmness," Philippe said, adding that there are thousands of "very determined people who are there to create disorder and to commit the acts I have just denounced."
CNN's Arnaud Siad contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/19/europe/macron-great-debate-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-19" labels="europe, Gilets jaunes protests: Macron struggles to keep up - CNN" title="Gilets jaunes protests: Macron struggles to keep up - CNN" >
Bourgtheroulde, France (CNN)
I'm sure you've heard the old bromide attributed to Charles de Gaulle, who wondered how it was possible to govern a country like France, with its 246 different kinds of cheese. 
These days, Emmanuel Macron is discovering the complexity de Gaulle was talking about as he confronts the myriad demands of his constituents in an effort to mollify the "gilets jaunes," or "yellow vest" movement. 
He's calling it Le Grand Débat -- the Great Debate. A chance over the next two months for everyone in France to get their gripes off their chests. 
Macron vowed to fight the populists. Now he's being engulfed by them
Shortly before Macron's visit to Normandy to launch Le Grand Débat, I received a lecture on "individualism" from a yellow-vested protester at a roundabout known colorfully as the Rond-Point des Vaches -- the Roundabout of Cows. (A side note: in France, "la vache!" is a mild curse, as well as a metaphor for obedient taxpayers who are constantly being pushed around and milked). 
"No one is in charge here," protester Olivier Bruneau, a 42-year-old factory worker, told me. "But everyone has a reason for joining in the movement." Welcome to Normandy.
Read More
The Rond-Point des Vaches has been occupied continuously from the very beginning of the Yellow Vest movement by "individualists" huddled around burning piles of wooden transport pallets. Each has a slightly different set of reasons for being here.  
As Denis Lacorne, senior research fellow at the prestigious Sciences Po, told me, "The Yellow Vest protests create a kind of artificial, but real, solidarity among protesters. They're isolated in their rural settings and suddenly they meet people like them, make friends and have a good time."
A car driver shows his yellow vest to cheer protesters as French President Emmanuel Macron visits Normandy on Tuesday.
Why here? I asked Bruneau. Well, he patiently explained, it is a place of maximum visibility for trucks passing from the coast through Normandy to other parts of France and Europe -- traffic that the protesters can easily block from time to time, creating impressive traffic jams.  
And as the protesters wreak havoc, they also spread the movement by explaining to one driver after another how aggrieved they are ... and encouraging them to put their own yellow safety vests in the windows of their cabs in solidarity. This is one protest that is wonderfully easy to join -- take out the safety vest everyone is obliged to have in their vehicle and the movement spreads.
What's more, who could be against a movement in which the chief complaint is the decline in buying power? Is there anyone in France who could be in favor of that?  And few would disagree that the 
far-off Paris government
 seems indifferent to the financial plight of those in the countryside. The response from the top has been slow -- and, some say, condescending. "Let them eat cake" had its origins here, after all. 
France's Emmanuel Macron calls for respect and unity in New Year's speech
President Macron chose Bourgtheroulde, a small town of 3,800 inhabitants, just down the road from Le Rond-Point des Vaches to kick off his Great Debate. 
It was the start of two months of talking over the concerns of the little guy; the President hoping, perhaps, to head off further protests by either addressing or appearing to address these concerns. Two months to search for a national consensus. And in spite -- or, perhaps, because -- of that individualism Bruneau talked about, the French are masters at building consensus. 
You see it everywhere, from the town hall to the workplace. If you want things to move along smoothly, you don't just issue orders from the top down but patiently find agreement and commonality from the bottom up.    
This was the reason for the trip to Normandy, the reason the President met with the local mayors, who are more in touch with those on the ground and in the streets. For centuries before anyone ever conceived of Le Grand Débat, mayors in France have maintained "complaint books" in their town halls so average citizens could come in and write down what's bugging them.  
Mayors have collected thousands of different grievances since the Yellow Vest movement began and many brought them along to share with Macron. 
The President came to listen -- perhaps because he knows that, in France, when you give everybody a chance to express themselves, it is much more difficult for them to later turn around and disown the collective decisions. They become part of a consensus built by the President rather than one constructed by the yellow vests.  
The only problem for Macron is that in France these days there are at least as many complaints as there are cheeses.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/07/europe/france-protests-police-officer-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-07" labels="europe, Gilets Jaunes: Police investigate reports of officer filmed punching protester - CNN" title="Gilets Jaunes: Police investigate reports of officer filmed punching protester - CNN" >
 (CNN)
French police are investigating reports that a highly decorated officer threw punches at protesters during yellow vest demonstrations over the weekend.
A 
video widely circulated on social media 
appears to show policeman
 
Didier Andrieux, who was awarded the Legion of Honor -- the country's highest accolade -- approaching a protester standing against a wall before punching him repeatedly. In the video, allegedly filmed in Toulon on Saturday, the police officer then approached other Gilets Jaunes protesters and punched them.
🔴 Un policier filmé en train de frapper à mains nus des manifestants à Toulon lors de là manifestations des 
#GiletsJaunes
 dont l'un très violemment contre un mur 
pic.twitter.com/bnG5JtsWpq
— Stéphane Larue (@larueofficiel) 
January 5, 2019


A spokeswoman for the national police told CNN that Andrieux had been sanctioned in the past for "violent behavior" and that an investigation has been opened into his actions.
The prefect of Var, the region where the alleged attack took place, tweeted that he has asked for an investigation. "As part of my administrative responsibilities, I have asked the IGPN (Inspection Générale de la Police Nationale) for an investigation to shed light on the suspicion of police violence in #Toulon," tweeted Jean-Luc Videlaine.
06/01/2019 : « Dans le cadre de mes responsabilités administratives, j'ai saisi l'IGPN afin qu'une enquête permette de faire toute la lumière sur les suspicions de violences policières à 
#Toulon
. » Jean-Luc Videlaine, préfet du 
#Var
. 
pic.twitter.com/aNNxUfS1gn
— Préfet du Var (@Prefet83) 
January 6, 2019
Meanwhile, a separate video went viral after another man was caught on camera throwing punches at French riot police on Saturday in Paris.
He was later identified as a former professional boxer. 
Read More
Wearing all black, the man jumped over a barrier and repeatedly punched officers as they shielded themselves.
A puño limpio hicieron retroceder a la policía en Francia: 
En una nueva jornada de protesta de los 
, mientras la policía reprimía en el puente peatonal Leopold-Sedar-Senghor, París, un boxeador (identificado como Christophe Dettinger) ayudó a repeler la represión 👊🏽 
pic.twitter.com/dA6ZK6zZ8Y
— Vagabundo ilustrado (@vagoilustrado) 
Interior Minister Christophe Castaner tweeted Monday that "the individual who violently attacked the policemen on the Senghor footbridge on Saturday has turned himself in to Paris investigators."
L'individu qui a violemment attaqué samedi des gendarmes mobiles sur la passerelle Senghor s'est présenté aux enquêteurs de la sûreté territoriale de Paris.
Il a été immédiatement placé en garde à vue et devra répondre de ses actes devant la Justice.
— Christophe Castaner (@CCastaner) 
January 7, 2019
Castaner described the attack "cowardly and intolerable" and praised the police for staying calm.
On Monday the boxer identified himself as Christophe Dettinger in a video posted
 on Facebook
 and said he was defending himself.
"I was the person who faced the riot police on Saturday, January 5. I wanted to explain things my way," he said.
"I love my country and I am patriotic. But, after being hit again and again, I was also gassed on the last day," Dettinger added. "Yes, the anger started building and I reacted badly. But I defended myself."
The French Boxing Federation called the behavior "unacceptable and shameful."
The Federation, as well as the National Professional Boxing League, "strongly condemns such acts of extreme violence that are totally contrary to the values ​​advocated by our discipline," the federation said in a statement.
Gilets jaunes
Unrest erupted across France on Saturday in the latest Gilets Jaunes, or "yellow vest," protests.  Around 50,000 people demonstrated, Castaner said. Large gatherings were held in Paris, Bordeaux and Marseilles.
'Yellow vest' protests across France trigger spurts of violence, calls for calm
The protests are named after the yellow high-visibility jackets French motorists must carry in their vehicles.
They have morphed from dissent over rising gas prices and eco-taxes into a broader demonstration against President Emmanuel Macron and his government, and tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor.
In December, Macron pledged to increase the minimum wage and get rid of new pension taxes, a move that didn't appease the anger of some of the protesters.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/05/europe/france-yellow-vest-protests-intl/index.html" date="2018-12-05" labels="europe, France protests: Fuel tax hike won't happen in 2019 - CNN" title="France protests: Fuel tax hike won't happen in 2019 - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
French President Emmanuel Macron backed down again Wednesday in the face of nationwide protests against his government, with a spokeswoman for his office saying  planned fuel tax increases will not be introduced in 2019.
His Prime Minister, Edouard Philippe, 
announced a day earlier that the tax hike would be delayed
 by six months, from January 1 to midyear, so this pushes the tax increase that sparked protests back at least another six months.
France announces postponement of tax hikes
The rising cost of gasoline and diesel fuel sparked protests that have since evolved into broader demonstrations against Macron's government, exposing tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor. 
The protesters, known as the "gilets jaunes," take their name from the high-visibility yellow vests that drivers are required to keep in their vehicles for safety reasons.
Macron had asked political leaders to meet the protest organizers this week
. However, two protesters who claim to lead the group, Benjamin Cauchy and Jacqueline Moreau, have pulled out of a meeting with Prime Minister Philippe planned for Tuesday,
 
according to the movement's spokesman, Maxime Nicole.
Read More
 Photos:
In photos: Protests in France
A yellow vest demonstrator faces riot police officers in Marseille, France, on Saturday, January 5, 2019.
Hide Caption
 1 of 39
Riot police stand in tear gas in Toulouse, France, during a protest January 5.
 2 of 39
Yellow vest protestors kneel in Lyon on January 5. About 50,000 people demonstrated throughout France on Saturday, according to Interior Minister Christophe Castaner.
 3 of 39
Protesters warm their hands over a burning tree in a Paris street on January 5.
 4 of 39
A firefighter tries to extinguish a burning car in a street in Paris on January 5.
 5 of 39
Protesters confront police during a "yellow vest" demonstration Saturday, December 22, in central Paris.
 6 of 39
Demonstrators rally in the Montmartre area of Paris on December 22.
 7 of 39
Protesters block a highway near the French border with Spain on December 22 in Biriatou, France.
 8 of 39
Demonstators turn out December 22 near toll booths on the A9 highway in Le Boulou, France.
 9 of 39
Protesters gather December 15 at Place de l'Opera in Paris.
 10 of 39
Activists dressed like Marianne, the symbol of the French Republic, face riot police on December 15 in Paris.
 11 of 39
Demonstrators wearing yellow vests form a human tower December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 12 of 39
A police water cannon sprays demonstrators on December 15 in Paris.
 13 of 39
Protesters take part in a demonstration on December 15 in Paris.
 14 of 39
Demonstrators run through tear gas during scuffles with police December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 15 of 39
Police use tear gas on protesters at the Place de l'Opera in Paris on December 15.
 16 of 39
A protester waves the French national flag during a demonstration on the Champs-Élysées in Paris on December 15.
 17 of 39
French police apprehend a man on December 8 during a protest in Paris.
 18 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests gather on December 8 in front of the Eiffel Tower in Paris.
 19 of 39
Demonstrators drop flat to the ground on the Champs-Elysees avenue during a protest on Saturday, December 8, in Paris. 
 20 of 39
Protesters install a barricade during clashes with police at a demonstration in Paris on December 8.
 21 of 39
Protesters gather on December 8 in Paris.
 22 of 39
A demonstrator is covered in blood after getting in injured during a protest in Paris on December 8.
 23 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests walk on the Champs-Elysees Avenue with the Arc de Triomphe in the background during a protest on December 8.
 24 of 39
Two demonstrators dance in front a group as they take part on December 8 in the demonstration at the Arc de Triomphe in Paris.
 25 of 39
A protester reacts during clashes with police on December 8 in Paris.
 26 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester on December 8 in Paris.
 27 of 39
Protesters throw objects at riot police on Saturday, December 1, during a demonstration that turned violent when protestors clashed with police in Paris.
 28 of 39
An injured woman sits on the ground as police officers spray yellow vest protesters with tear gas during a protest in Paris on December 1.
 29 of 39
A burned car is left in the street a day after the  yellow vests demonstration against rising oil prices and living costs in Paris on December 1.
 30 of 39
Firemen work to extinguish a burning car on December 1.
 31 of 39
A demonstrator leaves as water cannons evacuate the Place de l'Etoile on December 1.
 32 of 39
A demonstrator watches a burning car near the Champs-Elysees avenue on December 1.
 33 of 39
Riot police officers stand in position during clashes with demonstrators on December 1.
 34 of 39
Protesters and police clash in downtown Paris on December 1 during a national demonstration.
 35 of 39
Hooded demonstrators smash a car.
 36 of 39
A demonstrator throws a projectile during the December 1 protest.
 37 of 39
A demonstrator treats a wounded man during a protest where police and demonstrators clashed, injuring dozens on December 1.
 38 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester in Paris on December 1.
 39 of 39
Philippe canceled a trip to the COP24 climate conference in Poland to address the issue, which had threatened to flare again this coming weekend.
The government is likely hoping the suspension of the fuel hikes will take some heat out of the protests, which brought an estimated 36,000 people onto the streets of France on Saturday alone.
"Gilets jaunes" protesters at the Champs Elysees in Paris on Saturday
Around 400 people were arrested after a violent minority turned on police, throwing projectiles and vandalizing statues. 
Paris prosecutor Remy Heitz said that among the protesters were people from across the country who had descended upon Paris with the express intent of causing trouble. 
He added that authorities would crack down hardest on those who had joined the street demonstrations explicitly to carry out violent acts.
The cost of diesel has surged 16% this year from an average €1.24 ($1.41) per liter to €1.48 ($1.69), even hitting €1.53 ($1.74) in October, according to UFIP, France's oil industry federation.
CNN's Saskya Vandoorne reported from Paris, Euan McKirdy wrote from Hong Kong and Angela Dewan and Bianca Britton contributed from London. Steve Almasy contributed from Atlanta. 
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/10/europe/gilets-jaunes-speed-cameras-destroyed-france-scli-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-10" labels="europe, Gilets jaunes protesters have vandalized 60% of France's speed cameras - CNN" title="Gilets jaunes protesters have vandalized 60% of France's speed cameras - CNN" >
 (CNN)
Close to two-thirds of France's fixed speed cameras have been vandalized by yellow-vest protesters since November, as demonstrators revolt against lowered speed limits introduced by the government last year. 
A spokesman for the French Ministry of the Interior told CNN that 60% of fixed speed cameras have been damaged by gilets jaunes demonstrators since November 17, when the protests erupted. 
"I saw on social networks a few fools who appear next to burnt speed cameras. I do not wish for them to one day face the reality of a death on the road. It's not about figures, it's about life," Interior Minister Christophe Castaner told reporters Thursday. 
Emmanuel Barbe, the head of France's road safety agency, also warned that vandalism of the country's speed cameras will likely lead to more deaths. "This damage to the speed camera network... will lead to deaths. And that makes me profoundly sad," he told France Inter. 
Many protesters are angry at the French government's decision in 2018 to reduce the speed limit on two-lane highways to 80 km/h.
According to the French site 
radars-auto.com
, the proportion of cameras damaged by protesters could be as high as 65%.
Read More
French news agency Europe 1 estimated in December that around half of all speed cameras in France had been put out of service for either a short or long period of time, while close to 300 devices had been completely destroyed -- in most cases after being burnt. Other devices have been spray-painted or covered in film. 
In some departments including the Vaucluse in southeast France, upward of 90% of speed cameras were put out of service following protests in November and December. 
The French government's road safety association, Sécurité routière, previously refused to release official statistics on the precise number of speed cameras that had been affected during the protests. The organization has not responded to a CNN request for comment. 
This spike in vandalism is seen as a response to the French government's controversial decision in July 2018 to lower speed limits to 80 kilometers per hour (50 miles per hour) from 90 kilometers per hour (56 miles per hour) on two-lane highways in a bid to reduce a sharp rise in road deaths. 
The change affects 40% of France's road network, and around 250,000 miles of roads. The French government indicated that the measure could help avoid between 350 and 400 road deaths a year. 
"Unsafe roads are not inevitable," Prime Minister Édouard Philippe said in 2018. "Lowering speed reduces the number of accidents, as well as the severity of these accidents." 
He also told the Journal du Dimanche newspaper: "There are 3,500 deaths and 70,000 injured each year -- 70,000! After decades of progress, the toll is getting worse." 
French police investigate reports of decorated officer filmed punching protesters
Many people around the country have nevertheless revolted against the speed limit reduction, and it formed a key trigger for the roundabout blockades that brought France's road network to a halt at the height of the yellow-vest protests. 
"The outcry is strong because it is such a tangible issue for ordinary people," Jérôme Fourquet from the Ifop polling agency told the BBC. "Around 70% of the population is opposed, and there is no sign of that abating." 
The ensuing damage to France's speed cameras is costing road agencies and local councils millions of euros. The cost of repairing speed cameras ranges from 500 euros ($574) for minor damage, up to between 60,000 euros ($69,000) and 80,000 euros for the cost of totally replacing a device, according to the French business magazine Capital. 
France also faces the loss of billions of euros worth of revenue derived from speeding fines.
Protesters found guilty of vandalizing or destroying speed cameras face fines of up to 75,000 euros and prison sentences of up to five years.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/05/europe/france-protests/index.html" date="2019-01-05" labels="europe, Thousands take to streets across France in 'yellow vest' protests - CNN" title="Thousands take to streets across France in 'yellow vest' protests - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
French authorities appealed for calm on Saturday as spurts of unrest erupted across France in the latest gilets jaunes, or "yellow vest," protests.
About 50,000 people demonstrated, according to Interior Minister Christophe Castaner. Large gatherings were held in Paris, Bordeaux and Marseilles.
In Paris, 3,500 people participated in protests on Saturday, much higher than the 800 who took to the streets last week, police said. At least 34 people were taken in for questioning in the capital city.
Benjamin Griveaux, government spokesman, confirmed that he and his team had to evacuate his office in Paris after demonstrators broke into his courtyard by knocking down the door with construction machinery.
A protester in Marseille holds a flare in front of the town hall.
Violence was reported in Montpellier and Troyes, where demonstrators tried to enter prefectures, and in Avignon, where some attempted to break into the Court of Justice. Violence was also reported in Beauvais, authorities said.
Read More
The protests are named after the yellow high-visibility jackets French motorists must carry in their vehicles.
They have morphed from dissent over rising gas prices and eco-taxes into a broader demonstration against President Emmanuel Macron and his government, and tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor.
France's Emmanuel Macron calls for respect and unity in New Year's speech
"I call on everybody to be responsible and respect the rule of law," Castaner said on Twitter.
Castaner said he gathered local police officials for a video conference "as tensions and violence have been witnessed in Paris and in a few other cities."
Last weekend, an estimated 32,000 protesters took to the streets. There have been some protests since the year began but mostly they have been modest demonstrations on roads and roundabouts.
Saturday's protests are the first big gatherings of the year.
A government under pressure
In his New Year's address, Macron made reference to the "yellow vest" movement without naming it.
Tax rises, yellow vests and a gold desk: Emmanuel Macron's humbling year
He acknowledged anger against injustice but said hateful speech would not be tolerated. Macron said France "wants to build a better future" while imploring people to respect each other.
In December, Macron pledged to increase the minimum wage and get rid of new pension taxes, a move that didn't appease the anger of some of the protesters.
Ten people have died in connection with the protests, with most deaths taking place in traffic accidents related to blockades in November and December.
CNN's Katie Polglase wrote from London while Joe Sterling wrote from Atlanta.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/02/21/europe/macron-anti-semitism-france-crackdown-intl/index.html" date="2019-02-21" labels="europe, Emmanuel Macron says anti-Semitism at worst levels since WWII - CNN" title="Emmanuel Macron says anti-Semitism at worst levels since WWII - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
French President Emmanuel Macron has announced a crackdown on the "scourge" of anti-Semitism, days after 
protesters held rallies against a rise 
in anti-Semitic incidents across the country.
Speaking to leaders of the Jewish community in Paris on Wednesday evening, Macron criticized a "resurgence of anti-Semitism unseen since World War II," which he said is not only happening in France but in "all of Europe and most Western democracies."
The president added that "anti-Zionism is one of the modern forms of anti-Semitism," and in response, France will adopt the International Holocaust Remembrance Alliance's 
definition of anti-Semitism
. 
French Interior Minister Christophe Castaner is also taking measures to ban three anti-Semitic and far-right groups which the president said "fueled hatred."   
Protesters rally against anti-Semitism in France after more graves vandalized
France's Minister of Education will investigate cases of Jewish children who are "too often forced" to leave public schools for private Jewish schools because of harassment, Macron said. 
Read More
This comes amid a recent rise in anti-Semitic incidents. France, which is home to Europe's largest Jewish community, saw a 74% increase in such acts in 2018, of 541 incidents compared to 311 the year before, according to authorities. 
On Saturday, 
several gilets jaunes (or "yellow vest") protesters
 were filmed hurling abuse at philosopher and vocal Israel supporter Alain Finkielkraut as he ran into protesters during the 14th consecutive weekend of marches.
Insults including "dirty Zionist," "f***ing Islamophobe" and "f*** your mother" were hurled at Finkelkraut, while less hostile activists walked him away from the demonstration and behind police lines.
Spate of anti-Semitic vandalism hits Paris amid 74% rise in anti-Semitic acts
Tuesday's marches against anti-Semitism
 came after around 80 graves were desecrated with swastikas overnight in a Jewish cemetery in eastern France, according to local officials. Photos showed tombstones spray-painted with blue and yellow Nazi symbols and other graffiti.
Macron condemned the attack during his visit Tuesday to the cemetery in Quatzenheim, where he inspected the damage.
"We will take actions, we will use laws and we will punish," Macron told local communities leaders at the cemetery.
"Those who did this are not worthy of the republic ... France will punish them. I don't want what happened here to give ideas to others."
CNN's Bianca Britton contributed to this report
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/22/europe/france-yellow-vest-protest-intl/index.html" date="2018-12-22" labels="europe, 10th death linked to France's 'yellow vest' protests  - CNN" title="10th death linked to France's 'yellow vest' protests  - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
A 10th person has died in connection with the "gilets jaunes" or "yellow vest" protests in France as they enter their sixth consecutive weekend.
A 36-year-old man was killed in a road accident in the southern French city of Perpignan after encountering a blockade set up by "yellow vest" protesters late Friday night, according to a city spokeswoman.
"At a roundabout blocked by the gilets jaunes, a man in his car hit a truck in front of him. The driver of the car died," the spokeswoman said.
Most of the deaths occurred in traffic accidents related to blockades in November and December, according to Le Parisien newspaper and CNN reporting. Earlier this month, an 80-year-old woman died when a tear gas canister went through her window.
The protests -- named after the yellow high-visibility jackets French motorists must carry in their vehicles -- started November 17 in reaction to an eco-tax on gas but have since morphed into disparate demonstrations against President Emmanuel Macron.
Read More
Under pressure to respond, Macron pledged earlier this month to increase the minimum wage and scrap new pension taxes. But this move has done little to appease the anger felt by some hard-core protesters.
Protesters rally Saturday in the Montmartre area of Paris.
About 800 people marched Saturday in Paris, CNN French affiliate BFMTV reported, citing Paris police.
The number of demonstrators has dwindled over the past couple of weeks, while authorities have ramped up policing to prevent a repeat of 
earlier violence
.
By midafternoon on December 15, about 
34,000 protesters had turned out across France
, including more than 2,000 in Paris, according to the Interior Ministry. The previous week, some 77,000 protesters demonstrated across the country, including 10,000 in Paris.
CNN's Antoine Crouin reported from Paris, and Laura Smith-Spark wrote from London.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/04/europe/france-yellow-vest-protests-intl/index.html" date="2018-12-04" labels="europe, France protests: fuel price hike suspended after 'yellow vest' protests - CNN" title="France protests: fuel price hike suspended after 'yellow vest' protests - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
France will suspend fuel price hikes after ongoing protests turned violent over the weekend, in a major concession by President Emmanuel Macron's government. 
According to CNN affiliate BFMTV, Prime Minister Edouard Philippe will announce a moratorium Tuesday on fuel price hikes, which had been scheduled to come into effect on January 1.
The rising cost of gasoline and diesel fuel sparked protests that have since evolved into broader demonstrations against Macron's government, exposing tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor. 
The protesters, known as the "gilets jaunes," take their name from the high-visibility yellow vests that drivers are required to keep in their vehicles for safety reasons.
 Photos:
 
In photos: Protests in France
A yellow vest demonstrator faces riot police officers in Marseille, France, on Saturday, January 5, 2019.
Hide Caption
 1 of 39
Riot police stand in tear gas in Toulouse, France, during a protest January 5.
 2 of 39
Yellow vest protestors kneel in Lyon on January 5. About 50,000 people demonstrated throughout France on Saturday, according to Interior Minister Christophe Castaner.
 3 of 39
Protesters warm their hands over a burning tree in a Paris street on January 5.
 4 of 39
A firefighter tries to extinguish a burning car in a street in Paris on January 5.
 5 of 39
Protesters confront police during a "yellow vest" demonstration Saturday, December 22, in central Paris.
 6 of 39
Demonstrators rally in the Montmartre area of Paris on December 22.
 7 of 39
Protesters block a highway near the French border with Spain on December 22 in Biriatou, France.
 8 of 39
Demonstators turn out December 22 near toll booths on the A9 highway in Le Boulou, France.
 9 of 39
Protesters gather December 15 at Place de l'Opera in Paris.
 10 of 39
Activists dressed like Marianne, the symbol of the French Republic, face riot police on December 15 in Paris.
 11 of 39
Demonstrators wearing yellow vests form a human tower December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 12 of 39
A police water cannon sprays demonstrators on December 15 in Paris.
 13 of 39
Protesters take part in a demonstration on December 15 in Paris.
 14 of 39
Demonstrators run through tear gas during scuffles with police December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 15 of 39
Police use tear gas on protesters at the Place de l'Opera in Paris on December 15.
 16 of 39
A protester waves the French national flag during a demonstration on the Champs-Élysées in Paris on December 15.
 17 of 39
French police apprehend a man on December 8 during a protest in Paris.
 18 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests gather on December 8 in front of the Eiffel Tower in Paris.
 19 of 39
Demonstrators drop flat to the ground on the Champs-Elysees avenue during a protest on Saturday, December 8, in Paris. 
 20 of 39
Protesters install a barricade during clashes with police at a demonstration in Paris on December 8.
 21 of 39
Protesters gather on December 8 in Paris.
 22 of 39
A demonstrator is covered in blood after getting in injured during a protest in Paris on December 8.
 23 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests walk on the Champs-Elysees Avenue with the Arc de Triomphe in the background during a protest on December 8.
 24 of 39
Two demonstrators dance in front a group as they take part on December 8 in the demonstration at the Arc de Triomphe in Paris.
 25 of 39
A protester reacts during clashes with police on December 8 in Paris.
 26 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester on December 8 in Paris.
 27 of 39
Protesters throw objects at riot police on Saturday, December 1, during a demonstration that turned violent when protestors clashed with police in Paris.
 28 of 39
An injured woman sits on the ground as police officers spray yellow vest protesters with tear gas during a protest in Paris on December 1.
 29 of 39
A burned car is left in the street a day after the  yellow vests demonstration against rising oil prices and living costs in Paris on December 1.
 30 of 39
Firemen work to extinguish a burning car on December 1.
 31 of 39
A demonstrator leaves as water cannons evacuate the Place de l'Etoile on December 1.
 32 of 39
A demonstrator watches a burning car near the Champs-Elysees avenue on December 1.
 33 of 39
Riot police officers stand in position during clashes with demonstrators on December 1.
 34 of 39
Protesters and police clash in downtown Paris on December 1 during a national demonstration.
 35 of 39
Hooded demonstrators smash a car.
 36 of 39
A demonstrator throws a projectile during the December 1 protest.
 37 of 39
A demonstrator treats a wounded man during a protest where police and demonstrators clashed, injuring dozens on December 1.
 38 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester in Paris on December 1.
 39 of 39
Macron had asked political leaders to meet the protest organizers this week
. Two protesters who claim to lead the group, Benjamin Cauchy and Jacqueline Moreau, have however pulled out of a meeting with Prime Minister Philippe planned for Tuesday,
according to the movement's spokesman, Maxime Nicole.
Read More
Philippe canceled a trip to the COP24 climate conference in Poland to address the issue, which had threatened to flare again this coming weekend.
The government is likely hoping the suspension of the fuel hikes will take some heat out of the protests, which brought an estimated 36,000 people onto the streets of France on Saturday alone.
"Gilets jaunes" protesters at the Champs Elysees in Paris on Saturday
Around 400 people were arrested after a violent minority turned on police, throwing projectiles and vandalizing statues. 
The city's famed Arc de Triomphe was scrawled with slogans in support of the yellow vest movement and others criticizing Macron as the President "of the rich."
Students have also joined the "yellow vests" movement and, according to Reuters, demonstrators set buildings on fire and there were violent clashes with police on Tuesday. 
Devant notre terrasse belle vue sur le lycée st exupery à Blagnac... Qui Crame ‼️‼️ 😡 ! 
@actutoulouse_fr
@lyceens
@toulouse
@blagnac
@GiletsJaunesFr
pic.twitter.com/qJugEfXfOx
— troiscatalans (@troiscatalans) 
December 4, 2018


Saint-Exupery high school located in Blagnac near Toulouse in southwest France had been set on fire on Tuesday, Reuters reported. 
C'est cool Orléans 
#orleans
#blocus
pic.twitter.com/RJeXkUraMy
— Veyzersxn🦍 (@maui_klt) 
😂 c'est la gueeerrre
#lyceeencolere
#lacassagne
#lyon
#lycée
#crs
pic.twitter.com/D5bH4khO4x
— Lauryn_Chrp (@LaurynCHIPSY) 
Access to schools in Creteil and Versailles was also blocked, Reuters said.
The news agency also reported that there were clashes in Lyon, Marseille, Bordeaux and Orleans.
Paris prosecutor Remy Heitz said that among the protesters were people from across the country who had descended upon Paris with the express intent of causing trouble. 
He added that authorities would crack down hardest on those who had joined the street demonstrations explicitly to carry out violent acts.
"There are varied profiles but there are definitely profiles of people who have come from the provinces all over France, obviously to carry out acts of violence, and it is to these people that the criminal response I will say will be the strongest."
How the 'Yellow Vests' formed
The cost of diesel has surged 16% this year from an average €1.24 ($1.41) per liter to €1.48 ($1.69), even hitting €1.53 ($1.74) in October, according to UFIP, France's oil industry federation.
Protesters reacted by taking to the streets of Paris, setting fire to tires -- even cars, in some instances -- for two weekends in a row. Violence has left at least two people dead and more than 600 people injured. Protesters struck some of the wealthiest parts of the French capital, looting luxury shops and smashing bank windows. Police have arrested hundreds.
The "gilets jaunes" may have begun with motorists protesting the tax rise, but it has since mushroomed into a movement against the reformist policies of Macron, thrusting the most severe political crisis on the 40-year-old leader since he took office 19 months ago.
JUST WATCHED
Protests in France turn violent again
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
02:17
The "gilets jaunes" is a grassroots movement that emerged online with Facebook events set up by regular citizens to coordinate road blockades across France. 
The movement has no ties to the big French trade unions that usually organize large-scale protests in the country, nor does it have formal spokespeople. Some protesters say that Cauchy and Moreau, who have spoken on behalf of the group, are not their legitimate leaders. 
The group mirrors Macron's own rise to power, which began with the creation of his own grassroots movement, "En Marche!" ("On the move!"), and no backing by the big established parties. Macron said he was neither from the left nor right, just that he was "for France" and branded himself as a man of the people. Macron campaigned on promises to radically change France and his ideas were published in a book he wrote called "Revolution."
But the wave of support that brought Macron to power has waned, 
with the young leader's approval rating dropping to 25% in November
. And public support for the movement is high -- a Harris poll conducted after Saturday's protest suggests that
 almost three-quarters of French people support it. 
Macron is just the latest of many French leaders who have lost support for trying to transform France into a friendlier nation for doing business. His slashing of the wealth tax, for example, was unpopular and triggered criticism that he works for the elite and condescends to the poor.
One of the thousands of protesters who took to the streets to call for lower fuel prices
Many at the protests in Paris came in from rural areas and say they are struggling to make ends meet. Maxime Nicolle, 31, who was at a protest Saturday, is from a rural part of Brittany, and has been a member of the "gilets jaunes" since its creation in November. 
He said his family of three struggles to survive on €1,500 a month. "It's really about inequality and how the wealth is distributed. It's a battle between the financial system and the population," he told CNN. 
Hugo Melchior, from a wealthy neighborhood in Rennes, northwest France, doesn't even own a car, yet he supports the movement.
"We are dealing with a convergence of anger, frustration, exasperation and weariness that's been suppressed for too long. And they now have this immense power, they find themselves able to act together at a local level against a common enemy -- the state power personified by President Emmanuel Macron, who incites hatred because of his endless arrogance."
CNN's Saskya Vandoorne reported from Paris, Euan McKirdy wrote from Hong Kong, Angela Dewan and Bianca Britton contributed from London.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/23/opinions/uk-far-right-brexit-opinion-intl-gbr/index.html" date="2019-01-23" labels="opinions, The UK's far right thinks about lots more than Brexit - CNN" title="The UK's far right thinks about lots more than Brexit - CNN" >
David Toube
 is the political director of Quilliam International, a think tank based in London that specializes in researching counter-extremism. The opinions in this article belong to the author. 
 (CNN)
The deep social and political divisions exposed by the UK's Brexit vote  present both an opportunity for the British far right -- as well as being a challenge to it.
Indeed, only this week, Neil Basu the head of London's Metropolitan Police's counterterrorism operations, 
said that Brexit had the "potential to divide communities and set communities against each other," 
and that amid this "febrile" atmosphere there was the possibility of a "far-right drift into extreme right-wing terrorism."
While Basu makes an important point, it's worth putting the state of the UK's far right under the microscope.
The political parties and organizations that once dominated the landscape of the far right have been in a state of disintegration and collapse for some time. Although new extremist organizations have arisen to take their place, they have been quickly suppressed or have collapsed.
Far-right groups could exploit Brexit atmosphere, says counter-terror chief
Yet, paradoxically, the prospects for political extremism of all types are favorable.
Read More
In 2019, it is not uncommon to see conspiracy theories and sentiments of betrayal in mainstream political debate. The national wrangling over Brexit has encouraged that perspective. It is not, however, its primary cause.
First, the good news. For the past few decades, the landscape of the far right has been dominated by the British National Party: an organization which at its peak had two Members of the European Parliament and over fifty councilors. In 2018, its last councilor retired from politics, and was not replaced.
For a while, it looked as if the English Defence League -- a street politics movement which organized threatening demonstrations in neighborhoods with large Muslim populations -- might fill the void. But by 2013, the EDL fractured and lost its leadership.
Its place was taken by a largely online political movement calling itself "Britain First", that focused on circulating memes and misinformation and staged the occasional frightening mosque invasion.
In turn, Britain First fell apart when its leaders were convicted of public order offenses and banned from Twitter. An attempt to import the European "Generation Identity" movement into the UK also failed when it became clear that its members included neo-Nazis, and its leader resigned.
JUST WATCHED
Trump cheered Senate victory; so did supremacists
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
 
03:13
Of greater concern are the small, violent neo-Nazi groups, including National Action, that have formed in recent years. Though they were quickly suppressed under anti-terrorism legislation, we should be deeply concerned by their existence.
Remember: it only takes a single, radicalized individual to commit a murder or perpetrate an atrocity.
But, despite Basu's warning, it is difficult to draw a straight line from Brexit to the rise of these small and violent groups.
Yet, if we shift our focus from the failure of the organized far-right groups to the widespread sense of disappointment across the UK as a whole, a less optimistic picture emerges.
Read the comments in popular political Facebook groups, on Twitter, or in comments on newspaper articles.
Listen to the concerns of friends and family members. You will be struck by the profound sense of uncertainty and unhappiness.
Politicians are all crooks, they say. Public figures are cynical liars. We are being cheated and manipulated by shadowy forces wielding unlimited power. Brexit has a role in fueling such beliefs.
The rhetoric surrounding the negotiations, combined with the high expectations of both the ease of the process and the outcome, fed into the narrative that the public that voted Brexit are being stabbed in the back.
Macron vowed to fight the populists. Now he's being engulfed by them
However, Brexit did not cause the rise of similar amorphous, conspiracy-theory-loving movements. Brexit does not explain the rise of the Gilets Jaunes in France or the Five Star movement in Italy: both of them organizations which defy classification as far right or far left.
Indeed, the claim that we are being manipulated by "globalists," Soros, or the Rothschild family, can be found at both poles of the political spectrum.
Far-right groups are an opportunistic infection, feeding on a weakened body politic. Extremists are adept at exploiting grievances for the purposes of recruitment. Their failure to establish a cohesive and powerful mass movement, led by the far right, indicates that they are yet to reap the political dividend from Brexit. However, the far right remains emboldened.
Brexit itself is better understood as an issue that has focused an independent feeling of mistrust, rather than as its generator.
It is the political polarization that has resulted from the breakdown of what we used to regard as "normal politics", of confidence in the values of liberal democracy, that represents the most significant threat to cohesion.
That polarization may find its expression in movements that are far right, far left or radical Islamist in nature.
This, in itself, should be our greater concern.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/12/europe/yellow-vest-france-protests-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-12" labels="europe, Gilets jaunes: Police use water cannon as yellow vest protesters rise - CNN" title="Gilets jaunes: Police use water cannon as yellow vest protesters rise - CNN" >
 (CNN)
Police fired water cannon and tear gas at "gilets jaunes" or yellow vest protesters in central Paris, who have marched through the city for the ninth consecutive weekend.
A total of 59 people were questioned by authorities, on charges including unlawful weapons and participating in a group with the goal of committing violent crimes.
Violent clashes occurred on the Champs-Elysées, a epicenter of 
the protests which have brought repeated disruption to the city
.
'Yellow vest' protests across France trigger spurts of violence, calls for calm
The total number of demonstrators has also risen from last weekend, the country's Interior Ministry said.
More than 32,000 people were taking part across France at 2 p.m. local time (8 a.m. ET) on Saturday, a rise of 6,000 compared to the same time seven days ago.
Read More
In Paris itself, 8,000 were marching, a fourfold increase on last weekend. 
The protests began as a campaign against a gas tax hike, but have morphed into a broader rally against President Emmanuel Macron's government.
They caused many
 tourist sites and landmarks to be closed
 in anticipation of violent scenes.
Gilets jaunes protesters march through Paris on Saturday.
Some of the demonstrations in the capital on Saturday took place near the Rue de Trevise in the city's 9th arrondissement, where hours earlier 
an explosion at a bakery killed two firefighters and a Spanish citizen.
In his New Year's address, Macron referred to the movement without naming it specifically.
He acknowledged anger against injustice but said hateful speech would not be tolerated, and called on people to respect each other.
Last month, he pledged to increase the minimum wage and scrap new pension taxes, in an effort to appease the protesters.
At least 10 deaths have been linked to the protests, with most taking place in traffic accidents related to blockades in November and December.
CNN's Katie Polglase, Saskya Vandoorne and Arnaud Siad contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/17/europe/macron-aide-benalla-passports-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-17" labels="europe, Macron's ex-security aide Benalla in custody over diplomatic passport use - CNN" title="Macron's ex-security aide Benalla in custody over diplomatic passport use - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
A former security aide to French President Emmanuel Macron has been placed in custody as part of an investigation into his use of diplomatic passports, the Paris prosecutor's office told CNN on Thursday.
Alexandre Benalla was fired from Macron's office in July last year after 
being filmed beating up
 a May Day protester.
He is currently under investigation for the "illegal use of a document certifying a professional position" and "forgery and use of forgery," the prosecutor's office said.
Macron's chief of staff, Patrick Strzoda, on Wednesday testified at a Senate hearing that Benalla had used his diplomatic passports about 20 times between August 1 and December 31, 2018. 
Strzoda also said Benalla had used a fake document with the letterhead of the President's chief of staff to request his second service passport.
French President Emmanuel Macron leaves his house dressed for tennis with his then-deputy chief of staff Alexandre Benalla in June 2017.
Read More
Benalla used the passports on business trips to Africa, including to Chad, senators heard. 
Speaking to Le Journal du Dimanche newspaper in recent weeks, Benalla said he had gained no improper benefit from the use of the passports.
"I may have been wrong to use these passports," Benalla said in a December 30 interview. "But I did it only for personal comfort, to make it easier for me to travel in airports. I did not use them for my business, and I do not see what they could have done for me."
Benalla also told the newspaper that he had returned his diplomatic passports to the Elysée Palace at the end of August but that they were given back to him with other personal effects in early October by "a member of the presidency." 
"Since they were given back to me, I did not see any reason not to use them." Benalla said.
In a separate interview with digital outlet Mediapart, released on December 31, Benalla said he continued to have regular contact with the President on current affairs, such as the "gilets jaunes," or yellow vest, protest movement.
"They cannot deny it," Benalla told Mediapart. "It will be very hard to do because all these exchanges are on my mobile phone."
The judicial inquiry into the May Day incidents is still ongoing, the Paris prosecutor's office said Thursday. 
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/15/europe/france-paris-gilets-jaunes-protests-intl/index.html" date="2018-12-15" labels="europe, France's 'yellow vest' protesters turn out for fifth weekend  - CNN" title="France's 'yellow vest' protesters turn out for fifth weekend  - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
Crowds of "gilets jaunes" or "yellow vest" protesters gathered Saturday in Paris for a fifth consecutive weekend of demonstrations despite 
concessions this week by French President Emmanuel Macron
.
But their numbers were lower than in previous weeks, with some perhaps appeased by Macron's promises, while others may have been deterred by cold, wet weather or shaken by the 
terror attack
 earlier this week on a Christmas market in Strasbourg.
 Photos:
 
In photos: Protests in France
A yellow vest demonstrator faces riot police officers in Marseille, France, on Saturday, January 5, 2019.
Hide Caption
 1 of 39
Riot police stand in tear gas in Toulouse, France, during a protest January 5.
 2 of 39
Yellow vest protestors kneel in Lyon on January 5. About 50,000 people demonstrated throughout France on Saturday, according to Interior Minister Christophe Castaner.
 3 of 39
Protesters warm their hands over a burning tree in a Paris street on January 5.
 4 of 39
A firefighter tries to extinguish a burning car in a street in Paris on January 5.
 5 of 39
Protesters confront police during a "yellow vest" demonstration Saturday, December 22, in central Paris.
 6 of 39
Demonstrators rally in the Montmartre area of Paris on December 22.
 7 of 39
Protesters block a highway near the French border with Spain on December 22 in Biriatou, France.
 8 of 39
Demonstators turn out December 22 near toll booths on the A9 highway in Le Boulou, France.
 9 of 39
Protesters gather December 15 at Place de l'Opera in Paris.
 10 of 39
Activists dressed like Marianne, the symbol of the French Republic, face riot police on December 15 in Paris.
 11 of 39
Demonstrators wearing yellow vests form a human tower December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 12 of 39
A police water cannon sprays demonstrators on December 15 in Paris.
 13 of 39
Protesters take part in a demonstration on December 15 in Paris.
 14 of 39
Demonstrators run through tear gas during scuffles with police December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 15 of 39
Police use tear gas on protesters at the Place de l'Opera in Paris on December 15.
 16 of 39
A protester waves the French national flag during a demonstration on the Champs-Élysées in Paris on December 15.
 17 of 39
French police apprehend a man on December 8 during a protest in Paris.
 18 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests gather on December 8 in front of the Eiffel Tower in Paris.
 19 of 39
Demonstrators drop flat to the ground on the Champs-Elysees avenue during a protest on Saturday, December 8, in Paris. 
 20 of 39
Protesters install a barricade during clashes with police at a demonstration in Paris on December 8.
 21 of 39
Protesters gather on December 8 in Paris.
 22 of 39
A demonstrator is covered in blood after getting in injured during a protest in Paris on December 8.
 23 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests walk on the Champs-Elysees Avenue with the Arc de Triomphe in the background during a protest on December 8.
 24 of 39
Two demonstrators dance in front a group as they take part on December 8 in the demonstration at the Arc de Triomphe in Paris.
 25 of 39
A protester reacts during clashes with police on December 8 in Paris.
 26 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester on December 8 in Paris.
 27 of 39
Protesters throw objects at riot police on Saturday, December 1, during a demonstration that turned violent when protestors clashed with police in Paris.
 28 of 39
An injured woman sits on the ground as police officers spray yellow vest protesters with tear gas during a protest in Paris on December 1.
 29 of 39
A burned car is left in the street a day after the  yellow vests demonstration against rising oil prices and living costs in Paris on December 1.
 30 of 39
Firemen work to extinguish a burning car on December 1.
 31 of 39
A demonstrator leaves as water cannons evacuate the Place de l'Etoile on December 1.
 32 of 39
A demonstrator watches a burning car near the Champs-Elysees avenue on December 1.
 33 of 39
Riot police officers stand in position during clashes with demonstrators on December 1.
 34 of 39
Protesters and police clash in downtown Paris on December 1 during a national demonstration.
 35 of 39
Hooded demonstrators smash a car.
 36 of 39
A demonstrator throws a projectile during the December 1 protest.
 37 of 39
A demonstrator treats a wounded man during a protest where police and demonstrators clashed, injuring dozens on December 1.
 38 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester in Paris on December 1.
 39 of 39
By midafternoon Saturday, about 34,000 protesters had turned out across France, including more than 2,000 in Paris, according to the Interior Ministry. Last week, some 77,000 protesters turned out across the country, including 10,000 in Paris.
Paris police estimates earlier Saturday put the number of protesters in the capital at several thousand.
Some 69,000 police officers were deployed across the country in anticipation of the protests, including 8,000 in Paris, the Interior Ministry said.
Read More
Emmanuel Macron was anointed as France's last great hope for reform. Is that all lost now?
Police used tear gas on the Champs-Elysées in confrontations with protesters. Some were seen throwing rocks at security forces.
More than 100 people were in police custody for questioning early Saturday, Paris police said, much fewer than last week. The protests are named after the yellow high-visibility jackets French motorists must carry in their vehicles.
Paris department stores such as the Galeries Lafayette and Printemps are open this weekend as well as the Louvre museum and Eiffel Tower. Parts of the Champs-Elysées also reopened to traffic midmorning Saturday.
Speaking to CNN French affiliate BFMTV, Maxime Nicolle, a spokesman for the "gilets jaunes," called for a citizens' referendum. "We are protesting peacefully, but Mr. President give us back our freedom and our sovereignty!" he said.
A Paris protester holds a "RIC" sign Saturday in a reference to a demand for a citizens' referendum.
The protesters held a moment's silence at the Place de l'Opéra for those who have been killed since the movement began.
Authorities in northern France confirmed that a man died Friday evening in a car accident in Erquelinnes, Belgium, following a blockade by "yellow vests" near Jeumont.
Macron promises social reforms
On December 8, many Paris tourist hot spots and stores were shuttered in anticipation of 
violent protests
 after the previous week's demonstrations resulted in the worst riots to hit the French capital in decades. By the 
end of last weekend
, 1,723 people had been taken in for questioning and 1,220 into custody, according to the Interior Ministry. Across the country, 135 people were reported injured.
#giletsjaunes
pic.twitter.com/pGvwictBUQ
— Saskya Vandoorne (@SaskyaCNN) 
December 15, 2018


Under increasing pressure to respond, Macron may have taken some of the heat out of the protests when he pledged Monday night to increase the minimum wage and scrap new pension taxes. 
In a televised address to the nation, Macron said the violent protests -- which have morphed from a grassroots movement against fuel tax hikes into disparate demonstrations against his presidency -- have been "unacceptable" and "will not be in any way indulged."
He proposed some social reforms, including an increase in the minimum wage by 100 euros ($113) a month beginning in January that will not cost employers extra and a promise that overtime hours will not be taxed. Macron also remained defiant and said he would not reinstate the wealth tax but would fight tax fraud.
Nothing like last Saturday.. 
pic.twitter.com/iclNxOuRkQ
'Profound' anger
Journalist and political commentator Agnès Poirier told CNN that the anger felt by protesters, many of them lower middle class from more rural areas, remained "profound." 
Who are the 'yellow vest' protesters causing chaos in France?
But she said the measures announced by Macron -- and his televised appearance during which he seemed more humble and heartfelt than before -- may have swayed some people.
"We will see if the French are still supporting the movement, but also if the 'yellow vests' are ready to stop demonstrating and structure themselves," said Poirier, referring to the grassroots nature of the movement, which has no leadership and has largely been organized through social media.
"They need to structure themselves to meet with the government and go to the table to start negotiating."
"Yellow vest" demonstrators face riot police officers Saturday in the French capital. 
The reforms are expected to cost the government between $8.1 billion and $10.1 billion, Olivier Dussopt, France's secretary of state to the Ministry of Public Action and Accounts, told BFMTV.
Macron visited the Christmas market in Strasbourg on Friday evening to express his gratitude to members of the emergency services after this week's deadly attack there. Police killed the 
suspected attacker 
Thursday evening in the city following a two-day manhunt. Four people have died following Tuesday's attack.
CNN's Saskya Vandoorne reported from Paris and Laura Smith-Spark wrote from London. CNN's Sandrine Amiel contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/07/europe/paris-protest-gilets-jaunes-france-intl/index.html" date="2018-12-07" labels="europe, Eiffel Tower, Louvre to close amid fears of weekend protests - CNN" title="Eiffel Tower, Louvre to close amid fears of weekend protests - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
France is bracing for another weekend of protests that could rock Paris and other parts of the country.
Prime Minister Edouard Philippe said the government was deploying 89,000 security force members across France -- including 8,000 in the capital -- in case the demonstrations turn violent again. 
Many of Paris' famed sites -- including the Louvre, the Eiffel Tower, the Musée Delacroix and the Paris Opera -- will close over the weekend in advance of the protests, organized by the "gilets jaunes," or "yellow vest" movement. The name comes from the high-visibility yellow vests that drivers are required to keep in their vehicles for safety reasons.
Interior Minister Christophe Castaner vowed to deploy all the means available to ensure the latest protests are not hijacked by what he called "a small minority" who have been "radicalized and fallen into violence and hate."
The Eiffel Tower will be closed to visitors over the weekend because of expected "yellow vest" protests.
"We have to guarantee the safety of protesters and the right of citizens to move around freely," Castaner told a news conference Friday.
Read More
Stores along the famed Champs-Elysées have also been advised to remain shut. Shop owners were boarding up stores Friday amid fears of further disorder.
The French retail sector has suffered a loss in revenue of about $1.1 billion since the beginning of the yellow vest protests last month, a spokeswoman for the French retail federation, Sophie Amoros, told CNN. 
Amid heightened tensions, police seized 28 petrol bombs and three homemade explosive devices Friday at an area blockaded by protesters in Montauban in southern France, a spokesman for the Tarn-et-Garonne prefecture told CNN.
On Friday, Paris' public transport operator, RATP, announced on its website that 36 Metro stations would be closed Saturday. It also said 50 bus lines will have limited to no service.
Photographer Vartan Tanelian observed students protesting as part of a "yellow vest" demonstration in the Paris suburb of Alfortville on Friday morning. 
 
 View this post on Instagram
Dans la matinée,Rue etienne dolet 07/12/2018.
A post shared by 
 Tanelian Vartan
 (@v.moody) on 
Dec 7, 2018 at 2:33am PST


Tanelian, 25, told CNN that students were burning garbage near their high school. The school closed, as did local shops, and the traffic was at a standstill, he said.
Protester not backing down
Some 630 people were arrested and more than 260 injured, including 81 police officers, in 
last weekend
's protests nationwide, the third consecutive week of such demonstrations.
There have been four accidental deaths, according to officials. Three resulted from traffic accidents related to the blockades, and the fourth was that of an 80-year-old woman who died in Marseille after being hit by a tear gas canister that came through her window.
JUST WATCHED
Moisi: France was supposed to be carrier of hope
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
10:04
The demonstrations began as a form of grassroots opposition to rising gas prices and planned increases in taxes on polluting forms of transport, but they have evolved into broader protests against President Emmanuel Macron's government. 
Macron appeared to back down Wednesday, announcing that the fuel tax planned for January -- as part of measures to combat climate change -- would not be introduced in 2019. But the movement now appears to be about more than just taxes; it's exposed the growing divide between Paris' metropolitan elite and the country's rural poor. 
Maxime Nicolle, a member of the gilets jaunes from rural Brittany, told CNN: "I'm definitely not backing down now. The moratorium is useless. The people want a referendum, a referendum on Macron, the Senate and the National Assembly."
Street furniture, such as railings around trees, public bicycle stations and benches, will be removed from parts of Paris ahead of the expected protests so they can't be used as weapons, Mayor Anne Hidalgo said.
Municipal buildings will be closed, and services "mobilized and determined to ensure everyone's protection," she said. In an appeal to protesters, the mayor added, "Please take care of Paris, because Paris belongs to all the French people."
High school students demonstrate Friday at the Place de la Republique in Paris over education reforms.
On Friday, Benoit Potterie, a member of Parliament from Macron's En Marche party, wrote on Twitter that he received a bullet by mail and said that 
a note accompanying it
 contained the message, "Next time, it will be between your eyes."
In response to the threat, the lawmaker tweeted: "I have always been open to dialogue but these threats are unacceptable. I will not be intimidated and continue my work as a Member of Parliament with the same motivation, the general interest and the same method: exchange and dialogue."
It wasn't clear who sent the bullet.
Unrest spreads to schools 
Many of those demonstrating have moved to the suburbs due to rising real estate prices. Suburban protesters, like those from rural areas, argue they're disproportionately affected by the now-shelved gas tax, as they rely on gas and cars much more than city dwellers.
Castener, the interior minister, said he had talked to protesters and had some sympathy with their concerns and economic troubles. 
But, he said, the French government had made appropriate gestures. "The Prime Minister opened the door, and canceled the environment tax," he said. 
High schoolers set a barricade on fire to block a tramway during a protest Wednesday in Bordeaux.
The unrest has spread to hundreds of high schools across the country, where students are demonstrating against recent education reforms.
More than 140 people were arrested Thursday outside a school in the Paris suburb of Mantes-la-Jolie after protesters clashed with police.
Education Minister Jean-Michel Blanquer 
told radio station France Inter
 on Friday that he, like many others, had been shocked by images of students in Mantes-la-Jolie being made to kneel with their hands behind their heads by security forces. But he said that elements from outside the schools had used the situation to stir up trouble and attack security forces.
Police detain students Thursday in Mantes-la-Jolie after clashes with security forces.
Castaner said 12 officers were present to bring the situation under control, which was reflected in the methods they used.
Meanwhile, La Voix du Nord newspaper in northern France reported that a 
bottle containing acid
 had been thrown Friday at one of its journalists and a fellow reporter while they were covering a high school protest in the town of Wingles, in the Pas-de-Calais department. The two narrowly managed to avoid being hit, the paper said.
Presidency in crisis
It's unclear if the gilets jaunes demonstrations will be as violent or as large this weekend. The number of 
protesters peaked last month
 at 282,000, according to the Interior Ministry, but has been slowly on the decline, with 136,000 taking part Sunday.
Since the first protests were held in mid-November, 1,648 people have been injured, including 552 police officers, the Interior Ministry said. More than 1,600 people have been taken in for questioning and 1,387 arrested. 
Macron will not speak publicly before this weekend's protests, the press office for the presidency said Friday. Macron is resisting pressure from protesters and politicians to speak sooner to calm tensions ahead of time. 
Macron's top-down approach to fighting climate change serves as a cautionary tale
Dominique Moisi, a foreign policy expert at the Paris-based Institut Montaigne and a former Macron campaign adviser, told CNN the French presidency was not only in crisis but that Europe's future also hung in the balance.
"In a few months from now, there will be European elections, and France was supposed to be the carrier of hope and European progress. What happens if it's no longer? If the President is incapacitated to carry that message?" Moisi asked.
"It's about the future of democracy, as well; illiberal democracies are rising all over the world. And if Macron fails, the future of France risks looking like the presidency of Italy today. And it's much more serious because we have a centralized state, which plays a major role in the balance of power within Europe. 
"But make no mistake, it is a French version of a much more global phenomenon."
CNN's Saskya Vandoorne reported from Paris, while Laura Smith-Spark wrote from London and Joshua Berlinger from Hong Kong. CNN's Hilary Clarke, Sandrine Amiel and Leslie Perrot contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/07/app-news-section/quickly-catch-up-december-7-trnd/index.html" date="2018-12-07" labels="app-news-section, News today: Russia investigation, Kevin Hart, Eiffel Tower - CNN" title="News today: Russia investigation, Kevin Hart, Eiffel Tower - CNN" >
 (CNN)
Here's what you might have missed Friday on CNN:
-- There's a lot happening with special counsel Robert Mueller today. In separate filings, prosecutors from special counsel Robert Mueller's office and the Southern District of New York outlined their 
cases for former Trump attorney Michael Cohen's future.
 We're now learning that the President's former associate 
Paul Manafort lied about five major issues after his plea, according to Mueller's filing
. Former FBI Director 
James Comey testified before members of Congress
 behind closed doors. Mueller's team also interviewed 
John Kelly in the obstruction of justice probe into the President,
 sources told CNN.
-- A man who rammed his car into a crowd protesting a white nationalist rally in Charlottesville, Virginia, 
was found guilty of murder
.
-- Speaking of Kelly, sources say the 
White House chief of staff is expected to resign
 in the coming days.
-- Trump made his picks for both
 attorney genera
l and
 UN ambassador
Read More
-- The President called former Secretary of State Rex Tillerson
 "dumb as a rock" and "lazy as hell."
-- Kevin Hart says he won't host the Oscars after outrage over 
his homophobic tweets
-- The deputy who died in the Thousand Oaks mass shooting 
was killed by friendly fire
-- Cyntoia Brown must serve
 51 years before she's eligible for release
, Tennessee Supreme Court says.
-- Most US 
adults haven't gotten a flu shot
 for this mild season.
-- Snow is expected to 
blanket the Southeast and Mid-Atlantic
-- The Eiffel Tower and the Louvre are closing ahead of 
this weekend's 'gilets jaunes' protests
-- Bitcoin's 
epic plunge continues
-- The Grammy nominations are here and even brought 
Janelle Monáe to tears
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/27/europe/france-yellow-vest-protester-loses-eye-riot-police-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-27" labels="europe, Gilets jaunes: Jerome Rodrigues seriously wounded while protesting in Paris - CNN" title="Gilets jaunes: Jerome Rodrigues seriously wounded while protesting in Paris - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
A prominent figure in France's gilets jaunes, or "yellow vest," movement was seriously wounded during a protest in Paris on Saturday. 
Jerome Rodrigues, a self-described pacifist, was injured in his right eye by a projectile hurled towards him, allegedly by police.
In an interview with French broadcaster LCI on Sunday, Rodrigues said that he had stayed in Paris' Place de la Bastille to encourage fellow yellow vest demonstrators to leave the area as skirmishes between the Black Bloc -- another group of protesters often associated with anarchy and violent skirmishes -- and the police, escalated.
Rodrigues' lawyer Philippe de Veulle told CNN affiliate BFM TV that he believes that a flash ball  -- a controversial "less lethal" hand-held weapon launcher deployed by French police in riots -- injured him.
French police said the watchdog agency the General Inspectorate of National Police (IGPN) had launched an investigation into the case of "an injured man rescued on Bastille Square." 
Read More
Rodrigues's lawyer said he had evidence to give the IGPN.
"I have material elements in the sense that it's a Flash Ball shot. The Flash Ball will be handed over to the IGPN Divisional Commissioner, who contacted my client's sister last night," de Veulle told BFM TV.
Flash Ball is a French-made trademarked projectile whose manufacturer, Verney-Carron Security, calls it a "non-lethal 44mm-gauge weapon... versatile, adaptable, but always effective."
The incident was captured by Rodrigues, as he was livestreaming the protest, on his Facebook page. The video has been watched over 1.4M times and shared by 67,000 users. 
Shortly after the incident, Rodrigues posted a photo to his Facebook account that said: "I am going to lose my eye, fam."
The protests -- named after the yellow high-visibility jackets French motorists must carry in their vehicles -- started November 17 in reaction to an eco-tax on gas but have since morphed into broader demonstrations against President Emmanuel Macron and his government. 
Last month, 
a pressurized Macron
 pledged to increase the minimum wage and get rid of new pension taxes. But the move has done little to appease the anger felt by some hard-core protesters.
'No one is in charge here': How yellow vest protests spread, and why Macron's struggling to keep up
Saturday marked the 11th consecutive week of the demonstrations. A French Interior Ministry spokesperson told CNN that approximately 69,000 people marched on Saturday in solidarity with the yellow vest movement, including 4,000 protesters in Paris. 
"I am a hyper pacifist, I do not want anyone to get hurt," Rodrigues said. "I was there to make sure my little yellow guys could get out of this hell."
Rodrigues gave further details on the incident, saying that that he had been to the hospital and awaits further guidance from doctors regarding his injury.
"It's very painful. I'm waiting for the doctors to come and tell me what it is. It's my right eye, and I think I stayed in the operating room for seven or eight hours," Rodrigues said.
Rodrigues is planning on filing a complaint to the police, LCI reported. 
"I was deliberately targeted. I am a figure of the movement, at least in the Paris protests, and police pointed their fingers at me many times during previous demonstrations, so I think they knew very well who they were shooting at," Rodrigues told BFM TV Sunday.
Ten people have died
 in connection with the protests, with most deaths taking place in traffic accidents related to blockades in November and December.
On Sunday, 10,500 people marched in the French capital for the so-called "foulards rouges" or "red scarfs" protest, in opposition to the ongoing yellow vest demonstrations, according to the Paris Police Department.
CNN's Martin Goillandeau, Ben Marcus and Nada Bashir contributed to this report.
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/03/08/europe/gilet-jaunes-france-anti-semitism-intl/index.html" date="2019-03-09" labels="europe, Yellow Vest protesters fan flames of anti-Semitism in France - CNN" title="Yellow Vest protesters fan flames of anti-Semitism in France - CNN" >
Paris (CNN)
Recent weeks have seen black swastikas scrawled across portraits of Auschwitz survivor, Simone Veil; 96 tombs at a Jewish cemetery defaced in eastern France; and the words, "Dirty Zionist sh*t!", hurled in anger at 
French philosopher Alain Finkielkraut
 by a man wearing a fluorescent yellow vest. 
These are but a few of the anti-Semitic attacks that have blighted the country in recent months. Home to Europe's largest Jewish community, France has seen a 
74% rise in anti-Semitic incidents
 over the past year, according to French authorities. French President Emmanuel Macron has gone as far as to say that anti-Semitism is at its worst levels in France and in other parts of Europe since World War II.
'I'm scared for the future of my baby here': French Jews live in fear amid rising anti-Semitic acts
Studies have shown anti-Semitism is rising sharply across Europe but this violent resurgence in France has triggered some deep soul-searching with many asking: what's behind it? Why now? Some have questioned the Yellow Vest movement and whether its radical fringe is partly to blame for the sudden uptick. 
"Anti-Semitism was going strong before the yellow vests, but it's even stronger today thanks to some of them," the head of the French Council of Jewish Institutions, Francis Kalifat, said last month.
"Gilets Jaunes, Colere Noir" is a popular slogan among the leaderless movement, meaning "Yellow Vests, Black Rage." For almost four months it's this rage that has poured out along the Champs Elysees, shattering shop windows, leaving police officers wounded and symbolically knocking the Marianne, a national figure who embodies the French Republic, off her perch.
Read More
Protesters rally against anti-Semitism in France after more graves vandalized
Vitriol previously expressed in anonymous tweets has materialized in large letters plastered across the Arc de Triomphe monument for all to see. Offensive mutterings that were confined to the home have been amplified and have now taken center stage, as protesters scream their lungs out on live television. France has seen an unprecedented public expression of hate, where nothing now seems to be off-limits. 
The Yellow Vests are not an anti-Semitic movement per se but in a climate where every voice is considered legitimate, anti-Jewish sentiment has found a prominent platform. Thierry-Paul Valette, a spokesman for the Yellow Vests, rejects the accusation that the movement has empowered hate speech. "We didn't fuel anti-Semitism or hate, we simply put a mirror up to society," Valette says. 
"Yes, there are racists, homophobes and anti-Semites in our ranks but that's only a reflection of the French population as a whole."
Graves at the Jewish cemetery in Quatzenheim, near Strasbourg, France, have been desecrated with swastikas.
Nazi salute in reverse
France has a chequered and painful past with anti-Semitism. Even before the Nazi collaboration of the Vichy regime there was 
the Dreyfus affair
, the case of a Jewish army captain who was wrongly accused of spying for Germany: a miscarriage of justice rooted in blatant anti-Semitism that divided France at the end of the 19th century. 
And since the 1990s, a virulent left-wing anti-Semitism has flared up, mirroring the peaks and troughs of violence in the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. And on the right, nationalist anti-Semitism has been embodied by Jean-Marie Le Pen, a convicted Holocaust denier and founder of the National Front. 
There's no doubt that the far-left and right have been a part of the Yellow Vest movement. Pictures and videos of demonstrators performing the "quenelle," a downward pointing gesture believed by some to be a Nazi salute in reverse, have emerged online. 
JUST WATCHED
Why the Gilet Jaunes are going after Macron
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
 
01:54
The quenelle was invented by French stand-up comedian Dieudonne M'bala M'bala, a controversial entertainer who's 
been spotted
 at Yellow Vest protests alongside Jean-Marie Le Pen's former speech writer, 
Alain Soral
. 
Both men have been convicted of anti-Semitism several times. Dieudonne has been charged with "inciting hatred" due to "homophobic, racist and anti-Semitic" comments made during one of his performances in Belgium, and has several convictions in France for making anti-Semitic comments. Soral has also been charged with inciting hatred of Jews because of an anti-Semitic article he posted on his website. 
Dieudonne and Soral regularly appear on their YouTube channels donning Yellow Vests and encouraging their followers -- who are in the hundreds of thousands -- to overthrow "bankers" and "Zionist powers."
Alain Finkielkraut, whose Polish-Jewish father survived deportation to Auschwitz, told the French press he sees the influence of both Dieudonne and Soral in the rise of anti-Semitism. "We mustn't underestimate their influence. Their dream is to unify a multi-cultural France behind a hatred of the Jews," 
he said
.
Finkielkraut, was a strong supporter of the Yellow Vest movement when it started, although he now believes the protest is "grotesque" and should stop because "the violence and hatred have gone too far."
Over the past 15 years Rabbi Nissim Sultan has lost a significant part of his congregation in Grenoble because of anti-Semitism. He says the rise in conspiracy theories has played a huge part: "There's increasing distrust. With globalization and the fight between social classes, old stereotypes have returned," Sultan said. "It's during times of unrest that people look for a scapegoat so here we are again because we're a familiar figure to blame." 
Anti-Semitism has surged in recent years in France. A man holds a placard reading "I am afraid but I am here" during a gathering on Place de la Republique in January 10, 2016 in Paris.
Minority tars Yellow Vest movement
Conspiracy theories are popular with the Yellow Vests. Their distrust of the mainstream media has pushed many of them into social media echo chambers. Videos about the Rothschilds, the famous Jewish banking dynasty, have been widely circulated on Yellow Vest Facebook pages. 
A study conducted
 by the Fondation Jean Jaures shows 31% of people who identify as Yellow Vest supporters believe the US government was involved in 9/11 and a whopping 50% of those who participated in a Yellow Vest protest said they believed in a "global Zionist conspiracy."
Macron says anti-Semitism is at worst levels since World War Two 
Historian Pierre Birnbaum says the whole movement shouldn't be tarred with the same brush but he sees a crossover between the Yellow Vest ideology and anti-Semitism. "It's a movement against the elite, against globalization, against banks," he said. "All of this relies on the same stereotypical elements to do with money which can awaken a feeling of anti-Semitism." 
In the wake of these anti-Jewish attacks President Emmanuel Macron announced a crackdown on the "scourge" of anti-Semitism and said a draft law would be presented to parliament in May aimed at tackling online hate speech. "Anti-Zionism is one of the modern forms of anti-Semitism," Macron declared controversially, adding that in response, France will adopt the International Holocaust Remembrance Alliance's definition of anti-Semitism.  
A handful of senior Yellow Vests have publicly denounced anti-Semitism within the movement and several also took part in what the organizers estimated was a 20,000-strong demonstration against anti-Semitism last month. But in a movement with no clear organization or cohesion, there is yet to be a collective disavowing of anti-Semitism, with many of the self-proclaimed leaders remaining silent.
Yellow Vest turnout has been dwindling and the movement's wider support has waned significantly. But Friday will mark the beginning of a three-day sit-in held in Paris, climaxing with a large protest on the weekend of March 16/17 to mark four months since the movement began. Some worry that the moderate majority may be once again overshadowed by a radical and dangerous minority. 
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2018/12/03/europe/paris-yellow-vest-protests-intl/index.html" date="2018-12-03" labels="europe, Paris protests: Macron seeks way to defuse 'yellow vest' demonstrations - CNN" title="Paris protests: Macron seeks way to defuse 'yellow vest' demonstrations - CNN" >
 (CNN)
French President Emmanuel Macron has asked Prime Minister Edouard Philippe to meet with heads of political parties and representatives of the so-called "yellow vests" in an attempt to defuse tensions that erupted into violent protests over the weekend.
Around 36,000 people took part in protests across the country on Saturday, but while the turnout was lower than the previous two weekends, protesters clashed with police, torching cars, erecting roadblocks and burning barricades. 
The unrest has transformed from dissent over rising gas prices and eco-taxes into a broader demonstration against Macron, his government, and tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor.
Speaking on France's Europe 1 radio Sunday, spokesman Benjamin Griveaux said the government was considering "all options" to prevent "serious outbursts of violence," including introducing a state of emergency.
A burned-out car sits in a Paris street the day after riots spread through the city.
Griveaux said that between 1,000 and 1,500 people joined Saturday's demonstrations "only to fight with the police, to break and loot." He added that those protesters "have nothing to do with the yellow vests."
Read More
Yellow vests or "gilets jaunes" refers to the high visibility vests drivers in France are required to keep in their cars for safety reasons, should their cars break down.
Almost 400 people were arrested in Saturday's riots. 
As part of his response, Macron has asked the Ministry of the Interior to develop a policing plan to counter any further protests, according to CNN affiliate BFMTV.  No date has yet been set for the meeting between Philippe and the yellow vests, BFMTV reported.
 Photos:
 
In photos: Protests in France
A yellow vest demonstrator faces riot police officers in Marseille, France, on Saturday, January 5, 2019.
Hide Caption
 1 of 39
Riot police stand in tear gas in Toulouse, France, during a protest January 5.
 2 of 39
Yellow vest protestors kneel in Lyon on January 5. About 50,000 people demonstrated throughout France on Saturday, according to Interior Minister Christophe Castaner.
 3 of 39
Protesters warm their hands over a burning tree in a Paris street on January 5.
 4 of 39
A firefighter tries to extinguish a burning car in a street in Paris on January 5.
 5 of 39
Protesters confront police during a "yellow vest" demonstration Saturday, December 22, in central Paris.
 6 of 39
Demonstrators rally in the Montmartre area of Paris on December 22.
 7 of 39
Protesters block a highway near the French border with Spain on December 22 in Biriatou, France.
 8 of 39
Demonstators turn out December 22 near toll booths on the A9 highway in Le Boulou, France.
 9 of 39
Protesters gather December 15 at Place de l'Opera in Paris.
 10 of 39
Activists dressed like Marianne, the symbol of the French Republic, face riot police on December 15 in Paris.
 11 of 39
Demonstrators wearing yellow vests form a human tower December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 12 of 39
A police water cannon sprays demonstrators on December 15 in Paris.
 13 of 39
Protesters take part in a demonstration on December 15 in Paris.
 14 of 39
Demonstrators run through tear gas during scuffles with police December 15 on the Champs-Élysées in Paris.
 15 of 39
Police use tear gas on protesters at the Place de l'Opera in Paris on December 15.
 16 of 39
A protester waves the French national flag during a demonstration on the Champs-Élysées in Paris on December 15.
 17 of 39
French police apprehend a man on December 8 during a protest in Paris.
 18 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests gather on December 8 in front of the Eiffel Tower in Paris.
 19 of 39
Demonstrators drop flat to the ground on the Champs-Elysees avenue during a protest on Saturday, December 8, in Paris. 
 20 of 39
Protesters install a barricade during clashes with police at a demonstration in Paris on December 8.
 21 of 39
Protesters gather on December 8 in Paris.
 22 of 39
A demonstrator is covered in blood after getting in injured during a protest in Paris on December 8.
 23 of 39
Protesters wearing yellow vests walk on the Champs-Elysees Avenue with the Arc de Triomphe in the background during a protest on December 8.
 24 of 39
Two demonstrators dance in front a group as they take part on December 8 in the demonstration at the Arc de Triomphe in Paris.
 25 of 39
A protester reacts during clashes with police on December 8 in Paris.
 26 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester on December 8 in Paris.
 27 of 39
Protesters throw objects at riot police on Saturday, December 1, during a demonstration that turned violent when protestors clashed with police in Paris.
 28 of 39
An injured woman sits on the ground as police officers spray yellow vest protesters with tear gas during a protest in Paris on December 1.
 29 of 39
A burned car is left in the street a day after the  yellow vests demonstration against rising oil prices and living costs in Paris on December 1.
 30 of 39
Firemen work to extinguish a burning car on December 1.
 31 of 39
A demonstrator leaves as water cannons evacuate the Place de l'Etoile on December 1.
 32 of 39
A demonstrator watches a burning car near the Champs-Elysees avenue on December 1.
 33 of 39
Riot police officers stand in position during clashes with demonstrators on December 1.
 34 of 39
Protesters and police clash in downtown Paris on December 1 during a national demonstration.
 35 of 39
Hooded demonstrators smash a car.
 36 of 39
A demonstrator throws a projectile during the December 1 protest.
 37 of 39
A demonstrator treats a wounded man during a protest where police and demonstrators clashed, injuring dozens on December 1.
 38 of 39
French gendarmes apprehend a protester in Paris on December 1.
 39 of 39
The protests were initially conceived in response to rising fuel prices. The cost of diesel has surged 16% this year from an average 1.24 euros ($1.41) per liter to 1.48 euros ($1.69), even hitting 1.53 euros in October, according to UFIP, France's oil industry federation.
The price hike is largely caused by a leap in the wholesale price of oil, with Brent crude oil -- a benchmark for worldwide oil purchases -- increasing by more than 20% in the first half of 2018 from around $60 a barrel to a peak of $86.07 in early October.
Macron has borne the brunt of the demonstrators' anger instead of OPEC for reducing oil production, or the US for imposing tariffs on Iran, which crippled oil exports.
Many protesters are angry with the president for extending the environmental policies that were first implemented by former President François Hollande.
JUST WATCHED
Hundreds arrested in Paris fuel protests
Replay
More Videos ...
MUST WATCH
01:32
President: Tributes to police
The weekend saw the protests in the French capital descend into violence, with buildings cars set alight, and, authorities say, attacks on citizens.
The city's famed Arc de Triomphe -- a flashpoint in Saturday's violent protests -- was also vandalized, scrawled with slogans in support of the yellow vest movement and others criticizing Macron as the President "of the rich."
Upon his return to Paris from the G20 meeting, Macron immediately visited the war monument to "take stock of the damage" and pay tribute to the tomb of the unknown soldier at its base, CNN affiliate BFMTV reported.  He also met with police officers and firefighters who worked to contain the protests.
French President Emmanuel Macron waves as he leaves the Cafe Belloy, near the Arc de Triomphe in Paris on Sunday.
Macron also held an emergency security meeting with top officials on Sunday. In a written statement he paid tribute to law enforcement and rescue teams who "showed unrelenting bravery throughout the day and evening," according to a release from the French Presidency.
The statement also said that Macron "stressed the importance of judicial follow-up so that none of the acts committed remains unpunished."
Macron slams protests after violence erupts
02:15
Arrested rioters to face 'immediate trial'
French Justice Minister Nicole Belloubet said that the unrest was "absolutely unacceptable," but added that she would not yet recommend announcing a state of emergency, stressing that there were "alternatives," without elaborating what else was being considered.
"When there are not only defacements that are absolutely unacceptable in our republic, I think of what happened at the Arc de Triomphe, when there are fires, not only cars -- there have been 55 vehicles burned but also buildings that have been burned, when there are attacks on people, including I think a rape, these are elements that cannot be acceptable in our republic."
Workers clean grafitti off the Arc de Triomphe.
Paris prosecutor Remy Heitz alleged that among the protesters were people from across the country who had descended upon Paris with the express intent of causing trouble. He added that authorities would crack down hardest on those who had joined the street demonstrations explicitly carry out violent acts.
"There are varied profiles but there are definitely profiles of people who have come from the provinces all over France, obviously to carry out acts of violence, and it is to these people that the criminal response I will say will be the strongest."
</doc>
<doc source="CNN" link=">https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/12/europe/paris-bakery-explosion-intl/index.html" date="2019-01-12" labels="europe, Explosion in Paris leaves 4 dead, dozens injured - CNN" title="Explosion in Paris leaves 4 dead, dozens injured - CNN" >
 (CNN)
The body of a woman has been found buried under rubble following an explosion caused by a gas leak in central Paris, bringing the death toll of the disaster to four, a spokesman for the Paris prosecutor told CNN on Sunday.
The blast, which occurred at a bakery at 9 a.m. local time on Saturday, killed two firefighters who were responding reports of the leak, while a Spanish national died hours after the incident in hospital. 
"Profound sadness. Standing by the families of victims. The nation shares in their pain," French Interior Minister Christophe Castaner tweeted after the explosion, adding that 10 people, including a firefighter, were seriously injured and a further 37 were "in a state of relative emergency."
Pictures from the scene, on Rue de Trevise in the 9th arrondissement of the French capital, showed smashed windows and scattered debris across the street, as fire crews evacuated people from apartments above the bakery.
Firefighters intervene after the explosion of a bakery on the corner of the streets Saint-Cecile and Rue de Trevise in central Paris on January 12, 2019.
"At this stage, we can tell the origin of the explosion is accidental, a gas leak, but we should remain prudent as an ongoing investigation will determine the causes of this," Heitz said.
Read More
Castaner, who visited the scene with Prime Minister Edouarde Philippe and the city's mayor Anne Hidalgo, wrote earlier on Twitter that the toll of victims "will be heavy."
Rue de Trévise, aux côtés du Premier ministre, du procureur de Paris, du 
@prefpolice
 et de la Maire de la capitale.
Plus de 200 
@PompiersParis
 sont engagés dans les opérations de secours.
Le bilan s'annonce lourd.
Mes premières pensées vont aux blessés et leurs proches. 
pic.twitter.com/bg8n5bCpi8
— Christophe Castaner (@CCastaner) 
January 12, 2019


More than 200 firefighters were responding to the incident, Castaner wrote. "My first thoughts go to those injured and their loved ones," he added.
The explosion occurred hours before gilets jaunes (yellow vest) protesters 
marched through the city for a ninth successive weekend
, near the street on which the blast occurred. 
Police had earlier advised the public to stay away from the area, and to make space for emergency vehicles.
Gilets jaunes (yellow vest) protesters march through Paris on Saturday, hours after the blast that killed two firefighters.
An injured person is evacuated after the blast.
Firefighters intervene after the explosion.
Fire crews are seen assisting people in apartments surrounding the bakery.
CNN's Saskya Vandoorne and Arnaud Siad contributed to this report.
</doc>
</corpus>