<?xml version="1.0"?>
<corpus>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/30/belgian-police-fire-water-cannons-amid-fuel-price-protests" date="Fri 30 Nov 2018" labels="Belgium, " title="Belgian police fire water cannon at 'yellow vest' protesters | World news | The Guardian" >
Belgian police fired water cannon in central Brussels on Friday to drive back protesters inspired by France’s “yellow vest” movement who hurled rocks and firecrackers near the prime minister’s office.
Police made dozens of arrests and protesters destroyed at least two police vans as what started as a peaceful but unauthorised demonstration, lacking clear leadership and largely promoted on social media, descended into violence when people, many masked or hooded, tried to breach police lines.
For three hours, crowds complaining about fuel prices and a squeeze on living standards had disrupted traffic and walked the streets. Police said they had arrested about 60 people before the violence, mostly for blocking roads or carrying large fireworks.
Several hundred people wearing the fluorescent safety vests drivers must carry in their vehicles eventually converged on the office of prime minister Charles Michel. Some threw rocks, firecrackers and road signs towards police who doused them with high-pressure water jets and fired gas rounds.
The disturbances lasted over an hour before riot police surrounded and then arrested some demonstrators while the rest of the crowd dispersed. Police put the total number of protesters at about 500.
Michel tweeted: “No impunity for unacceptable violence in Brussels. Those who came to smash and loot must be punished.”
Protests in Belgium, notably around fuel depots in the French-speaking south, have been inspired by the yellow vest – or “gilet jaune” – actions in France against increases in fuel duty imposed by President Emmanuel Macron’s government as part of efforts to reduce emissions causing global warming. Those protests have snowballed into wider demonstrations across France over economic hardship.
France’s minister for overseas territories, Annick Girardin, was forced to cut short a meeting with fuel tax demonstrators on the French island of Réunion on Friday after being booed by protesters shouting “Macron, resign!” The Indian Ocean island of around 800,000 people has been brought to a standstill by demonstrations against the fuel duty increases.
In Brussels people chanted “Michel, resign!” on Friday. Michel, a liberal ally of Macron, voiced sympathy for people’s troubles on Thursday, but added: “Money doesn’t fall from the sky.”
His centre-right coalition faces an election in May.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/21/how-hi-vis-yellow-vest-became-symbol-of-protest-beyond-france-gilets-jaunes" date="Fri 21 Dec 2018" labels="Protest, " title="How hi-vis yellow vest became symbol of protest beyond France | World news | The Guardian" >
It started on 10 October, with a Facebook appeal launched by two fed-up truck drivers from the Seine-et-Marne department, east of Paris, calling for a “national blockade” of France’s road network in protest against rising fuel prices.
Within days the campaign had gathered 200,000 backers and spawned hundreds of local spinoffs across the country; two weeks later, a video urging motorists to display their hi-vis yellow vests behind their windscreens in solidarity garnered 4m views.
The gilets jaunes, named after the vest drivers are required to carry in their vehicles, were born, and since 17 November, the movement’s first nationwide day of action, its sustained, sometimes violent protests have rocked France.
But not only France. Mostly leaderless, unstructured and organised on social media, “yellow vest” demonstrations have multiplied internationally, from Belgium to Bulgaria, Serbia to Sweden and Israel to Iraq.
The popular anti-establishment insurrection by France’s squeezed middle, living mostly in rural or deindustrialised areas and small or medium-sized towns far from the globalised cities where the wealth of the 21st century is increasingly concentrated, has found a global echo.
As in France, where it has overwhelming public support, these diverse national movements have brought together people with disparate demands and political views but one overriding and common complaint: they cannot make ends meet.
“If the hike in the price of fuel triggered the yellow vest movement, it was not the root cause,” said the geographer Christophe Guilluy. “The anger runs deeper, the result of an economic and cultural relegation that began in the 80s … Western elites have gradually forgotten a people they no longer see.”
Cheap, readily available, easily identifiable and above all representing an obligation imposed by the state, the the yellow hi-vis vest itself has proved an inspired choice of symbol and has plainly played a big part in the movement’s rapid spread.
“The point, remember, of the yellow vest is to ensure its wearer is visible on the road,” Guilluy said. “And whatever the outcome of this conflict, the gilets jaunes have won in terms of what really counts: the war of cultural representation. Working-class and lower middle-class people are visible again.”
The revolt spread first to French-speaking Belgium, where 400 people have been arrested over the past few weeks as police used teargas and water cannon to disperse crowds pelting them with flares, cobblestones and billiard balls, and setting cars and trucks alight in Brussels, Charleroi, and elsewhere.
Dismissive, like their counterparts in France, of all their country’s established parties, Belgium’s gilets jaunes, who have demanded the resignation of the prime minister, Charles Michel, aim to launch a Mouvement citoyen belge (Belgian citizens’ movement) to compete in next year’s European and Belgian federal elections.
There have been largely peaceful yellow vest protests in half a dozen Dutch cities including Rotterdam, where marcher Ieneke Lambermont said her children had to “pay taxes everywhere, and can’t get housing anymore”. Things were “not going well in Dutch society”, she said. “The social welfare net we grew up with is gone.”
In Italy an anti-austerity, anti-EU protest group inspired by the gilets jaunes has garnered thousands of supporters online and plans a large rally in January, while in Spain Facebook groups of chalecos amarillos plan to begin demonstrating in Madrid in the new year because “it’s worse here than in France”.
Protesters wearing yellow vests have also been seen in Sweden, Greece and the UK, where a group of pro-Brexit campaigners blocked Westminster Bridge and on Wednesday at least two accosted the pro-European Tory MP Anna Soubry outside parliament. In Germany, both the far right and the far left organised yellow-vest protests – separately – in Berlin and Munich.
More than 100 protesters turned up for an anti-government yellow-vest demonstration in Dublin. In Poland yellow-vested farmers blocked the main A2 motorway 20 miles from Warsaw, complaining over a range of grievances.
Protesters wearing yellow vests in Bulgaria, the EU’s poorest member, have blocked major roads including the border crossings with Turkey and Greece, demanding not just cheaper fuel and higher living standards but the departure of a government they likened to “the mafia”.
A civil rights organisation and far-right politicians have adopted yellow vests – for different reasons – in Serbia, while beyond Europe gilets jaunes protests have also occurred in Canada (over the UN migration pact), Israel and Jordan (over corruption and the high cost of living).
In Tunisia, a Facebook group of gilets rouges is complaining about the country’s ailing economy; in Basra, Iraq, gilets jaunes have been protesting against high unemployment, corruption and the terrible general state of the city; and authorities in Egypt are so worried about the movement spreading they have banned sales of yellow vests.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/16/macrons-ratings-fall-further-after-month-of-gilets-jaunes-protests" date="Sun 16 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="Macron's ratings fall further after month of gilets jaunes protests | World news | The Guardian" >
A month of gilets jaunes, or yellow vests, protests have taken a further toll on the popularity of President Emmanuel Macron, a new poll showed on Sunday, with analysts saying he will be forced to change his style of governing.
Around 66,000 protesters turned out again on Saturday on the fifth round of anti-government demonstrations, which sprung up over diesel taxes last month.
The figure was about half the number of the previous weekend, suggesting momentum was waning and the most acute political crisis of Macron’s 19-month presidency was coming to an end.
Around 69,000 security forces were mobilised across France on Saturday, down from 89,000 the weekend before when 2,000 people were detained.
“It is calming down, but what remains of it all is a strong feeling of hatred towards Macron,” said veteran sociologist Herve Le Bras from the School of Advanced Studies in the Social Sciences (EHESS).
A major poll by the Ifop group published in Journal du Dimanche newspaper showed Macron’s approval had slipped another two points in the last month, to 23%. The proportion of people who declared themselves “very dissatisfied” by his leadership jumped by six points to 45%.
Many of the protesters have targeted Macron personally, focusing on his background as an investment banker and alleged elitism, and called on him to resign.
A different poll by Ipsos on Wednesday last week showed that a mere 20% of respondents were happy with his presidency, a fall of six points to its lowest ever level.
Le Bras said the protests had underlined the depth of dislike for Macron’s personality and style of governing, which critics see as arrogant and too distant. “Even by being more humble, it’s going to be complicated,” he added.
Until last week, a clear majority of French people had backed the protests, which sprung up initially over fuel tax hikes before snowballing into a wider opposition front against Macron.
In a bid to end the standoff, Macron announced a package of measures for low-income workers on Monday in a televised address, estimated by economists to cost up to €15bn (£13.5bn).
The 40-year-old also acknowledged widespread animosity towards him and came close to apologising for a series of verbal gaffes seen as dismissive of the poor or jobless. 
The government has announced a six-month consultation with civil society groups, mayors, businesses and the gilets jaunes to discuss tax and other economic reforms.
Hikes in petrol and diesel taxes, as well as tougher emissions controls on old vehicles – justified on the grounds of environmental protection – were what sparked the gilets jaunes movement. 
In Paris on Saturday, the more than 8,000 police on duty easily outnumbered the 2,200 protesters counted by local authorities.
There were 168 arrests by early evening, far fewer than the 1,000 or so of last Saturday.
Tear gas was occasionally fired, but only a fraction compared with the weekends of 8 December or 1 December, when graffiti was daubed on the Arc de Triomphe in scenes that shocked France.
Richard Ferrand, the head of the National Assembly, welcomed the “necessary” weakening of gilets jaunes rallies on Saturday, adding that “there had been a massive response to their demands”.
Christophe Castaner, the interior minister, also called on protesters to halt their blockades across the country which have seen traffic and businesses disrupted.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/27/gilets-jaunes-leader-hit-in-eye-during-protest-will-be-disabled-for-life" date="Sun 27 Jan 2019" labels="France, " title="Gilets jaunes leader hit in eye during protest 'will be disabled for life' | World news | The Guardian" >
A gilets jaunes (yellow vests) demonstrator injured in the eye at a demonstration in Paris will be disabled for life, his lawyer has said.
Jérôme Rodrigues, a high-profile member of the protest movement, claims he was struck by a “flash-ball”, a launcher used by French riot police to fire large rubber pellets. They have been blamed for dozens of injuries, some serious, including the loss of an eye.
Investigators are looking into the incident after police reportedly insisted Rodrigues’s injuries were caused by a crowd-control grenade that exploded near him, a version of events his lawyer “categorically” denied.
Rodrigues was injured at Place de la Bastille on Saturday afternoon, during an 11th weekend of demonstrations by the gilets jaunes in Paris. Witnesses said the police used flash-balls, “sting-ball” crowd dispersal grenades and tear gas while protesters calling for the French president, Emmanuel Macron, to resign threw projectiles at them
There have been calls for French police to be banned from using the flash-ball launchers, and last week the interior minister, Christophe Castaner, ordered officers carrying them to wear body cameras.
Witnesses were reported to have picked up the projectile that struck Rodrigues and handed it to investigators. Internal police investigators have launched an inquiry, as has the Paris prosecutor. More than 80 similar inquiries have been launched following serious injuries or legal complaints during gilets jaunes protests.
Rodrigues’s lawyer, Philippe de Veulle, told BFM television: “He will be disabled for life. It’s a tragedy for him and his family.” De Veulle said he was lodging a complaint against police for “voluntary violence by a person of public authority” because Rodrigues was allegedly struck with one of the 40mm hard rubber projectiles.
On Sunday, Rodrigues, conscious and speaking to LCI television from hospital, said he was also hit by a sting-ball grenade, another controversial riot control tool used to disperse crowds.
“Everything happened very quickly. They threw a grenade at me and I took a [rubber] bullet. I was attacked twice – a grenade to the foot and the bullet,” he said. He accused police of carrying out “all the violence the rules permit”. “I’m going to take legal action against Mr Macron, Mr Castaner and against the police officer who shot at me … I remain firmly pacifist whatever happens.”
A “yellow night” event, organised by protesters at Place de la République in central Paris on Saturday evening, was broken up by police who used tear gas and water cannon.
The gilets jaunes movement started last November in protest over a proposed eco-tax on fuel, but has since grown to embody a wider expression of grievances against Macron and his centrist administration. It is named after the hi-vis vests French motorists must carry in their vehicles, and which the protesters wear.
The interior ministry estimated 69,000 people turned out for “act 11” of the protests across France on Saturday, compared with 84,000 the previous week. Protesters have not provided their own figures. Last week, a leading member of the movement, which has no official leaders or organisation behind it, announced it would field 79 candidates in May’s European parliament elections.
On Sunday, an anti-gilets jaunes event was organised to “defend democracy and (republican) institutions” in Paris. The marchers, calling themselves the “red scarves”, chanted “on a rien cassé” (we’ve not smashed anything). Others shouted “Yes to democracy, no to revolution” as they waved French and European Union flags. They said they were demonstrating against the violence at recent gilets jaunes protests, including attacks on politicians and journalists.
Laurent Soulie, an organiser of the march, said the protesters responded to a call to the “silent majority who have remained holed up at home for 10 weeks.”
Police estimated that despite the rain about 10,500 people turned out. The previous day, 4,000 gilets jaunes protested in Paris, police estimated.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/13/yellow-vests-protesters-fight-for-ideological-ownership" date="Sun 13 Jan 2019" labels="Protest, " title="Yellow vests: protesters fight for ideological ownership | World news | The Guardian" >
What is not in dispute is who came first. On the French side of the channel lie the original gilets jaunes (yellow vests), a grassroots, social media-based citizens’ movement with no formal structure, recognised leader or party or union backing, named after the hi-visibility jackets that French drivers are required by law to carry in their vehicles.
As French yellow vests kicked off their ninth straight weekend of protests against President Emmanuel Macron’s economic policies, a battle for ownership of what has become an symbol of anti-government agitation across Europe has broken out in Britain as leftwing anti-austerity activists donned yellow in a bid to wrestle it from the far-right.
The phenomenon began in France in mid-November to oppose proposed rises in fuel taxes, but has since widened to a range of grievances against Macron (who the demonstrators see as arrogant and out of touch) and his centrist, pro-business government and the establishment in general.
The numbers involved – in France hundreds of thousands have taken to the streets – are the most visible difference between the two countries. In Britain, yellow vest protests have ranged from involving a few dozen – including those who blocked Westminster bridge in December – through to the thousands in London on Saturday who joined an anti-austerity protest addressed by figures including the shadow chancellor, John McDonnell, and which included French jaunes.
Tom Griffiths, an organiser of the People’s Assembly event, said it was not too late for the left to be the dominant force in Britain’s yellow vest movement. He insisted that thousands who rallied in Trafalgar Square – while welcoming both remain and Brexit supporters – vastly outnumbered the hundred who rallied outside St James’s Park tube station under a pro-Brexit banner.
Time to get the Tories Out!! Britain is Broken - General Election Now! Saturday 12 January #GeneralElectionNow #YellowVest #GTTOdetails here:https://t.co/almaRTdyvs pic.twitter.com/YudTVkJixh
But for others such as Mike Stuchbery, a historian and writer who has been monitoring far-right cooption of yellow vests, “the well has already been poisoned” by pro-Brexit and far-right figures such as James Goddard, who was at the centre of controversy over the harassment of MPs and journalists outside parliament. At one point on Saturday, there were clashes in Trafalgar Square between rival yellow vest wearers, with known far-right supporters involved.
As in France, the picture in the UK is muddied by the battle for ideological ownership unfolding on social media platforms including two rival Facebook pages. One, “liked” by more than 2,300 people, is badged around opposing austerity and describes itself as the “official branch of the yellow vests”, while another with 14,000 likes is promoting a “great British betrayal rally” about Brexit and hosts anti-immigration videos.
Causes promoted by some yellow vests have included a campaign mounted by Tracy Blackwell, the mother of one of three teenage boys killed by a hit-and-run driver, along with others including suicide among veterans and child abuse.
In France, protesters’ diverse social and financial demands have ranged from the scrapping of the planned fuel tax increase and a hike in the minimum wage (on both of which Macron has conceded, as well as agreeing to a “great national debate” on their concerns) to increased purchasing power, improved public services, the president’s resignation and more direct democracy.
At root, the movement is a protest by France’s forgotten periphery, many living in rural areas or in small and medium-sized towns far from the cities’ wealth.
Outside the big cities, they have mainly gathered peacefully on roundabouts and at partial roadblocks to air their grievances. In Paris and other urban centres, however, protests have taken the form of Saturday demonstrations.
According to the interior ministry, the protests mobilised 285,000 people across the country on 17 November, the gilets jaunes’ first nationwide day of action, declining steadily to 50,000 last weekend. These are not big numbers for French protests: the mass demonstrations of 1995 against former the prime minister Alain Juppé’s liberal reforms drew more than 2 million.
While dismissive of all established political parties, the movement has attracted the tacit and sometimes overt support of France’s far right and far left. And as often in France, the demonstrations have also attracted not just radicalised supporters of the movement itself, but also violent “casseurs”: extreme rightwing sympathisers, anarchists, vandals and rioters interested mainly in fighting running battles with the police and looting shops.
This explains the sometimes extreme violence seen in the Saturday gilets jaunes protests seen so far, which according to the prime minister, Édouard Philippe, who this week announced measures to crack down on the violence (though not legitimate protest), have so far seen 5,600 people arrested and 1,000 convicted.


</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/dec/03/paris-streets-riots-violence" date="Mon 3 Dec 2018" labels="Opinion, France, " title="Never before have I seen blind anger like this on the streets of Paris | John Lichfield | Opinion | The Guardian" >
France is a republic that was founded in popular violence. Politics runs to the street here more rapidly than in any other western democracy. I’ve lived in France for 22 years and have witnessed street protests by workers, farmers, wine producers, truck drivers, railway employees, university students, sixth-formers, teachers, youths in the multiracial suburbs, chefs, lawyers, doctors and police officers. Yes, even police officers.
I have never seen the kind of wanton destruction that surrounded me on some of the smartest streets of Paris on Saturday – such random, hysterical hatred, directed not just towards the riot police but at shrines to the French republic itself such as the Arc de Triomphe. The 12-hour battle went beyond violent protest, beyond rioting, to the point of insurrection, even civil war.
The centre of Paris has not seen violence on this scale since the student and worker rebellion of May 1968. Much of the worst violence in 1968 came from the police.
And France has not seen widespread destruction of this kind since the riots that burned like a forest fire through almost all the multiracial inner suburbs of French towns and cities in 2005. Then, the violence stopped at the invisible moat that divides the centre of prosperous French cities from their troubled banlieues, or suburban ghettos.
On Saturday, the gilets jaunes – or a large, violent fringe of the wider, peaceful “yellow vest” movement – took evident joy in smashing up the grandest and wealthiest parts of the French capital. Appeals on social media, where the movement began a month ago, are calling for another assault on Paris this weekend.
How can a movement that began a month ago with broadly peaceful protests against high fuel prices have generated such vicious enmity towards not just President Macron but the entire French political system? Some French commentators have suggested that the yellow vests should be rebranded “yellow shirts” – a fascist rabble. This is dangerous and misleading talk, for now.
An extreme wing of the gilets jaunes has turned towards the nihilist detestation of democratic institutions and symbols of success and wealth. But while Saturday’s crowd was mostly white (there are many black and brown gilets jaunes) this movement shows, so far, few outward signs of racism or extreme nationalism. The great bulk of the movement represents genuine economic and social distress in a peripheral and middle France which, with some reason, says that it is despised and fiscally exploited by the country’s thriving cities. Part of the French media suggests that Saturday’s protests were hijacked by ultra-violent sects of the hard right and hard left. This is also misleading.
There were groups of masked, young men among the 5,000 or so people on the Etoile and its radiating avenues but they were a minority. The great majority of the rioters were, by my reckoning, men and some women in their 30s and 40s from suffering rural towns in northern or western France and the hardscrabble outer suburbs of greater Paris. They came dressed and armed for combat.
There are similarities between the insurrection of 2018 and the student rebellion of 1968 – and even similarities between Saturday’s events and the banlieues riots of 2005. All three movements lacked accepted leaders. All three had no clear or broadly agreed political objective or manifesto. But the comparisons should not be pushed too far.
There was a joyous side to the 1968 rebellion. It was a revolt against the ennui of postwar social conservatism as much as capitalism. It was hijacked by the trades unions and then resolved by a general pay rise and the summer holidays. Above all, 1968 was a time of growing prosperity in France. In 2018, part of the country is thriving but much feels abandoned and rejected. The 2005 riots were a shout of anger against police violence and economic deprivation. They were never the religious-political “intifada” decreed by some in the French and foreign media. After exhausting their anger, the very young rioters went back to normal life.
The gilets jaunes do have a series of demands but they are not accepted by all. They range from the abolition of next month’s planned rise in green taxes on petrol and diesel, to a referendum to impeach Macron, to a new constitution in which all laws would be decided by popular vote.
The yellow vests do have informal leaders or spokespeople but they are rejected or disputed or threatened with violence by other gilets jaunes as soon as they emerge. Part of the movement is faux-Maoist in pushing its hatred of politicians to the point of hating any would-be politicians who emerge from their own ranks.
A second attempt by the yellow vests to create a delegation to meet the prime minister, Édouard Philippe, will be made this week. Even if a programme of negotiations emerges, it is unlikely to be accepted by the blindly angry people I saw on the streets of Paris last Saturday. Will Paris burn again? Quite probably.
• John Lichfield is a journalist based in France since 1997. He is the author of Our Man in Paris

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/20/canada-yellow-vest-protests-gilets-jaunes" date="Thu 20 Dec 2018" labels="Canada, " title="Canada spawns its own yellow vest protests – with extra rightwing populism | World news | The Guardian" >
Amid growing concerns over Canada’s ailing domestic oil market, protests have erupted in western parts of the country, where some demonstrators have donned yellow reflective vests inspired by France’s gilets jaunes.
Like their French counterparts, the protesters have organized on Facebook pages, and focused their fury on a federal carbon tax, but their grievances also include stalled pipeline projects, oil sector layoffs, and – for a small minority – the government’s liberal asylum policies.
Canada, the world’s fourth-largest oil exporter, has been hit hard by a recent slump in oil prices, and a lack of pipelines to move its crude to markets.
Some companies have begun to lay workers off, prompting fears of potentially widespread job losses in the oil-rich province of Alberta, where at least 40,000 jobs were lost during the last oil market crash of 2014.
On Wednesday, a convoy of more than 1,000 heavy trucks in Alberta rolled through the town of Nisku, in a show of support for the beleaguered energy sector.
“We are in dire need. Many people that are in the industry have lost their homes, lost their families,” said Chad Miller, founder of Oilfield Dads, a group that helped organize a separate rally of more than 1,500 people in Grande Prairie, Alberta, at the weekend. “The kids feel the anxiety. There’s the roundtable discussions that you have with your wife over bills about what you can pay and what you can’t pay. It’s tough.”
While global crude oil prices rallied over the last year, the cost of Canadian crude has remained low because of oversupply. The Alberta government has said the gap in prices is costing the Canadian economy C$80m ($59m) each day in lost revenues.
This week, the federal government announced a C$1.6bn bailout for oil and gas companies, and the province’s premier, Rachel Notley, has launched a series of measures to contain the crisis, purchasing rail cars to move oil to markets and ordering a rare cut in oil production to rein in oversupply.
But for workers in the resource-rich province, the moves are too little, too late.
Sunday’s protest was motivated by anger over federal energy policies – including the stalled Trans Mountain pipeline and the implementation of a federal carbon tax as part of government’s climate change strategy.
“A lot of people are frustrated about what’s going on in their country,” said Miller.
Some at the rally wore yellow vests: standard safety clothing for workers in the province’s tar sands fields – but also the symbol of the French protests which began as a revolt over an environmental fuel tax and morphed into an anti-establishment movement against low incomes and tax inequality.
Canadian protesters have also called for an end to their country’s carbon tax, but the country’s nascent Yellow Vest groups – a minority in the broader protests – have also embraced rightwing populist causes.
One Facebook group for protesters, Yellow Vests Canada, has amassed nearly 90,000 members since it was created two weeks ago. A description on its main page reads: “This group is to protest the CARBON TAX and the Treason of our country’s politicians who have the audacity to sell out OUR country’s sovereignty over to the Globalist UN and their Tyrannical policies.”
One of the group’s administrators, Josue St-Cyr, said most of its members are in western Canada. “We’re trying to make ourselves heard because obviously nobody’s listening to us,” said St-Cyr, a heavy-equipment operator in the oil sands fields.
Discussions on the group often target Canada’s approval this month of a new UN pact designed to promote cooperation to ensure safe migration between states.
The agreement is not legally binding, and will not change Canada’s migration policies, but it has become the focus for intense criticism from the country’s right.
“I’m not racist. I’m pro-immigration. But let’s do it the right way. Let’s not just open our borders to the UN to bring whoever they want,” said St-Cyr, who said asylum claimants entering Canada were a bigger issue for him than the carbon tax. “It’s up to Canadians to choose how many and who to bring in and make sure that they’re screened.”
Such ideas have been encouraged by mainstream politicians; in recent weeks, the Conservative leader, Andrew Scheer, has repeatedly voiced strong opposition to the pact, falsely warning it would prevent Canada from controlling its borders.
In an interview over the weekend, the prime minister, Justin Trudeau, criticised Scheer for “fearmongering”, saying the Conservative leader was “deliberately and knowingly spreading falsehoods for short-term political gain”.
Outside of Alberta, yellow vest-inspired rallies have begun to appear throughout the country over the last week, but are significantly smaller than their French counterparts.
Nelson Wiseman, a professor of political science at the University of Toronto, said that the largest yellow vest protests so far have been in Alberta’s Conservative electoral strongholds, where there was pre-existing opposition to the current Liberal government.
A recent yellow vest rally in Toronto (population 2.7 million) drew roughly 60 people, and Wiseman was skeptical that the protest movement would take root across Canada.
“When you scratch the surface, it’s very shallow,” he said. “It’s a vehicle for people who are very conservative [and] anti-immigrant – and want to use anything they can against the current government.”

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2018/nov/24/gilets-jaunes-protest-against-macron-policies-in-paris-and-across-france-in-pictures" date="Sat 24 Nov 2018" labels="" title="'Gilets jaunes' protest against Macron policies in Paris and across France – in pictures | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/dec/04/emmanuel-macron-crisis-france-europe-far-right" date="Tue 4 Dec 2018" labels="Opinion, Emmanuel Macron, " title="Macron’s crisis in France is a danger to all of Europe | Natalie Nougayrède | Opinion | The Guardian" >
For Europe’s sake, Emmanuel Macron needs help – not our scorn or hatred. A young, reformist French president who promised a “European renaissance” finds himself struggling at the helm of a country that is fast becoming “the sick man of Europe” again. It was a telling moment last weekend when rioters disfigured the face of a statue of Marianne, the republic’s symbol, at the Arc de Triomphe in Paris. Just three weeks earlier, world leaders had gathered there with Macron for the centenary of the Armistice. If the “sad passions” that Macron has warned of many times take hold in France, an entire continent will be affected – not just one man’s political career.
Extreme forces across Europe are busily rejoicing over Macron’s gilets jaunes predicament. From Britain’s hardline Brexiters (both left and right) to Italy’s far-right strongman Matteo Salvini, not to mention Putin’s propaganda outlets, the relish is unmistakable. Upheaval and chaos in liberal democracies is what they thrive on. The prize the extremists seek is a political takeover of Europe in next May’s European parliament elections. Events in France are ominous, and their significance extends far beyond one country’s borders.
Not long ago, Macron proudly branded himself as the arch enemy of Salvini and Hungary’s Viktor Orbán, two leaders whose trademark policies target migrants, political opponents and the rule of law. Macron is weakened, on the defensive, and ever more isolated.
Scenes in France these past two weeks may seem, to some, like a revival of the May 1968 uprising, but a more pertinent parallel may be 6 February 1934. That day, gangs of far-right nationalists marched on the French capital and clashed with the police in violence that left 15 dead. The events of the day served as a founding myth for that generation of France’s far right.
Macron has certainly made mistakes. Most of the protesters have genuine, if chaotically expressed, grievances. They consider themselves the “invisible” people treated with contempt by Parisian elites, and now they’ve made themselves very visible with their fluorescent vests. Public opinion is behind them.
One of their most eloquent members is Ingrid Levavasseur, a young nurse and single mother of two from Normandy. Last week she spoke movingly on television of her struggle to make ends meet, and of her sense of deep injustice: “Some people complain that we block roads, but they don’t complain when they’re stuck in traffic jams on their way to ski resorts, do they?” she asked softly.
But France’s crisis has more sinister undercurrents, embodied by another gilets jaunes spokesperson, Christophe Chalençon. A blacksmith from the southern Vaucluse region, Chalençon is openly anti-Muslim and has called for a military-led government to be installed – “because a true commander, a general, a strong hand is what we need”. Far-right outfits such as Action Française are meanwhile trying to make a comeback.
Today’s announcement that tax rises would be suspended is probably too little, too late. French anxieties are threefold. There is the fear of losing power and prestige; the fear of the economic impact of globalisation, and the fear of losing a “national identity”. The country also suffers from deep domestic fault lines which one president alone could hardly heal in just eighteen months.
Entire social groups feel pitted against one another: young versus old, unemployed versus employed, rural versus urban, unqualified versus educated. Such divisions exist in many countries, but in France they take on an existential dimension because of the ideal of egalitarianism historically associated with the republic. Many French people feel reality doesn’t reflect what they are entitled to have.
When Macron ran for office in 2017, he promised a “revolution” (it was even the title of his campaign book) to address a widespread need for domestic renewal and a rebooting of French prestige, not least on the European stage. 
Now the president looks paralysed at home, and the last rites could soon be read over his European plans. Just as a weakened Merkel didn’t do much to help Macron in relaunching the European project, a weakened Macron will now provide new fodder for extremists and populists across the continent. The Le Pens, Orbáns and Salvinis are waiting in the wings. If we don’t find solutions, the EU election in France risks becoming a referendum against Macron.
So the gloss has come off the French president as a champion for liberals and pro-Europeans. But to see that as good news for Europe and democracy at large is mind-bogglingly dangerous. It’s like wishing for a train crash so that some carriages can be replaced. Social pains in France are real, and must be addressed. But the forces which stand to gain from collective wreckage and street violence are those that will push us into an abyss. Look at the death threats made to the gilets jaunes who said they were ready to negotiate with the government.
A few years ago an exhausted, tense Italy had its “vaffanculo days” of protests (the message being: “fuck you” to the establishment) from which the populist Five Star movement grew its strength. What’s happened since? This year, Italy has fallen into the grip of the far right. France’s current “vaffanculo days” will lead to a similar scenario if sober-minded people don’t somehow help Macron rebuild a minimum of trust. There can be no European democratic project or social justice without a European democratic France. Marianne’s face must be restored.
•Natalie Nougayrède is a Guardian columnist

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/08/paris-under-siege-gilets-jaunes-open-act-iv-fourth-weekend-protests" date="Sat 8 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="Paris under siege as gilets jaunes open ‘Act IV’ – a fourth weekend of protest | World news | The Guardian" >
Even before the sun had risen on Place de la Bastille, the enduring symbol of the revolution, France’s security forces were taking no chances.
As members of the gilets jaunes (yellow vests) protest movement enjoyed an early morning coffee in a cafe on the square, police and gendarmes deployed. In the middle of a long line of vans filled with CRS riot police was a dark blue VBRG armoured vehicle, often used in military operations abroad – including Kosovo – but rarely in Paris.
The gilets jaunes carried on with their breakfast. “We’re not here to cause trouble,” said one.
The massive windows of a nearby branch of the Banque de France were entirely boarded up, as were other banks, businesses and shops. Some shopkeepers had placed gilets jaunes – the high-visibility vests that all French motorists must keep in their vehicles, and the uniform of the movement – in their windows, as a sign of support and a plea not to smash up the store.
Across the city, the pre-dawn lockdown continued. On what should have been one of the busiest shopping days of the year, a fortnight before Christmas, Paris was eerily quiet. The facades of its celebrated department stores, Galeries Lafayette and Printemps, were dark, their Christmas lights and window decorations turned off and covered with blinds. Dozens of Métro stations were closed and buses cancelled. More than a dozen monuments and museums were closed, including the Eiffel Tower and the Louvre; opera houses cancelled performances. Six Ligue 1 football matches have been cancelled.
On the Champs-Élysées, the gilets jaunes gathered for what their unofficial leaders had described as Act Four of their action, calling for a fourth weekend of demonstrations. A small group tried to prise up paving stones, but they were a minority and were quickly hauled out of the crowd. Most of the demonstrators were content to shout slogans against the president, Emmanuel Macron, wave banners and sing the Marseillaise as they dodged the teargas.
As the day wore on, increasingly violent skirmishes broke out between police and extreme elements of the movement, some reportedly from the far right and far left. On the grands boulevards, a group of men, some dressed in black and wearing masks and scarves, ripped branches from trees and set them alight, and used metal grilles to build a barricade across the street. Police used water cannon to put out the flames and push demonstrators back, forcing them to disperse down side streets.
On the Champs-Élysées, another group ripped off wooden boards from a large store and set them alight. In many cases, plainclothes officers could be seen identifying trouble-makers then diving into the crowd to haul them out and throw them into police vans parked nearby. The first use of teargas came just before 10.30am as police cleared protesters who had been shouting slogans against Macron and singing the Marseillaise from a side street and pushed them back on to the Champs-Élysées.
A group of gilets jaunes attempted to block the Péripherique, Paris’s ring road, west of the city. Outside the capital, 2,000 gilets jaunes demonstrated inthe Mediterranean port of Marseille, and there were protests in Grenoble, Saint-Étienne and in the Belgian capital, Brussels.
Politicians, police and gendarmes were desperate to avoid the running battles, torched buildings and destruction of last Saturday – the worst violence in central Paris for at least 50 years – when they were accused of losing control.
Tactics have changed. Officers stopped and searched anyone and everyone, whether or not they were wearing a yellow vest. They emptied bags, confiscating face masks that could be worn against teargas, helmets, hammers and anything that could be used as a projectile, including baseballs and boules. There were also hundreds of “preventative arrests”. By midday, the interior ministry announced that 548 people had been arrested, 272 of them remanded in custody. On 1 December there had been a total of 412 arrests for the whole day.
A group of gilets jaunes from the Auvergne in central France, who had made the five-and-a-half-hour journey to the capital by coach overnight, seemed lost near the Champs-Élysées, which had been entirely sealed off. “We’re here for many reasons but basically because we’re fed up. Everyone’s fed up. The politicians ask us to make sacrifices while they do nothing,” said one young man.
They insisted the government’s decision last week to drop the tax on fuel was too little too late. Since then, the gilets jaunes have widened their demands to include lower taxes, higher wages and more purchasing power. “The government is wrong if it thinks that the fuel tax is the only problem. The problem is the cost of living, reduced pensions … problems we have to deal with every day.”
Asked if they were afraid the protests would degenerate into violence, one added: “Worried. Not afraid. We know that police have put on yellow vests and smashed things up just to give the gilets jaunes a bad image.”
How did he know? “I saw it on the internet. They were definitely police, smashing things up.”
Far-right and far-left groups have been accused of whipping up the movement with fake news spread via social media.
As Saturday wore on, the government’s decision to deploy 89,000 police and gendarmes across the country, 8,000 in Paris, alongside a dozen VBRG armoured vehicles, appeared to be paying off.
Macron has not spoken publicly about the unrest for three weeks but is expected to make a public statement early this week. Élysée officials suggested the president – the gilets jaunes’ primary target – was anxious not to inflame the situation by speaking before Saturday’s demonstrations.
Macron has not spoken publicly about the unrest for three weeks but is expected to make a public statement early this week. Élysée officials suggested the president – the gilets jaunes’ primary target– was anxious not to inflame the situation by speaking before Saturday’s yesterday’s demonstrations.
In an interview with the Observer, Daniel Cohn-Bendit, one of the leaders of the May 1968 student riots and one of Macron’s friends and advisers, said the president and the government needed a “complete reset …and a tax revolution” to answer protesters’ demands.
“A Pandora’s box has opened out of which has come the deep bitterness of part of France. People say, ‘you’ve given gifts to the rich and gifts to businesses but what happens to those living on pensions of €1,200 a month? You’ve given things to those who already have money and nothing to us’. The government has not succeeded in countering this. Now it’s urgent, there’s a convergence of demands, the cover has come off the box and exploded.”
He said there was something “dangerous … and frightening” about the violence. “There have been many great revolts by the working class in French history. And there’s the mythology of the French Revolution. It’s all part of the genetic culture. But we are now witnessing the kind of extreme violence never seen before,” he said.
“For lycéens to be burning their high schools, for protesters to be trying to set fire to buildings with people inside them … this is terrible. We see that there are some in the gilets jaunes movement who can be very violent, some who are like football hooligans, and some who are disaffected youths from the banlieues. It’s an explosive mix.”
He added: “It would be a pity if this violence destroyed what the movement has achieved, which is to highlight the situation of people at the bottom. The French government’s responsibility is to capitalise on this great show of solidarity and propose negotiations, particularly with the unions. If it’s intelligent, that’s what it will do.”
Having been given directions to the Champs-Élysées, the Auvergne group had one parting shot. “Don’t mix us up with the casseurs [vandals or looters]. They have nothing to do with the real gilets jaunes and we’re not here for that.”
A charter of gilets jaunes’ “suggestions to end this crisis” has been circulating on Facebook. While far from “official” – the movement has no agreed representatives – it does illustrate the diverse, and sometimes contradictory, nature of their demands:
Economy/work A full review of taxation, with no citizen to be taxed at more than 25% of income; an immediate 40% increase in the minimum wage, pensions and benefits; “mass hirings” in the state sector to restore quality of services in hospitals, schools, etc; 5m new homes; make banks “smaller”.
Politics France’s constitution to be rewritten “by the people and for the interests of the people”; lobbying to be banned; France should leave the EU; recover €80bn lost to tax evasion each year; halt and/or reverse all privatisations; removal of “useless” speed cameras; reform of education system, removal of all “ideologies”; quadruple budget of judicial system, which must be simplified, free and accessible for all; break up media monopolies and end cosy relationship between media and the political class; open media up to the people.
Health/environment 10-year guarantee on products to end planned obsolescence; ban plastic bottles; limit power of pharmaceutical companies; ban GM foods, carcinogenic pesticides, monoculture; reindustrialise France to reduce imports and therefore pollution.
Geopolitics Pull France out of Nato and foreign wars; end the plunder of French-speaking Africa; prevent migration flows that cannot be welcomed or integrated given current “civilisational crisis”; scrupulous respect for international law and engagements.• This article was amended on 11 December 2018. The original version incorrectly stated that there were 412 arrests on 2 December. Those arrests actually happened on 1 December. This has been corrected.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/06/italys-deputy-pm-luigi-di-maio-meets-senior-gilets-jaunes-figure" date="Wed 6 Feb 2019" labels="France, " title="France condemns Italy's meeting with gilets jaunes leader | World news | The Guardian" >
France’s foreign ministry has accused the Italian deputy prime minister, Luigi Di Maio, of undermining relations between the two countries after he met with leaders of the gilets jaunes (yellow vests) movement.
Di Maio, who also leads the anti-establishment Five Star Movement (M5S), and Alessandro Di Battista, a prominent M5S member, met Christophe Chalençon, as well as candidates the protest movement has put forward for the European elections in May, on the outskirts of Paris on Tuesday.
Di Maio described the meeting as “beautiful” in a Facebook post. “The wind of change has crossed the Alps,” he wrote. “I repeat. The wind of change has crossed the Alps.”
In response, a French foreign ministry spokesman said in a daily online briefing: “This new provocation is not acceptable between neighbouring countries and partners in the European Union. Mr Di Maio, who holds government responsibilities, must take care not to undermine, through his repeated interferences, our bilateral relations, in the interest of both France and Italy.”
Di Maio had previously expressed his admiration for the gilets jaunes, who have been holding at times violent anti-government protests each week across France for the past few months. He urged the movement not to “give up” and said the demonstrations reminded him of the spirit that gave birth to the M5S in 2009.
On Tuesday he said the two groups shared “many common positions and values that focus on the battles for citizens, social rights, direct democracy and the environment”.
Chalençon said while both sides “practically agree on everything”, there was no talk yet about whether they would form an alliance for the elections to the European parliament. Italian media reported that Ingrid Levavasseur, who heads the gilets jaunes’ list of 10 candidates for the elections, would meet M5S officials again in Rome next week.
The meeting follows a series of verbal attacks from Di Maio and his co-deputy prime minister, Matteo Salvini, on the French president, Emmanuel Macron, in recent weeks and is also seen as an additional tactic by M5S to regain some of the popularity lost to Salvini’s far-right League since the coalition government came to power last June.
“M5S is weak right now,” said Massimiliano Panarari, a politics professor at Luiss University in Rome. “They are losing traction in their traditionally antagonistic contingencies and they need to find every antagonistic issue to demonstrate that they are strong. Macron is also the perfect target for populist movements.”
Panarari said the meeting with the gilets jaunes was also a way to tell Italian voters that M5S still had its “anti-establishment soul”, as well as to attract similar groups with whom they might be able to build a coalition after the EU elections.
M5S launched its European election campaign in January, with Di Maio and Di Battista travelling to the European parliament in Strasbourg and denouncing the institution as a “waste of money”. At the time, Di Maio said he was preparing an election manifesto with other European populist groups.
Opinion polls in France have suggested that the main impact of one or more gilets jaunes parties running in the European elections would be to reduce support for the far-right party of Marine Le Pen and the far left, led by Jean-Luc Mélenchon.
A survey last month by Elabé showed 13% of voters could vote for a gilets jaunes party, knocking three points off the score of Le Pen’s National Rally and 1.5 off that of Mélenchon’s France Unbowed, and extending the lead of Macron’s La République En Marche (LREM).
“A gilets jaunes party would likely mobilise people who do not usually vote, but also take votes from the National Rally and France Unbowed,” Emmanuel Rivière of he pollsters Kantar Public France told Le Monde. “Paradoxically, the principal beneficiary would be the party of the president.”
An Ifop opinion poll published on Wednesday showed Macron’s approval rating surging from 23% in December to 34% in February.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2019/feb/20/thousands-march-in-france-against-rise-in-antisemitism-video" date="Wed 6 Feb 2019" labels="France, " title="Thousands march in France against rise in antisemitism – video report | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/17/gilets-jaunes-grassroots-heroes-or-kremlin-tools" date="Mon 17 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="Gilets jaunes: grassroots heroes or tools of the Kremlin? | World news | The Guardian" >
Russian state television has spent much of the last two weeks playing up the chaos of France’s protests, continuing a trend of coverage that emerged long before troll factories and the modern era of “fake news”.
Seven years ago, the Kremlin-backed TV station Russia Today went all in on coverage of a leftist street protest in the west. Did Occupy Wall Street fit the Kremlin’s interests of showing a western nation in (relative) chaos? Yes. But at that time, few would have suggested that Occupy was anything but a genuine protest movement.
By contrast, at that time it was autocratic governments, like Russia and the monarchies of the Middle East, which suggested that foreign coverage of the Arab spring and the White Ribbon protests of 2011-12 were part of a vast plot from abroad.
Thanks to recent events, specifically the 2016 US election, protests in the west are now treated with wariness, and France is already investigating whether it too has been a victim of Russian disinformation.
Projects that track Kremlin influence abroad, such as the Alliance for Securing Democracy dashboard, listed “#giletsjaunes” as one of the trending terms used by accounts “linked to Russian influence operations”.
The thinktank doesn’t name the accounts it monitors, which makes checking the reports impossible. But in this case it would be hard not to notice Russian media laser-focused on the protests and Russian online trolls doing what they love: trolling.
What similar studies do not measure is the efficacy of Russian messaging. Can fake Facebook groups or flashy RT programming prompt mass protest movements or significantly change voting behaviour abroad?
It is possible that time will come, but there is scant evidence to prove that it has done so already. For the moment, on-the-ground reporting shows that participants in the gilets jaunes (yellow vests) have organic, significant causes for protest that are tied neither closely to Russia or to what they read online.
The gilets jaunes movement is a grassroots citizens’ movement that has no leader or organised structure. The protests began in November against a proposed fuel tax that would have pushed up the price of petrol, affecting many people in rural and suburban areas who depend on cars, having little access to public transport.
On the barricades on roundabouts and at tollbooths in rural and suburban France, gilets jaunes demonstrators said they had joined the protests out of frustration with their struggle to make ends meet.
Although most had organised their protests via local Facebook groups or social media, many said they were protesting because of real difficulties in their lives rather than because of what they had been reading or watching online.
However, the French government has been attentive to foreign leaders trying to jump on the back of the gilets jaunes protests or use them for their own domestic audiences. And Russia has not been the only focus. Donald Trump falsely tweeted on December 8 that French protesters were chanting: “We want Trump!” 
The French foreign minister, Jean Yves le Drian, said on French radio: “I tell Donald Trump – and the French president tells him too – we don’t take part in American debates. Let us live our life as a nation.”
Asked whether Russian tweets may have contributed to protests, he said: “I’ve heard those rumours. An investigation is under way by our secretary general of national defence. We’ll wait for the results.”
Russian television has given significant airtime to suggestions that Moscow is behind the protests, but used it to say the accusations just discredit the west. At the same time, it has also highlighted events that seem to suggest a connection between Russia and what is happening in France.
The Russia-24 state television station aired footage that supposedly showed protesters playing the Russian folk song Kalinka on a piano, which was later shown to be fake.
Sixty Minutes, a hawkish political talkshow, interviewed a French protester who unveiled the flag of a Russian-backed separatist state in east Ukraine during the marches. The hosts urged him to take out the flag again. “This is just a joke,” he said. “But I would like the Kremlin to send me a million dollars.”
But none of that reflects the genuine interests of most French protesters, or indicates that Russian media has done more than jump on a bandwagon.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/06/pamela-anderson-political-activism-is-no-flash-in-the-pan" date="Thu 6 Dec 2018" labels="Activism, " title="Pamela Anderson's political activism – from French riots to broken capitalism | World news | The Guardian" >
Following protests that have taken place in France over the past few weeks and riots that saw hundreds arrested in Paris, the gilets jaunes or yellow vests movement has found a vocal, and to some, surprising supporter in Pamela Anderson.
Earlier this week the Canadian-American actor and activist, who now lives in France, attempted to explain the aim of the movement in a series of tweets and in a blogpost on her website.
Her intervention sparked online appreciation and fury in equal parts as her cogently argued post delved into the complex social issues behind the violence and the rising social movement that is rocking French politics.
But Anderson’s foray into the political issue of the day shouldn’t come as a surprise. For years now she’s been well known for her activism, stretching back to the 90s when she began her work with Peta (People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals).
Among her more notable campaigns for the animal rights group were a 2003 “I’d Rather Go Naked Than Wear Fur” campaign, a protest against Kentucky Fried Chicken and an attempt to stop seal hunting.
“Activism is sexy,” she said once. 
The French protests first began as a response to President Emmanuel Macron’s proposed fuel tax increase, something he has said would help the country’s green initiatives. But they have since encompassed everything from the minimum wage and taxes to demands for the dissolution of parliament and Macron’s resignation.
“I despise violence … but what is the violence of all these people and burned luxurious cars, compared to the structural violence of the French – and global – elites?” Anderson tweeted on Monday.
The photos of the destruction in Paris made for captivating viewing, she said, but it was important to examine what the motivation behind the protests were.
“[It] came from the rising tensions between the metropolitan elite and rural poor, between the politics represented by Macron and the 99% who are fed up with inequality, not only in France, all over the world,” she added.
On her Pamela Anderson Foundation site she further elaborated the following day.
The yellow vest movement, she wrote, “is a revolt that has been simmering in France for years. A revolt by ordinary people against the current political system which – as in many other western countries – colludes with the elite and despises its own citizens.”
Despite what critics of the movement have said, she wrote, the average person in France is not opposed to environmental initiatives, they simply don’t think the burden of paying for it should fall on them while the wealthy are given tax breaks.
“When some protesters destroy cars and burn shops, they symbolically attack private property that is the basis of capitalism. When they attack police officers, they symbolically reject and challenge repressive state forces – forces that primarily protect the capital.”
Some on Twitter were quick to highlight the righteousness of Anderson’s framing of the political situation.
Pamela Anderson has an infinitely more substantive take on what's happening in France than the Wall Street Journal
Pamela Anderson has a Henry Miller quote in her bio and tweeted the best essay on class conflict I've read all year. pic.twitter.com/b9AqmLivjS
Elsewhere many others shared her tweets with a knowing wink at the apparent incongruousness of Anderson, who rose to fame as a Playboy model and Baywatch star, laying out a cogent response to the structural violence of capitalism.
﻿But in fact Anderson has often taken on global events far from the normal purview of a workaday television actor.
In 2013 she travelled to Haiti to distribute aid after the devastating earthquake and has continued to raise funds for relief.
On occasion, Anderson’s work has seen her join forces with some questionable allies. Seal hunting is one cause she shares in common with Vladimir Putin, which has led to rumors of a romantic entanglement with the Russian leader, something she has denied. Anderson has spoken at the Kremlin numerous times about environmental issues, she has said.
The WikiLeaks founder Julian Assange is another controversial figure with whom Anderson has formed a friendship. She has been visiting Assange in the Ecuadorian embassy in London for two years.
Anderson “doesn’t believe there’s a link between Julian and Russia”, she told the Daily Beast, and is adamant Assange “represents everything America does when it comes to true information and freedom of speech”.
The US intelligence community’s findings that Assange worked with Russia to leak Democrats’ emails do not bother her, she told 60 Minutes in Australia.
Anderson has also caused a storm with comments she made on that program about the #MeToo movement and feminism which were criticized heavily as damaging to women’s rights.
“I’m a feminist but I think third-wave feminism can go too far,” she said on 60 Minutes. “I think it paralyzes men. I think this #MeToo movement is a bit too much for me. I’m sorry, I’ll probably get killed for saying that. My mother taught me don’t go to a hotel with a stranger and if someone answers the door in a bathrobe and it’s supposed to be a business meeting, maybe I should go with someone else. I think that some things are just common sense.”
Just don’t tell her you’re surprised to see her getting involved in politics.
“Motherfucker, I’ve been doing this since I fucking came to LA,” she told W magazine last year in response to just such a question.
“I’m an activist, and I’m not doing it for myself,” she said. “I’m doing it for animals and people who are vulnerable and can’t speak for themselves. It was never my intention to get any credit for any of it, and people are just noticing.”

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/05/france-wealth-tax-changes-gilets-jaunes-protests-president-macron" date="Wed 5 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="Macron scraps fuel tax rise in face of gilets jaunes protests | World news | The Guardian" >
The French government has bowed to gilets jaunes (yellow vests) protesters and abandoned the fuel tax rise that has sparked more than three weeks of violence and seen parts of central Paris in flames.
Just a day after announcing a six-month freeze on the eco-tax, the Elysée Palace declared it was dropping the measure from the 2019 budget.
Hours earlier, the prime minister, Édouard Philippe, had said his government was prepared to reconsider the tax if other solutions could be found to make the transition to cleaner fuel without hitting people in their pockets, as he spoke to MPs during a debate on next year’s finance bill in the Assemblée Nationale.
In a statement on Wednesday evening, the Elysée said that Philippe and the president, Emmanuel Macron, “both wished the increase in the carbon tax be removed” from the budget for 2019.
“The citizen and parliamentary debate in the coming weeks and months will have to find solutions and funding that will meet the challenges of the ecological transition; solutions that will preserve the purchasing power of our citizens,” it added.
François de Rugy, the minister for ecological change, told a French TV news channel he had spoken to Macron to confirm that the eco-tax had been “cancelled for the year 2019”.
De Rugy added: “I had the president on the telephone a few minutes ago. He told me: ‘People have the impression there’s some sort of trick, that it has been suspended but it will come back afterwards.’”
However, Macron has ruled out a return of the impôt de solidarité sur la fortune, or solidarity tax on wealth (ISF). The president reportedly told a meeting of the council of ministers on Wednesday: “We’re not going to unpick anything we’ve done in the last 18 months.”
Lifting part of the ISF was a pillar of Macron’s election campaign and one of the first fiscal measures he implemented on taking power in May 2017, leading to his nickname “president of the rich”.
Macron  earlier called on all political, social and business leaders to issue a “clear and explicit” appeal for calm as France faced a new round of the gilets jaunes protests which are threatening to destabilise his presidency.
The gilets jaunes have called for further protests, while hauliers are being urged to strike and farmers have announced plans for demonstrations next week. 
Speaking to the Assemblée National on Wednesday, a government spokesman, Benjamin Griveaux, told MPs: “Emmanuel Macron asks all the political and union organisations as well as business leaders to issue a clear and explicit appeal for calm.”
Griveaux added: “What we are living through is no longer political opposition, but opposition to the republic.”
The government was forced into a change of direction after last Saturday’s scenes of running clashes with police, torched cars and buildings, and smashed shop fronts in one of Paris’s most exclusive areas, as well as damage to the Arc de Triomphe in a third week of protests.
Before Wednesday evening’s announcement that the eco-tax rise was being abandoned, representatives of the gilets jaunes movement, which has no official organisation or leadership, dismissed the government’s concessions as too little too late.
Various gilets jaunes organisers have called for wider social reforms, including a rise in the minimum wage and higher taxes on international companies such as Google and Amazon.
Easing the ISF for the wealthy was described by one political commentator as Macron’s “original sin” and has been regarded as socially divisive at a time when French workers have felt increasingly squeezed financially.
The ISF was imposed on those worth more than €1.3m (£1.2m) including their main residence. It has been replaced by the impôt sur la fortune immobilière (ISI), which in effect lifted or reduced the tax on certain properties, share portfolios and life assurances.
Last year, Philippe said the move would make the country more attractive to investors and stop wealthy people leaving France. The ISI came into effect in January and Griveaux has said it will take 18 to 24 months to see if it brings in more revenue.
The gilets jaunes have been calling for another day of action on Saturday while trying to organise some kind of popular leadership. Previous attempts have led to threats being made against protesters putting themselves forward to give media interviews or meet elected representatives.
André Lannée suggested organising Facebook referendums to elect two gilets jaunes representatives for every region.Once elected, he said, the group could then propose new legislation.
“We will arrive at the Elysée with a demand. It will be an official delegation, legitimate as it has been elected by popular referenda. We are not going to smash anything up, there is no interest in smashing up our country.” He concluded: “We let nothing go; we continue.”
Across the country, protests and blockades by high school students opposed to plans to introduce criteria for university entrance – at present it is open to anyone with a baccalauréat pass – added to the air of crisis and insurrection in France.
The Chamber of Commerce and Industry claimed 142 shops and businesses had been seriously damaged by last Saturday’s clashes in central Paris. An additional 95 were less seriously damaged.
France’s main unions are planning a joint meeting on Thursday and transport leaders are to meet the government minister Élisabeth Borne after calls for a hauliers’ strike from next Sunday. 
Blockages at petrol refineries have led to fuel shortages in certain regions and gilets jaunes continue to block a number of refineries, roads and commercial centres.
Recent polls reflect conflicting findings: an IFOP survey found 72% of people in France support the gilets jaunes movement but not the violence. Another poll by BVA found 70% of people thought the freeze in the fuel tax rises should mean the end of the protests.
An IFOP poll showed Macron’s popularity had dropped to a new low of 23%. 

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/03/who-are-the-gilets-jaunes-and-what-do-they-want" date="Fri 7 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="Who are the gilets jaunes and what do they want? | World news | The Guardian" >
A grassroots citizens’ protest movement began in early November against a planned rise in the tax on diesel and petrol, which Emmanuel Macron insisted would aid the country’s transition to green energy. A poll at the time found that the price of fuel had become France’s biggest talking point.
The movement was named “gilets jaunes” (yellow vests) because protesters wear the fluorescent yellow high-vis jackets that all motorists must by law carry in their cars. But what began as a fuel tax protest has now morphed into a wider anti-government movement.
We’d like to hear your experiences and reaction to the gilets jaunes demonstrations. Do you support them? How do you feel about the rioting that has taken place? If you have taken part, we’d also like to hear from you.
You can get in touch by filling in this encrypted form.
Your responses will only be seen by the Guardian and we’ll be in touch if we are considering your response as part of our reporting. You can read terms of service here.
Unlike previous French protest movements, it sprang up online through petitions and was organised by ordinary working people posting videos on social media, without a set leader, trade union or political party behind it.
A first national day of protests was held across France on Saturday 17 November and the protests have continued daily, including roadblocks, barricades of roundabouts and the blockading of fuel depots.
The French interior ministry says the total number of people demonstrating has dropped since its peak on 17 November, when about 285,000 people demonstrated across France. On 1 December, two weeks after the first protests, the interior ministry said that at 3pm 75,000 people were on the streets. It is thought that about 100,000 in total demonstrated in France throughout the day.
However, violence has escalated at the weekly Paris protests held on Saturdays. While thousands demonstrated peacefully on 1 December, about 3,000 people fought running battles with police, burned more than 100 cars, set fire to several buildings and smashed bank windows and shopfronts on some of the most expensive streets in the capital.
Authorities blamed extreme-right and extreme-left “professional” rioters for infiltrating the peaceful demonstrations. The Paris prosecutor said a majority of the more than 300 people in police custody after the Paris violence were men aged between 30 and 40 who “had come to fight police while also claiming to be part of the gilets jaunes movement”.
There were also violent clashes with police in Toulouse. In Le Puy-en-Velay, the local prefect’s office was petrol-bombed and briefly caught fire.
Gilets jaunes protesters in other regions continue to stage roadblocks, and some fuel depots have been blocked in the north-west. Some high-school students have also now joined the movement and barricaded schools.
A poll for Harris Interactive conducted after the violence on 1 December in Paris found 72% of French people continued to support the gilets jaunes but 85% said they disagreed with the violence in Paris.
Protesters have largely come from peripheral towns, cities and rural areas across France and include many women and single mothers. Most of the protesters have jobs, including as secretaries, IT workers, factory workers, delivery workers and care workers. All say their low incomes mean they cannot make ends meet at the end of the month.
The movement is predominantly against a tax system perceived as unfair and unjust, but there are numerous grievances and differences of opinion. Most want to scrap the fuel taxes, hold a review of the tax system, raise the minimum wage and roll back Macron’s tax cuts for the wealthy and his pro-business economic programme. But some also want parliament dissolved and Macron to resign.
This is the first big crisis of Macron’s presidency. The 40-year-old pro-business, pro-Europe centrist has staked his political identity on insisting he would never give in to street protests. But polls suggest he is seen as not listening to the concerns of ordinary working people on low incomes, and he is under pressure to make concessions.
It is damaging that Macron – whose own fledgling political movement, La République En Marche, was styled as a grassroots movement to listen to the people – was taken by surprise by this sudden tax revolt. Although Macron beat the far-right Marine Le Pen in last year’s presidential election, the mood of distrust of the political class never went away.
The first 18 months of Macron’s presidency were defined by his drive for businesses to become more competitive; he cut taxes on companies and transformed France’s wealth tax, easing the tax burden on the very wealthy.
He is now under pressure to consider the gilets jaunes’ demands, and to that end the government executed a U-turn on 5 December when it scrapped the fuel tax rise, one day after announcing a six-month freeze on the policy.
AnalysisWarnings of latest crisis facing Macron were in plain sightAre the French hit especially hard by fuel taxes?
OpinionNever before have I seen blind anger like this on the streets of ParisFrance is deeply fractured. Gilets jaunes are just a symptom


</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2019/jan/09/top-pro-brexit-yellow-vest-activist-said-all-muslims-should-be-removed-from-uk" date="Wed 9 Jan 2019" labels="House of Commons, " title="Pro-Brexit activist said all Muslims should be removed from UK | Politics | The Guardian" >
The most prominent of the protesters who have harassed MPs and journalists outside the Houses of Parliament in recent weeks argued last year that all Muslims should be removed from the UK, saying he wanted to “ban Islam from the west”, it has emerged.
In another indication of the far-right views held by several of the self-styled yellow vest activists stationed outside parliament, ostensibly to call for Brexit, a video exists of James Goddard arguing that Islam should be removed from the UK.
Goddard, who has regularly filmed himself and other activists harassing and abusing people including the Conservative MP Anna Soubry, has built up his profile by live-streaming confrontations to Facebook and seeking donations to finance his actions.
However, following calls from the Speaker, John Bercow, as well as from more than 100 MPs for a stronger response from the police after a group including Goddard barracked Soubry as she walked to parliament, his Facebook and Paypal pages were removed.
Goddard’s page on the mass-funding website Patreon, on which he styled himself a “political activist” and sought donations, has also been suspended.
The video, uploaded in September, shows Goddard engaged in a long debate about Islam with Jaffer Ladak, the imam of a mosque in Stanmore, north London.
During the conversation, Goddard said that the estimated 2,000 mosques around the UK “shouldn’t be there” and he would “get rid of them”.
Asked what this meant in practice, Goddard said: “I wouldn’t blow them up. If I ever got into power I’d give you all £5,000 to £10,000 and ask you to leave. I don’t believe that Islam should be in the west, no. This is a Christian country.”
If Muslims refused to leave voluntarily, “then we’d have to think of a legal way that we could do it”, he said.
Goddard said he wanted to “ban Islam from the west”, calling the faith “a threat to every man, woman and child in this country”. He added: “I just don’t think that Islam is compatible with the west. I just don’t think that people who believe in child marriage and terrorism should be in the United Kingdom, or Europe for that matter. That book poses a threat, and as long as that book exists there will never be peace in the west.”
Goddard has previously posted anti-Islam statements on Gab, a social media site popular with the far right, and has supported Tommy Robinson, whose real name is Stephen Yaxley-Lennon, the founder of the English Defence League street movement.
Other yellow vest activists outside the Houses of Parliament, who model their tactics on the French gilets jaunes movement, have said they do not share such views, and insist Goddard is not a leader of the group.
However, the group Hope Not Hate has said that the emergence of the movement raises fears that amid the Brexit process, “the threat from the far right is growing and the risk of disorder and violence is on the rise”.
In recent weeks, members of the group outside parliament have also blocked Westminster Bridge, shouted sometimes sexist and racist abuse at TV crews, stormed into the offices of a radio station and the Labour party, and held small demonstrations in a number of cities.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/11/egypt-bans-sale-of-gilets-jaunes-yellow-vests-in-fear-copycat-protests" date="Tue 11 Dec 2018" labels="Egypt, " title="Egypt bans sale of yellow vests in fear of gilets jaunes copycat protests | World news | The Guardian" >
Egyptian authorities restricted the sale of yellow reflective vests amid fears opponents might attempt to copy French gilets jaunes protesters during next month’s anniversary of the 2011 uprising that toppled  Hosni Mubarak.
Security officials and retailers said industrial safety equipment dealers have been instructed not to sell yellow vests to walk-in buyers and to restrict business to wholesale to verified companies, but only after securing police permission. They were told offenders would be punished, the officials said without elaborating.
Six retailers in a Cairo downtown area where industrial safety stores are concentrated said they were no longer selling yellow vests. Two declined to sell them, giving no explanation, but the remaining four said they were told not to by police.
“They seem not to want anyone to do what they are doing in France,” said one retailer.
“The police came here a few days back and told us to stop selling them. When we asked why, they said they were acting on instructions,” said another. 
Both spoke on condition of anonymity for fear of reprisals.
Security officials said the restrictions would remain in force until the end of January. They said industrial safety product importers and wholesale merchants had been summoned to a meeting with senior police officers in Cairo this week and informed of the rules.
The officials, who have first-hand knowledge of the measures, spoke on condition of anonymity because they were not authorised to brief the media. Repeated calls and messages to the spokesman of the interior ministry, which oversees the police, to seek comment went unanswered.
The move showcases the depth of the government’s concern with security. Egyptian authorities have clamped down heavily over the past two years, deploying police and soldiers across the country to prevent marches to commemorate the 25 January anniversary of the start of the 2011 uprising. Scores of people have been killed and wounded in clashes during previous anniversaries.
The yellow vests worn by French protesters have become the symbol of the wave of demonstrations that began in November against a rise in fuel taxes but mushroomed to include a range of demands, including the resignation of President Emmanuel Macron.  

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2018/dec/02/the-aftermath-of-the-gilets-jaunes-riots-in-paris-in-pictures" date="Sun 2 Dec 2018" labels="" title="The aftermath of the gilets jaunes riots in Paris – in pictures | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/dec/02/france-is-deeply-fractured-gilets-jeunes-just-a-symptom" date="Sun 2 Dec 2018" labels="Opinion, France, " title="France is deeply fractured. Gilets jaunes are just a symptom | Christophe Guilluy | Opinion | The Guardian" >
From the 1980s onwards, it was clear there was a price to be paid for western societies adapting to a new economic model and that price was sacrificing the European and American working class. No one thought the fallout would hit the bedrock of the lower-middle class, too. It’s obvious now, however, that the new model not only weakened the fringes of the proletariat but society as a whole.
The paradox is this is not a result of the failure of the globalised economic model but of its success. In recent decades, the French economy, like the European and US economies, has continued to create wealth. We are thus, on average, richer. The problem is at the same time unemployment, insecurity and poverty have also increased. The central question, therefore, is not whether a globalised economy is efficient, but what to do with this model when it fails to create and nurture a coherent society?
In France, as in all western countries, we have gone in a few decades from a system that economically, politically and culturally integrates the majority into an unequal society that, by creating ever more wealth, benefits only the already wealthy.
The change is not down to a conspiracy, a wish to cast aside the poor, but to a model where employment is increasingly polarised. This comes with a new social geography: employment and wealth have become more and more concentrated in the big cities. The deindustrialised regions, rural areas, small and medium-size towns are less and less dynamic. But it is in these places – in “peripheral France” (one could also talk of peripheral America or peripheral Britain) – that many working-class people live. Thus, for the first time, “workers” no longer live in areas where employment is created, giving rise to a social and cultural shock.
'Workers' no longer live in areas where employment is created, giving rise to a social and cultural shock
It is in this France périphérique that the gilets jaunes movement was born. It is also in these peripheral regions that the western populist wave has its source. Peripheral America brought Trump to the White House. Peripheral Italy – mezzogiorno, rural areas and small northern industrial towns – is the source of its populist wave. This protest is carried out by the classes who, in days gone by, were once the key reference point for a political and intellectual world that has forgotten them.
So if the hike in the price of fuel triggered the yellow vest movement, it was not the root cause. The anger runs deeper, the result of an economic and cultural relegation that began in the 80s. At the same time, economic and land logics have locked up the elite world. This confinement is not only geographical but also intellectual. The globalised metropolises are the new citadels of the 21st century – rich and unequal, where even the former lower-middle class no longer has a place. Instead, large global cities work on a dual dynamic: gentrification and immigration. This is the paradox: the open society results in a world increasingly closed to the majority of working people.
The economic divide between peripheral France and the metropolises illustrates the separation of an elite and its popular hinterland. Western elites have gradually forgotten a people they no longer see. The impact of the gilets jaunes, and their support in public opinion (eight out of 10 French people approve of their actions), has amazed politicians, trade unions and academics, as if they have discovered a new tribe in the Amazon. 
The point, remember, of the gilet jaune is to ensure its wearer is visible on the road. And whatever the outcome of this conflict, the gilets jaunes have won in terms of what really counts: the war of cultural representation. Working-class and lower middle-class people are visible again and, alongside them, the places where they live.
Their need in the first instance is to be respected, to no longer be thought of as “deplorable”. Michael Sandel is right when he points out the inability of the elites to take the aspirations of the poorest seriously. These aspirations are simple: the preservation of their social and cultural capital and work. For this to be successful we must end the elite “secession” and adapt the political offers of left and right to their demands. This cultural revolution is a democratic and societal imperative – no system can remain if it does not integrate the majority of its poorest citizens.
Christophe Guilluy is the author of Twilight of the Elites: Prosperity, Periphery and the Future of France

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/global/video/2018/dec/11/macron-offers-concessions-amid-violent-protests-video" date="Sun 2 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="'This was a long time coming': Macron offers concessions amid violent protests – video | Global | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2018/dec/07/french-high-school-students-made-to-kneel-with-hands-on-heads-by-police-video" date="Sun 2 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="French high school students made to kneel with hands on heads by police – video | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/31/authoritarian-anti-protest-gilets-jaunes-measures-draw-criticism-in-france" date="Thu 31 Jan 2019" labels="France, " title="French MPs condemn 'authoritarian' plans to curtail gilets jaunes protests | World news | The Guardian" >
French politicians have approved controversial measures to ban what the government calls “brute” troublemakers from street demonstrations as gilets jaunes (yellow vests) anti-government protests enter their 12th week.
There were tense and heated exchanges in parliament late on Wednesday night, including from rebels within Emmanuel Macron’s own centrist party, as deputies backed giving regional prefects – local state security officials – the power to ban people presumed to be violent from taking part in demonstrations.
Deputies on the left and some on the centre said the measures posed an “authoritarian” threat to civil liberties.
The most controversial measure in the bill – which angered some rebels in the French president’s party – means that individuals deemed to represent a “particularly serious” threat to public order will be prevented from taking part in street protests. Their names will be added to a special police file. Any person presumed to have been involved in violence in previous demonstrations can be banned from street protests, but they don’t need to have been previously convicted. Regional prefects, rather than judges, will have new powers to impose the ban.
There will also be a new crime of covering your face during a street demonstration – whether with a helmet, mask or scarf – punishable by a fine of €15,000 (£13,117) or a prison sentence.
The measures are an attempt by the government to crack down on violence on the edges of gilets jaunes demonstrations in cities such as Paris and Bordeaux, in which cars and shops were smashed and torched, monuments like the Arc de Triomphe vandalised and police attacked.
But some MPs, even within the ruling La République En Marche party, warned the law threatened people’s constitutional right to demonstrate in the street. “Who are we to protect the state of law if we’re weakening its essential and fundamental principles?” asked one MP from Macron’s party.
Some politicians said the new law could be abused if a far-right party came to power in the future.
Charles de Courson, from the centrist UDI party, told parliament the law was extremely dangerous. He said: “It’s as if we’re back under the Vichy regime [the Nazi-collaborationist regime of the 1940s]. You’re presumed to be a résistant so we throw you in prison. Wake up! Wake up, colleagues! … The day you have a different government in power – a far-right government – and you’re in opposition, you’ll see that it’s pure madness to vote for this text.”
Macron’s interior minister, Christophe Castaner, argued that “a small minority of brutes” were “threatening, targeting and attacking” during demonstrations and they had “a thirst for chaos” that must be stopped.
The full law will be voted on in parliament next week.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/12/police-use-water-cannon-and-teargas-on-paris-protesters-gilets-jaunes" date="Sat 12 Jan 2019" labels="Paris, " title="Police use water cannon and teargas on Paris protesters | World news | The Guardian" >
Gilets jaunes protesters engaged in a ninth weekend of protests all over France on Saturday as the president, Emmanuel Macron, prepared to stake his political future on an open letter to the French people and a national debate.
Officials said that at least 84,000 demonstrators turned out across France, thousands more than last weekend, with about 8,000 of those in Paris where protests passed “without serious incident”. Gilets jaunes – named after the hi-vis yellow vests French motorists must carry in their vehicles – said the number was higher but did not give a figure.
After the violence of previous weeks, the government put on a show of strength, deploying 80,000 police officers nationwide and about 7,000 in Paris.
As night fell, security forces used teargas and water cannon against gilets jaunes at the Arc de Triomphe.
In Bourges, a town of 66,000 people – chosen because of its central location – about 6,700 gilets jaunes gathered despite a ban on protests in its historical centre.
There were 4,500 gilets jaunes demonstrators at Bordeaux and 5,500 in Toulouse, according to officials.
Police said 156 people were arrested in Paris, 108 of whom were remanded in custody. Nationwide, 244 people were arrested, of whom 201 remained in custody.
The latest opinion polls showed a slight reduction in the high level of public support for the gilets jaunes following last weekend’s violence, and a slight increase in popularity for Macron, whose approval rating remains at a low of 30%.
Bruno Cautrès, of the elite Sciences Po political research unit CEVIPOF, said the gilets jaunes movement was at a “crossroads”.
“We are beginning to see in our research that the question of violence will polarise the movement between those, like members of the France Insoumise [far left] and the Rassemblement Nationale [far right], who feel this violence might be justified and others who feel it’s gone too far.
“Having said that the level of support for the gilets jaunes remains high.”
The gilets jaunes movement began in November as a protest against a new eco-tax on petrol and diesel. Although the government dropped the tax and made certain concessions to protesters, the movement has grown to encompass a wide range of demands, including giving people a greater say in policy via citizens’ referenda.
Macron has attempted to take the sting out of the protests by announcing a “great national debate” to sound out the public on four themes: taxation, state institutions, democracy and citizenship, but just days before the consultation is due to begin on Tuesday, there is still confusion over how it will be carried out.
The president will publish an open letter to the French people on Monday to “explain what I intend to do”. He said the debate was “a vital and very useful moment for our country”.
“It’s a great opportunity and everyone must take it … I want a real debate,” he said.
Cautrès added: “There is a situation of extreme tension and frustration in the country. Our research shows an rejection of politics, politicians and political parties to the point of disgust and distrust. The level of this is really incredible.
“At the moment we don’t know the position Macron will take: will it be, ‘I have heard the people but I’m continuing my reforms’, or ‘I have heard the people and will adapt my programme’? That’s the unknown element,” Cautrès said.
“If he and the government can show it is taking people’s hopes and views into account it might be one positive thing to come out of this and lighten the very dark place that France is in right now.”
Eddy Fougier, a political researcher with the French Institute for International and Strategic Affairs, said the national debate was the government’s only option for “getting out of this crisis”. 

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2019/jan/05/girl-13-arrested-in-london-yellow-vest-brexit-protest" date="Sat 5 Jan 2019" labels="UK news, " title="Girl, 13, arrested in London 'yellow-vest' pro-Brexit protest | UK news | The Guardian" >
A 13-year-old girl has been arrested on suspicion of assaulting a police officer after protesters emulating the gilets jaunes demonstrations in France blockaded Westminster Bridge and stopped traffic around parliament.
She was one of four suspects arrested for taking part in the demonstration, which had apparently not been arranged in advance with police. The others detained were all men arrested for alleged public order offences.
According to reports, about 100 demonstrators took part in the protest, which began at 11am on Saturday with a blockade of Westminster Bridge. They moved on to Parliament Square, where they set off smoke bombs and sat in the roads.
The disruption caused tailbacks and diversions, according to Transport for London, which said buses serving the area had been delayed and subsequently diverted.
The Metropolitan police’s Westminster division reported the arrests on its Twitter feed. It said: “Four arrests have been made following protests on Westminster Bridge, SW1 at approximately 11am today. Three men arrested on suspicion of public order offences.
“A 13-year-old girl was also arrested on suspicion of assault on police. Inquiries continue.”
According to a call to action circulated on social media, protesters met at 10.30am at Waterloo station before marching on Westminster bridge. Photos and video showed several dozen dressed in high-visibility vests blocking the bridge, waving union flags and burning an EU flag.
“No to globalists; yes to free freedom,” one man shouts in the footage shared on Periscope, before the group collectively raise their voices in a song of “bye bye EU”, to the tune of Auld Lang Syne.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2018/nov/17/its-macrons-fault-parts-of-france-in-gridlock-as-thousands-protest-fuel-tax-hikes-video" date="Sat 5 Jan 2019" labels="France, " title="'It's Macron's fault': parts of France in gridlock as thousands protest fuel tax hikes - video | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2019/mar/07/my-hand-was-hanging-from-my-wrist-gilets-jaunes-protesters-mutilated-by-police-weapons" date="Sat 5 Jan 2019" labels="France, " title="'My hand was hanging from my wrist': gilets jaunes protesters mutilated by police weapons | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/08/the-police-are-after-all-of-us-pro-brexit-protesters-ditch-yellow-vests" date="Tue 8 Jan 2019" labels="Brexit, " title="'The police are after all of us': pro-Brexit protesters ditch yellow vests | Politics | The Guardian" >
Such was the official fuss after “yellow vest” protesters harassed and verbally abused Anna Soubry outside parliament, that a day later the few activists who had turned up again were being so low key they had not even donned their trademark garments.
“They’re in that bag,” said one man, who like all those present declined to be identified. “We’ll put them on when there’s more of us. The police are after all of us, so we’ve got to be careful.”
With police having promised to respond to any future incidents, six police vans were parked opposite parliament and officers greatly outnumbered the men, some of whom identified themselves instead with union flag bobble hats.
The outcry has followed weeks of intermittent action by a small, varying and semi-organised group, primarily men, who have borrowed the outfit and the tactics of France’s much larger gilets jaunes movement to barrack MPs and journalists seen as opposing Brexit.
In recent weeks they have also blocked Westminster Bridge, shouted sometimes sexist and racist abuse at TV crews, stormed into the offices of a radio station and the Labour party, and held small demonstrations in a series of cities.
The most visible figure throughout has been James Goddard, a self-styled “political activist” with close links to the far right and a background in making anti-Muslim comments, who solicits public donations to continue his activities.
Goddard, who filmed an earlier targeting of Soubry in December in which he and a group of men called the Conservative MP a traitor and “on the side of Adolf Hitler”, has routinely promoted himself by live-streaming his confrontations on Facebook.
However, both of his Facebook pages disappeared on Tuesday – Goddard tweeted that the company had “silenced” him – and a link to his PayPal donations page also stopped working. He did not appear outside parliament and one of his fellow protesters said Goddard feared being arrested.
The man said of Goddard: “He turned up about nine months ago. He’s a new kid in town, a normal, working-class boy. Passionate. They claim he’s our leader. But he’s not our leader. There’s no leader.”
According to the men, Goddard started his protests, like several other “yellow vest” members, in response to a conspiracy theory popular with anti-Muslim activists, connected to a case in which three teenage boys were killed by a driver in west London.
The driver, Jaynesh Chudasama, was found to have been speeding, drunk, and under the influence of cannabis when he ran the boys over in January last year, and was jailed for 13 years.
However, Goddard and other activists have claimed, without evidence, that the deaths were a terrorist attack covered up by police. He was among a group who disrupted a court hearing in the case in December.
Much like their French counterparts, the UK yellow vest group are somewhat opaque about their aims beyond securing Brexit. “I’ve never been a member of any political party. It’s about justice,” one said.
Another said he was uncomfortable about the incident on Monday in which Soubry was shouted at and abused as she walked back to parliament after a TV interview nearby.
“It was a bit over the top, if you ask me,” the man said. “All her ‘I was being prevented from entering parliament’ isn’t true. But if I was her I wouldn’t be happy with that sort of treatment. She was treated very harshly.”
On Tuesday evening, police on the parliamentary estate arrested a man as he tried to gain entry to the Palace of Westminster via Carriage Gates.
Scotland Yard was not treating the incident, which happened at about 7.20pm, as terror-related. The man, who has not been named, was taken to a police station.
The group Hope Not Hate, which monitors far-right activity, has alleged that the UK yellow vest protesters are linked to a new far-right group called the Liberty Defenders, which is supported by Nick Griffin, the former leader of the British National party.
Hope Not Hate said activists were planning protests this weekend in Cardiff, Birmingham, Manchester and Leeds, and were thinking about targeting the offices of remain-voting Labour MPs.
Nick Lowles, the head of Hope Not Hate, said that amid the Brexit process, “the threat from the far right is growing and the risk of disorder and violence is on the rise”.
He said: “The British far right are attempting to copy the French ‘yellow vests’ protests in order to stir up trouble and harass, threaten and attack their political opponents.”
While the protesters insist they were not linked to such views, Goddard in particular has been associated with the anti-Muslim activist Tommy Robinson, whose real name is Stephen Yaxley-Lennon, and shares similar views. Last year he spoke at a rally calling for the then-jailed Robinson to be freed from a prison sentence for contempt of court.
Last June Goddard shared a picture on Twitter of himself posing with the leader of Ukip, Gerard Batten, who in November appointed Robinson as an adviser.
A pleasure meeting you @GerardBattenMEP #FreeTommy pic.twitter.com/HqtZPyiRAB
Goddard has posted anti-Muslim messages on the social media site Gab, which is popular with far-right users. In one message he said: “Wherever Islam exists you will find murder and rape.”
In a video posted last year by Goddard he filmed himself castigating a young woman taking part in a pro-Palestine demonstration. When told to go away, he responded: “Educate yourself, love. I bet you’re a feminist as well, aren’t you? Sort yourself out, you mug.”

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2019/jan/12/ninth-weekend-of-gilets-jaunes-protests-sees-police-use-water-cannon-in-paris-video" date="Tue 8 Jan 2019" labels="Paris, " title="Ninth weekend of gilets jaunes protests sees police use water cannon in Paris – video | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/29/dutch-yellow-vest-protest-broken-up-by-mounted-police" date="Sat 29 Dec 2018" labels="Netherlands, " title="Dutch 'yellow vest' protest broken up by mounted police | World news | The Guardian" >
Dutch police on horseback broke up a protest on Saturday by “yellow vest” demonstrators who threw rocks and fireworks at them, a statement said.
The police statement said the mounted officers “carried out several charges” to end the demonstration in The Hague, which had not been approved by authorities and had turned violent. Eight protesters were detained for disturbing the peace after clashing with police.
Around 150-200 demonstrators took part in the protest march near government offices, wearing the hi-vis jackets also worn by anti-government protesters in France.
Dutch TV showed footage of the protesters in front of parliament waving Dutch flags, shouting anti-government slogans and later trying to break through a police cordon. Several mounted police and dozens of officers on foot could be seen. No one sustained any injuries, police said.
In France, meanwhile, demonstrators kept numerous roads across the country blocked on Saturday as groups of protesters gathered in city centres, but the anti-government backlash was more muted than in previous weeks.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2018/dec/23/police-probe-far-right-yellow-vest-group-anna-soubry" date="Sun 23 Dec 2018" labels="Brexit, " title="Police probe far-right ‘yellow vest’ group that intimidated Anna Soubry | Politics | The Guardian" >
Police are investigating a group of far-right members of the UK’s embryonic “yellow-vest” movement who accosted the Conservative MP Anna Soubry outside parliament and called her a traitor, the Observer can reveal.
Senior Met officers have studied the group’s own video, which shows them harassing the pro-Remain MP, and believe a public order offence may have been committed.
Commons Speaker John Bercow contacted Soubry asking how he could help after the incident on Wednesday, during which far-right supporters shouted the MP was “on the side of Adolf Hitler”.
Soubry said: “A senior officer in parliament then contacted me and he downloaded and watched the entire video and he took the view that a public order offence had been committed and they are now investigating.”
The group’s leader, James Goddard – whose use of the word “traitor” is the same term used by members of the far right to describe the murdered Labour MP Jo Cox – filmed himself calling Soubry a “disgrace to the country” because of her tenacious campaigning for a people’s vote.
In a Live Facebook broadcast on Friday afternoon, Goddard – who declined to talk to the Observer – defended the targeting of Soubry, saying that “we attacked her with a bit of verbal”.
Goddard, who styles himself as a Brexiter, has posted anti-Muslim messages on the social media site Gab, including messages stating: “Wherever Islam exists you will find murder and rape” while another calls for mass deportations of “illegals”. He also gave a speech at a rally in the summer supporting the far-right activist Tommy Robinson, whose real name is Stephen Yaxley-Lennon.
Soubry said that the group should not be considered pro-Brexit supporters but viewed as extremists.
The development comes as the Observer has learned that BNP founder Nick Griffin is among a cohort of prominent far-right figures keen to hijack the UK’s yellow-vest movement, which has recently appropriated the high-visibility jackets worn in the French gilet jaune protests.
Griffin has established links with a recently formed group called Liberty Defenders that purports to fight for civil rights. This group is attempting to establish itself as a prominent part of the UK’s yellow vests and in turn hoping to hijack the Brexit debate to gain support.
According to Hope Not Hate, which monitors far-right activity, prominent members of the group include former soldier Tim Scott, who once led the UK branch of Germany’s anti-Islam group Pegida, and former Ukip candidate Jack Sen, who was suspended from the party over racially charged comments.
After the Soubry incident Griffin, who was ejected from Hungary last year on the advice of the country’s counter-terrorism police, tweeted that: “the Yellow Vest Movement is here to stay &amp; will only grow.”
The former far-right leader also sent a link to an online Liberty Defenders piece requesting an interview with him and Sen to be retweeted to “help build the resistance!” Below the interview on the Liberty Defenders website, Goddard is described as one of Britain’s “most honourable activists” and is praised for his part in the yellow-vest protests in central London, which hoped to “demand our government give us the Brexit we voted for”.
Matthew Collins of Hope Not Hate said: “Hiding in the recesses of all this is Nick Griffin. He’s got more spare time on his hands than ever before and he’s desperately trying to resurrect himself with Brexit.” The group said messages sent by Goddard showed he was “a vile racist yob, pure and simple.”
Other yellow-vest protesters thought to be involved in the incident involving Soubry include David Coppin of Margate, an EDL supporter who has attended numerous far-right rallies across the UK including a “White Lives Matter” march.
Live Facebook broadcasts last week showed the small group shouting verbal abuse through a megaphone at pro-Remain protesters and journalists broadcasting from outside parliament, with Sky’s Kay Burley made a particular target.
On Thursday a group called “The Official UK Branch of the Yellow Vests” went up on Facebook, along with a “code of ethics”, which said: “We seek only to inform and encourage the reinstallation of British interest [sic] in parliament.”

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2019/feb/13/yellow-vest-activist-james-goddard-arrested-after-protest" date="Wed 13 Feb 2019" labels="UK news, " title="Yellow vest activist James Goddard charged with assault | UK news | The Guardian" >
The yellow vest activist James Goddard has been charged with assault and a public order offence after a protest in Manchester.
The 29-year-old was detained on Wednesday by Greater Manchester police (GMP) in relation to the demonstration in the city centre on Saturday. 
The public order charge relates to the alleged use of threatening or abusive words and behaviour with intent to cause fear or provoke unlawful violence, GMP said.
Goddard has been bailed to appear at Manchester and Salford magistrates court on Wednesday 20 March.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/07/i-understand-why-they-are-angry-readers-on-frances-gilets-jaunes" date="Fri 7 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="'I understand why they are angry': readers on France's gilets jaunes | World news | The Guardian" >
I don’t support gilets jaunes (yellow vests) but I understand why they are angry. In France, all the politicians say that we’re in an economic crisis, we must make an effort... Macron promised a new world in politics and a lot of people believed him. Now his new world looks very much like the old one: the taxes are always for the middle and working class. He even suppressed ISF [solidarity tax on wealth], one of the very rare taxes that are only for the wealthiest. I can’t agree with people defending polluting cars against ecological taxes, even if I think that industries should be taxed. Besides, most of these people are Marine Le Pen supporters and some are really crazy. I don’t like demonstrations to be that violent. Breaking everything is not a good way to show Macron that his politics aren’t good. Juliette, 21, Alsace
I drive past the gilets jaunes every day and quite often twice. I’ve lived in France for 20 years and things have never seen easy here. We’re all concerned. There’s a huge difference between those wanting to make ends meet and those who joined the disturbances in Paris to express violence and anger. The government obliged people to buy yellow safety jackets through the law and they are now being used to show discontent against Macron, which is ironic in its own way. The last time I filled up on petrol I had to double check that there wasn’t a hole in the tank as the total just kept on rising. I support them, they’re us. Who doesn’t want to be allowed to earn a reasonable wage? But let’s not confuse the pillaging with the real gilets jaunes here. Every speed trap vandalised comes out of our taxes later, and ransacking restaurants? As we say here, ‘ça rime à rien’ (“it doesn’t make sense”). Protest yes, but trashing restaurants and monuments? That’s not the real movement. Lois, Marseille
I support them. At least, those who are not racist, xenophobic and fascist. From the beginning of Macron’s term, liberalism, privatisation, and the “capitalist way” have been the only response to the real problems of people. Macron and his majority have been very arrogant and contemptuous with French citizens and the opposition, especially from the far left side (François Ruffin, among others). They now just have what they deserve. Rich and privileged people are now more afraid than ever, I guess. What is very sad is that everything is finally about money: political leaders are now panicking about Christmas, the trade, the image of France abroad, tourist bookings, etc. “Liberté, Égalité, Fraternité” is now only remembered in folklore. Money rules the world, even in the country of the human rights! How sad. I’m going next Saturday, with a friend. We want to walk peacefully. Sébastien, 47, Saint-Ouen
It may have started off as a protest against fuel taxes but has quickly become a protest on a system that people see as being rigged in favour of the rich. What is amazing to see is all ages and all social backgrounds mobilising. This protest is different from others in that people are waving French flags. It’s not organised under the umbrella of unions or political parties. It’s telling that the government emphasise the rioting and praise the police as they are frightened to see ordinary people protesting. Their strategy is to divide the population to keep a lid on the protest. Interestingly a cry often heard at rallies is “police avec nous” (“police with us”). The media of course are complicit in this with headline terms such as “French riots”. These are dangerous times, as if it continues and evolves there is a risk of a government being overwhelmed, new elections and the extreme [parties] being elected. A lot of Macron’s ministers and deputies are political novices and they along with him are struggling to react. What is sad in all of this is that a move away from a carbon economy is necessary, but it needs to be done in a coherent and fair way. Protests are happening all over the country from big cities to small towns. As France is such a centralised country, to make your voice heard you have to take it to Paris otherwise it’s generally ignored. Col, 46, Bordeaux
They [the gilets jaunes] are people like me, trying to get by on small salaries while the cost of living keeps rising. It’s not normal that working people cannot live well – this tax on fuel is the straw that’s breaking the camel’s back. Macron needs to wake up to this – he’s giving tax breaks to the rich while the ordinary Joe in the street like me can barely afford the basic necessities in life. Something has to give. I support the protesters but not the violence and pillaging: I believe much of this was carried out by extremists who are not representative of the movement at large. I don’t want to see the city I love get wrecked, and I’m afraid this is just the beginning – there could be serious trouble on the horizon. Christina, 48, teacher, Paris
I do not support the gilets jaunes for several reasons. First, that “carbon tax” was part of Macron’s 2017 platform. He won that election. He is delivering what he promised. Secondly, I think the timing is very poor and that many companies and financial institutions that would have moved to Paris due to Brexit will move elsewhere now. Probably Frankfurt? Thirdly, like most people who work in Paris, I don’t drive. So the tax doesn’t affect me nor my friends and colleagues. What they demand is not clear. They have no leaders, no specific demands. How do you negotiate then? How do you improve things? I hate Macron. I understand the anger, but not like this. There were candidates with welfare programs at the 2017 election. There were candidates who promised to revitalise the rural areas. People did note vote for them. And now they riot. Until now the main riots have happened on Saturdays, when I went to work on Mondays, everything was perfectly normal. Very few of the protesters appear to be Parisians, they seem to come from the provinces, especially rural areas, which are the most impacted by the new tax. But it’s not really about the new tax. I think the unrest is the result of the complete abandonment of our countryside for the last 30 years or so. The tax is just the last final straw. Our rural areas have turned into deserts. No infrastructure, no administration, no jobs, no respect, no power. William, 32, Paris
I live in a small village in southern France, we have no public transportation at all here and the closest large city is 40 minutes’ drive. I am also disabled and even if it was possible to just ride a bike (up the side of a mountain) or walk I couldn’t. On top of all of this I only make a small pension thanks to a work accident; I’m still under social security, drawing just 80% of my former salary, which wasn’t a lot to begin with. It’s already extremely difficult just to pay my bills and buy food. How on earth could I afford even more? Tell me, how is it fair to all of us who work hard, pay our taxes, own homes, and just try to get by? We aren’t rich like the many in Paris who support this [fuel tax] and say things like “it’s a necessary evil”. We tried to be nice but the government refused to listen – it took until things were burning before they backed off! I carry a yellow vest on my car dashboard. Everyone can see it and they know I support this cause. All over France you see this. Lennon, 40, southern France

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/16/gilet-jaunes-yellow-jackets-protesters-france-standstill" date="Fri 16 Nov 2018" labels="France, " title="'Gilets jaunes' protesters threaten to bring France to a standstill | World news | The Guardian" >
The French president, Emmanuel Macron, faces a new challenge this weekend as a motorist protest movement threatens to bring the country to a standstill.
The so-called gilets jaunes (yellow vests) protest movement has no official organisation, no identified leader and no political affiliation. Instead, it has been almost entirely coordinated on social media.
As a result, the French authorities fear the location of the protests is almost impossible to pin down and nobody has a clue how many people will turn up.
On Friday, the prime minister, Édouard Philippe, said the gilets jaunes were free to protest but blocking the country was “obviously not acceptable”.
A call to action across France in protest at the rising cost of diesel and petrol, has sparked vigorous support on Facebook, where the Blocage 17 Novembre 2018 page, has almost 25,000 followers. The group states: “We point out that we are not part of any organisation (or political party). This event comes about only from the French people.”
The “yellow vests” are named after the hi-vis tops motorists are obliged to carry in their vehicles under French law in case of a breakdown. France has a long history of citizens taking to the streets to force the hands of successive governments over the past 50 years.
Macron has defended the rise in taxes on fuel next year, which comes after a 23% rise in the cost of diesel and 15% in petrol in the past year. Ministers say price increases are mainly due to higher wholesale oil prices globally. But there is anger about taxes on fuel that have risen incrementally since 2014. Diesel is due to be taxed another 6.5 cents per litre and petrol by 2.9 cents in France from January.
The government says its transport policy is aimed at long-term “ecological transition” and encouraging more environment-friendly vehicles.
“I prefer taxing fuel to taxing labour,” Macron said last week. “People complaining about rising fuel prices are the same ones who complain about pollution and how their children suffer.”
Critics say the rising fuel prices hits workers who depend on cars to get to and from their jobs particularly in the countryside. The dispute has sparked a rift between the city “elite” and the rural poor in France, where Macron has been labelled the president of the rich because of his tax breaks for business.
Laurent Wauquiez, the leader of the opposition centre-right Les Républicains, tweeted: “You have to be completely out of touch with reality not to understand that taxing fuel is taxing those who work.”
The economy minister, Bruno Le Maire, has spent recent days promoting the government’s financial incentives for drivers to move away from diesel. These include a rebate for owners who trade in vehicles for a more environmentally friendly model.
There is also an “ecological bonus” for drivers who rent or buy new electric vehicles. Protesters struggling to meet the rising cost of fuel say this does not help them in the short term.
While go-slow actions will be tolerated during the demonstration, police have been ordered to break up any protests that bring roads to a standstill.
A poll by Elabe for BFM TV on Wednesday suggested 73% of French people supported the protests and 70% said the government should scrap the fuel price rises. 

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/01/paris-france-protests-yellow-vests-gilets-jaunes-champs-elysees" date="Sun 2 Dec 2018" labels="Paris, " title="French government considers state of emergency over gilets jaunes protests | World news | The Guardian" >
France will consider imposing a state of emergency to prevent a recurrence of some of the worst civil unrest in more than a decade, a government spokesman said on Sunday, as peaceful protestors were urged to come to the negotiating table.
The morning after groups of young men wearing masks rioted on the streets of central Paris, Benjamin Griveaux told Europe 1 radio: “We have to think about the measures that can be taken so that these incidents don’t happen again.” When asked about imposing a state of emergency, Griveaux said the president, prime minister and interior minister would discuss all options available to them at a meeting on Sunday.
The French president, Emmanuel Macron, has insisted he will “never accept violence” after central Paris saw its worst unrest in a decade on Saturday when thousands of masked protesters fought running battles with police, torched cars, set fires to banks and houses, and burned makeshift barricades on the edges of demonstrations against fuel tax.
Near the Arc de Triomphe, one of Paris’s best-known monuments, masked men burned barricades, set fire to buildings, smashed fences and torched luxury cars on some of the most expensive streets in the city as riot police fired teargas and water cannon.
Then, by early evening, rioters spread around Paris in a game of cat and mouse with police. Luxury department stores on Boulevard Haussmann were evacuated as cars were set alight and windows smashed. Near the Louvre, metal grilles were ripped down at the Tuileries Garden where fires were started. On the Place Vendôme, a hub of luxury jewellery shops and designer stores, rioters smashed windows and built barricades.
Anti-Macron graffiti was scrawled over the Arc de Triomphe near the tomb of the unknown soldier and protesters burst into the monument smashing up its lower floors before climbing on to the roof.
More than 250 people were arrested and at least 100 injured – including one protester who was in a serious condition on Saturday night – after the violence erupted on the margins of anti-fuel tax demonstrations held by the citizens’ protest movement known as the gilets jaunes (yellow vests). 
Macron, who was attending the G20 summit in Buenos Aires, said he would lead an emergency meeting of senior government ministers after returning to Paris on Sunday morning. He said: “No cause justifies that security forces are attacked, shops pillaged, public or private buildings set on fire, pedestrians or journalists threatened or that the Arc de Triomphe is sullied.”
He said that the peaceful demonstrators – whose name derives from their fluorescent high-visibility jackets and who have been demonstrating against taxes for two weeks – had legitimate concerns and he would hear their anger. But he said their demonstrations across the country on Saturday had been infiltrated by violent rioters who would be brought to trial in court.
In Paris, the protest began early in on Saturday morning as peaceful gilets jaunes arrived at the Champs Élysées to stage a march. The spontaneous citizens’ movement began in mid-November in opposition to rising fuel taxes but it has shifted into a much broader anti-government and anti-Macron protest movement about inequality and poor living standards. Slogans on Saturday slammed the centrist, pro-business president as a symbol of an elite cut off from the people.
The gilets jaunes have significant support from the general public and are proving the biggest headache yet for Macron, who was taken by surprise by the anti-tax revolt and is struggling to quell it.
Saturday’s violence and shocking scenes of burning buildings, torched cars and flames rising on the smartest streets of central Paris present an even bigger challenge to the government, which fears being seen as unable to keep a lid on the unpredictable protests and the violence on its edges.
Authorities on Saturday stressed the difference between peaceful protesters who marched along some Paris streets on Saturday morning, singing and waving flags, and the violent clashes that followed.
About 5,000 gilets jaunes marched down the Champs Élysées at midday, some carrying roses, many shouting: “Macron, resign!” and singing the national anthem. The Champs Élysées was closed to cars and tightly monitored by police, with identity and bag checks taking place as shop workers boarded windows and dismantled outdoor terraces.
But by early on Saturday afternoon the Arc de Triomphe was surrounded by masked protesters fighting running battles with police. The interior minister, Christophe Castaner, said thousands of troublemakers unconnected to the peaceful demonstrations had deliberately come to “pillage, smash, steal, wound and even kill”. He called them rioters who were “professionals at causing disorder”.
Authorities suggested extreme-right and extreme-left militants were involved in the rioting. The interior minister said that by 8pm police had cleared most rioters from central Paris.
Across France, more than 75,000 gilets jaunes demonstrated in cities or blocked roads and toll booths, some briefly stormed the runway of Nantes airport and others blocked supermarkets and major motorway junctions or staged barricades near government buildings. There were 580 roadblocks across the country. 
In the past two weeks, hundreds of thousands of protesters have taken similar action, complaining that Macron’s pro-business fuel tax policy was unfair and that people in low-income jobs could not make ends meet.
“The yellow vests will triumph,” was daubed across the facade of the 19th-century Arc de Triomphe monument in large black letters – and greeted with condemnation from politicians.
Many gilets jaunes protesters spoke out against the violent skirmishes on the edge of the demonstrations.
“What message do the yellow vests want to pass today? That we set France on fire, or find solutions? I find this [violence] absurd,” Jacline Mouraud, a prominent activist within the movement, told BFM television.
However, another protester said: “The government is not listening. Revolution cannot happen without violence.”
Jean-Luc Mélenchon, the head of the leftwing France Insoumise party, described the protests as “a process of citizens’ revolution”.
Macron said last week that he understood the anger people felt over the rise in fuel tax. He promised three months of national talks on how to transform France into a low-carbon economy without penalising people on low incomes who had to drive to work.
But government attempts to negotiate with the movement have not calmed the protests.
“We want our dignity back and we want to be able to live from our work, which is absolutely not the case today,” Jason Herbert, a spokesman for the movement, said after walking out of talks with the prime minister, Édouard Philippe, on Friday.
Hundreds of people have been injured and two people have been killed in car accidents since the protests began on 17 November. Polls continue to show that the demonstrations are supported by most French people. The protests have also spawned copycat demonstrations in Belgium.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/02/french-yellow-vests-march-in-paris-to-denounce-police-violence" date="Sat 2 Feb 2019" labels="France, " title="French 'yellow vests' march in Paris to denounce police violence | World news | The Guardian" >
Several thousand “gilets jaunes” protesters have marched through Paris and other French cities on Saturday on the 12th weekend of action against the government despite opinion polls pointing to a recovery in Emmanuel Macron’s popularity.
The protests – named after the fluorescent jackets French motorists are required to carry in their cars – began in November over plans to raise fuel taxes, before developing into a broader revolt against the government that mobilised tens of thousands of demonstrators nationwide each Saturday.
As in previous weeks, protesters carried French flags and held signs attacking the French president as being out of touch or calling for referendums tabled by citizens.
Protesters injured in previous weeks of violence were put at the front of the protests, some of whom wore eyepatches with a target sign on them.
The government warned on Friday that police would not hesitate to use flashballs in the event of violence by demonstrators after it was authorised by France’s highest administrative court. Flashball riot control guns are banned in much of Europe.
About 1,000 police officers have been injured along with 1,700 demonstrators since the start of the protests, according to official figures.
“It’s true that this intermediate weapon can hurt, but faced with rioters, the police need it to defend themselves against those who attack them,” said the interior minister, Christophe Castaner.
Opinion polls show a recovery in Macron’s battered popularity rating after he launched consultations, including town hall debates, to try to quell social unrest.
A Harris Interactive poll of 1,000 people on Friday showed Macron gaining four percentage points since December, taking him to a 35% approval rating. 

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/09/more-violence-in-paris-as-gilet-jaunes-protests-enter-13th-weekend" date="Sat 9 Feb 2019" labels="Paris, " title="More violence in Paris as gilet jaunes protests enter 13th weekend | World news | The Guardian" >
Thousands of French gilets jaunes (yellow vests) demonstrators marched on Saturdayin what was their 13th weekend of action. There were scuffles in Paris and a demonstrator’s hand was mangled by a small explosive.
There was also an overnight arson attack on the Brittany residence of the National Assembly head, Richard Ferrand, though no immediate link was made to the actions against President Emmanuel Macron.
The demonstrations, named for high-visibility jackets worn by the protesters, began in mid-November over fuel taxes. They have since broadened into a more general revolt against a political class they view as out of touch with common people.
In Paris, several thousand people marched on Saturday beside symbols of power such as the National Assembly and Senate.
The demonstrations were mainly peaceful, but some protesters threw objects at security forces, a scooter and a police van were set on fire and some shop windows were smashed.
One participant’s hand was severely injured when he tried to pick up a so-called “sting-ball grenade” used by police to disperse crowds with teargas, a police source told Reuters.
Another man had blood streaming down his face in front of a line of riot police.
The interior ministry put the total number of protesters around France at 12,000, including 4,000 in Paris. The police source, however, said numbers were higher, with 21,000 demonstrators taking part in rallies outside Paris.
“We’re not children, we’re adults,” said Hugues Salone, a computer engineer from Paris, who among the chanting and placard-waving protesters. “We really want to assert our choices, and not the choices of the politicians who do not live up to them.”
Leaders of the movement have denounced the police for injuring protesters, but have also struggled to contain violence from their own lines.
Politicians from across the spectrum condemned the arson attack on the home of Ferrand, a close ally of Macron and president of parliament’s lower house.
He published pictures on Twitter of a scorched living room, saying police found materials soaked in fuel. Ferrand said criminal intent was the likely cause, although the perpetrators’ identity was unclear.
“Nothing justifies intimidations and violence towards an elected official of the Republic,” Macron tweeted in relation to the incident.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2018/nov/24/french-police-fire-teargas-at-gilets-jaunes-protesters-in-paris-video" date="Sat 9 Feb 2019" labels="Paris, " title="French police fire teargas at 'gilets jaunes' protesters in Paris – video | World news | The Guardian" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/30/paris-police-fire-tear-gas-yellow-vest-gilet-jaunes-protesters" date="Sun 30 Dec 2018" labels="France, " title="Paris police fire tear gas as gilets jaunes protests turn violent | World news | The Guardian" >
Police fired tear gas at gilets jaunes (yellow vests) demonstrators in Paris on Saturday but the turnout for round seven of the popular protests that have rocked France appeared low.
Several hundred gathered at the BFM TV channel in the centre of the capital shouting “Fake news” and calling for the resignation of President Emmanuel Macron.
Protesters spilled on to tram lines and lobbed projectiles at police who replied with tear gas grenades and detained several people.
Several cars were also set alight outside the offices of the Le Parisien newspaper, although a fire service spokesman said it was not clear if the blaze was linked to the protests.
Tear gas was also fired in Nantes, western France, and protests were expected in Lyon, Bordeaux and Toulouse.
In the southern city of Marseille, police said around 1,000 protesters turned out amid cries of “Macron out”.
The official turnout numbers have plunged with the passing weeks, with police saying up to 12,000 had joined Saturday’s rally by midday. The government recorded 38,600 demonstrators on 22 December compared to 282,000 for the first major demonstrations on 17 November.
But leading figures within the movement that has flourished outside of trade union and political groups, say the low numbers are due to the holiday season and January will bring a resurgence of the street protests.
The focus of the protests has morphed from anger over fuel taxes to a broad rebuke of Macron, accused by critics of neglecting the rising costs of living for many in rural and small-town France.
“We want to get our purchasing power back and have a say in the decisions,” said Priscillia Ludosky, who launched the gilets jaunes petition against fuel price hikes.
Government tax concessions to boost disposable income among the low paid “are not enough”, Ludosky said in Marseille.
The movement has increasingly targeted Macron, and 40 gilets jaunes on Thursday tried to storm the medieval fort of Brégançon that serves as his official summer retreat on the Mediterranean before being turned back by police.
Die-hard gilets jaunes supporters believe the movement will live on in 2019 and plans are underway for New Year’s Eve protests.
Nearly 8,000 people are listed on Facebook as intending to attend, insisting it will be “festive and non-violent”.
Paris officials said preparations would continue for a fireworks display and sound and light show on the Champs-Élysées, the epicentre of repeated violent action against the government, with the Arc de Triomphe ransacked on 1 December.
Tens of thousands of tourists and locals traditionally ring in the new year on the wide shopping boulevard, which rises to meet the Arc monument.

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/09/who-really-are-the-gilets-jaunes" date="Sat 9 Feb 2019" labels="Observer special report, " title="Just who are the gilets jaunes? | World news | The Guardian" >
The gilets jaunes movement is the longest-running protest in France since the second world war. It has lasted for 13 weeks but has mobilised fully for only 13 days – all of them Saturdays.
In the protesters’ own eyes, this is not a protest. It is an insurrection which happens mostly at the weekends. Through a series of Saturday putsches, the yellow vests hope not merely to bring down President Emmanuel Macron but to rip up the constitution of the Fifth Republic and replace representative democracy with popular government. Their support, always limited compared with previous French rebellions, is waning. They will not give up easily or soon. They are mostly peaceful, but acts and words of great violence are committed and spoken.
There is no simple explanation for the gilets jaunes. It is not a monolithic, single-minded movement. It has no leadership structure, no single, accepted programme of demands. That’s what makes it fascinating. And worrying.
In May last year, a young businesswoman of French West Indian origin, Priscillia Ludosky, 31, placed a petition online complaining about the high cost of petrol and diesel in France. Reaction – practically nothing. Ludosky is a calm young woman with dreadlocks who runs her own cosmetics business from home. She is an unlikely pioneer for a populist movement which is sometimes accused of being racist and far right (as parts of it undoubtedly are).
In October she was contacted by Eric Drouet, a 33-year-old lorry driver, who teamed up with her to promote her original petition. Drouet is a car fanatic, a “petrol head”, but also someone with extremist political tendencies. He is now, many weeks later, probably the most influential figure in the gilets jaunes.
There is confusion in France about whether he should be seen as far right or far left. Drouet’s original motivation may well have been his car obsession rather than his politics. Pre-gilets jaunes, he was a loud-mouthed young man more likely to watch Top Gear than to read Das Kapital or Mein Kampf.
By the time he intervened, petrol prices were spiking because of a rise in world oil prices. Ludosky’s original petition exploded online, attracting hundreds of thousands of signatures.
It was Drouet, from Melun in the brie cheese country east of Paris, who thought of the idea of a nationwide protest against fuel taxes on 17 November. Someone else had the brilliant PR idea of dressing everyone up in the yellow hi-vis vests that French motorists must by law carry in their cars. Petrol prices rapidly set alight other grievances in rural and outer suburban France, some concrete, some more existential: a lack of public services, the high cost of living, a new tax on some pensions, the fact that Macron had partially abolished a tax on wealth. No one should underestimate the importance of a decision last July to reduce the two-lane speed limit in France from 90kph to 80kph.
This aroused a long-simmering belief in “peripheral France” that the countryside and outer suburbs are somehow subsidising the insolent success of the cities. Speeding fines, in this rural view, are just another way of taxing ploucs or pecnos – yokels or rednecks. There is also a belief that lower and middle France is taxed unfairly in favour of the rich.
Both beliefs are factually untrue. If anything, the rich subsidise the public services of the poor and lower-middle. The metropolitan areas subsidise peripheral France.
But it is true that energy, life and local sources of wealth have been sucked out of large swathes of France in recent decades – as they have in parts of Britain or the United States. All this adds up to an existential conviction that peripheral France is not only being left behind but mocked and cheated by those who are forging ahead. I believe that this resentment – a sense of being slighted or ignored or despised or abandoned or humiliated – explains the yellow-vest movement more than any particular grievance.
The first day of action on 17 November mobilised 283,000 people across France. This figure has never been reached since. It was impressive but fell well below the numbers that have turned out for other social protests in the last 20 years. Its significance was that it took place not just in cities but also in small towns and on almost every local roundabout. Like the Tour de France, it was a national event which came “down your way”.
People who had previously felt powerless felt abruptly powerful because they could hold up cars and lorries at a roundabout. People who had been invisible became highly visible in their hi-vis vests.
Here is our second paradox. The gilets jaunes are an internet-spawned and driven movement. They could not have existed before Facebook existed. But their attraction is that they are also something tangible, a social club as well as a social protest.
The gilets jaunes were brought to a white-heat pitch of anger by the halls of facing mirrors of “anger groups” online. But they also allowed people to escape from the isolation of their terminals or smartphones to come together and do things.
The 17 November protests – Act One – were mostly peaceful. There was little violence, except a few scuffles with police in Paris and with motorists on blocked roundabouts. The government stood back and allowed the protests to happen, even though the gilets jaunes deliberately defied the law which demands advance permissions for large gatherings.
It is important to remember this when gilets jaunes and Russian news sites allege that Macron has tried to “suppress” the movement.
On 24 November, Act Two of the movement, there was some violence in Paris. Police responded robustly to being attacked by a militant fringe of protesters on the Champs-Élysées. There were several serious injuries from police weapons. This was treated on GJ sites as deliberate police violence and repression, stoking tempers for the next weekend.
On 1 December, Act Three, I was out on streets of Paris from early morning. I happen to live near the Arc de Triomphe, and when I left my building at 9am I walked out into the middle of a street battle. A number of yellow vests – not just hard left and right militants but rural or provincial disaffected men and women in their 20s, 30s and 40s – attacked police from early morning.
The Arc de Triomphe was tagged with graffiti. Police were pelted with acid, paint, iron bolts, stones and bottles. Buildings around the Étoile were set briefly alight. A mob surged down the Avenue Kléber, overturning and burning cars and smashing bank, shop and restaurant windows.
Before the next Saturday – Act Four on 8 December – there were dark reports that there would be an insurrection, using live weapons and explosives. Macron, shaken, visited the Élysée nuclear bunker to make sure there was a place that he could take refuge. In the event, 8 December was again a violent day – not just in Paris but in several cities. It was not the feared revolution. The violence this time was mostly provoked by militia of the hard right and hard left. Some “ordinary” GJs waded in. Police were more aggressive in their response.
Since then there have been nine further Acts or Saturday putsches, some more violent than others, some better supported than others. Violence has switched from Paris for the most part to provincial cities, especially Toulouse, Bordeaux, Caen, Rouen and Rennes. The numbers taking part have fallen to around 60,000.
The roundabout rebellion is almost over. Support in rural areas is slackening. In early December my own unscientific poll of yellow vests placed on car dashboards in rural Normandy was 40%. It’s now 10% to 14%.
There has been no systematic attempt to repress protest. But the police’s so-called defensive weapons – rubber bullets and stun grenades – have become a serious problem that the government has been too slow to recognise. Seventeen eyes and four hands have been lost so far. That is unacceptable, whoever is initially responsible for the violence.
Is this just the French being the French? Not really. It’s true that protest goes to the street in France more rapidly than in almost any other democratic country. There is a default position in the country that social demands will not be taken seriously without street demos, and demos will not be taken seriously without a dose of violence.
But there is also something very un-French about the gilets jaunes movement. It has, first of all, broken all the unspoken and spoken rules of French manifestations. Protests are usually choreographed within certain limits, with agreed venues and routes and marshals. Riots happen but they are predictable riots.
The gilets jaunes refused from the beginning to be bound by any of these rules, although this is now changing. The movement, supposedly peaceful, allowed its own violent fringe as well as opportunist, urban, state-hating militia of hard right and hard left to take over.
The violence is not limited to the Saturdays-only protests in French cities. There have been scores of arson and other attacks on the offices of MPs who support Macron. There have been attacks on motorways toll-booths, newspapers and radio stations. A starred restaurant whose boss criticised the gilets jaunes was burned. Town halls, prefectures and other public buildings have been vandalised. The gilets jaunes are also un-French – or at least atypical – because they have not come from the usual or expected sources of protest: unions, farmers, students, the multi-racial banlieues. They come from a section of French society that is usually invisible, permanently grumpy but little engaged in politics.
I mean rural, non-farming France, small town France, outer suburban France. I mean many people who have not voted for years, as well as many who have voted hard right or hard left.
Gilets jaunes do include people at the bottom of society, the unemployed, the marginalised, but more typically they are people who are above the bottom but think that they should be doing better. They are people with low-paid jobs or pensioners or artisans or small business people or technicians or people at the lower level of the caring professions.
This mixture of supporters explains in part the heterogenous character and demands of the movement, which point both left and right, to higher welfare payments and pensions but also to lower taxes, to less state and more state. There is no coherent ideology, even a refusal of ideology.
Some see this as a camouflage for a movement whose heart beats on the far right. But many of the usual far-right hot topics – migration, Islam, abortion, gay marriage, Europe – are not the first things that you hear on the lips of gilets jaunes.
What are the sources of grievance and how justified are they? Here it is difficult to prise apart French and un-French elements.
The words you hear most often are mépris and ras le bol. Mépris means contempt. Gilets jaunes are convinced or have been convinced that the little or middling people like them are held in contempt by the trendy, rich, globally-oriented people of successful metropolitan France.
That’s why, I think, Macron has sparked such anger and hatred: not so much for what he has done in the past 20 months but for what he represents and some of the things he has said. He typifies the kind of person that GJs didn’t like even before they were GJs or before there was Macron.
He is the embodiment of the rich, clever, self-replicating people from the governing classes who’ve been to the finishing schools of the governing elite and think they know everything.
And so to the second word or phrase you hear: ras le bol, which means sick to the teeth. It conveys a sense of having been pushed to the breaking point. In my experience, French people almost always have a sense of ras le bol about something or other. But the white-hot anger of the GJ movement is something new and different. It can only be explained, I think, by the silos of facing mirrors of social media sites, which fill heads with exaggerated versions of real grievances blended with complete bullshit.
“France has been sold to the UN”; “Alsace has been given back to Germany”; “Politicians are living high on the hog – if we sweep them away, we can have lower taxes and higher welfare payments”; “Brigitte Macron, as first lady, earns €550,000 a year from the state”. Actually she earns, nothing, zero, rien.
This nonsense is always accompanied, as it often is in the United States and Britain, by a message telling you that the mainstream media is lying. Thus suspicion of the media, already high, is cranked to the point where journalists, newspapers and radio stations have become targets for GJ violence.
The gilets jaunes rapidly moved from a protest movement with specific demands to a revolutionary movement of unlikely revolutionaries. The view in much of the foreign media is that these are anti-Macron protests. And they are. But they go way beyond him and call for the sluicing out of the entire political class, left and right, even hard left and hard right, to be replaced by a bottom-up, direct democracy of permanent popular decisions by referendums.
Thus we have a revolution which did not just start on the internet and Facebook but wants to use the internet to impose a new form of government and yet is at the same time anti-globalist and nostalgic for a simpler, more traditional kind of France. Yet another paradox.
The movement is now splitting. Some gilets jaunes have decided to enter the mainstream political system to try to reform it or destroy it from the inside. Three rival GJ lists, broadly left, right and centrist, are being prepared for the European elections in May.
An extraordinary diplomatic row exploded last week when the Italian deputy prime minister, Luigi Di Maio, leader of the populist Five Star Movement, arrived unannounced in the south Paris suburbs for a photo opportunity with one of these electoral lists.
France withdrew its ambassador from Rome in protest. It emerged that Di Maio had been invited by Christophe Chalençon, a gilets jaunes figure with far-right connections, not by the leader of the list, Ingrid Levavasseur. She described both Di Maio and Chalençon as “sharks”.
All of this may help Macron. He is already recovering strongly in the opinion polls as well-heeled, urban France turns to him to save them from yellow chaos. He has made €10bn of concessions to motorists and the low-paid. He has started a “great national debate” in hundreds of village and town meetings.
Even one yellow vest list in the European elections will take votes from Marine Le Pen’s Rassemblement National and Jean-Luc Mélenchon’s far-left La France Insoumise. For Macron’s party to top the European poll in France would be a “mid-term” triumph.
There is talk of Emmanuel Macron calling a referendum on the same day as the EU poll on 26May to take further wind from the sails of the gilets jaunes. This is probably a silly idea. Senior ministers are campaigning against it.
If the referendum asks marginal questions – ie should there be fewer French MPs? – it will seem like a betrayal of the promise of Macron’s “great debate”. If it asks explosive questions – should Macron resign? Should he push ahead with his state-shrinking reform programme? – the results could be catastrophic for him.
LeVavasseur, an auxiliary nurse from Normandy, is one of the more thoughtful gilets jaunes (and therefore detested by many others). She is leading one of the GJ lists in the European elections. Asked to sum up yellow-vest demands in a single sentence, she said: “That we should feel recognised and valued.”
The anger of the gilets jaunes is understandable. What is scary is their fury. Where does that come from? What explains the radicalisation of home carers and garage mechanics in small towns who don’t understand the basics of how their own country’s political and tax system works but want to tear them both down?
That fury has many sources but its depth and strength can only be explained by the compound or viral effect of social media. The gilets jaunes are a French phenomenon and a French crisis.
They also point to a wider, existential crisis for 21st-century democracies.
This article is adapted from a talk given to a conference of the Brussels European Employee Relations Group

</doc>
</corpus>