<?xml version="1.0"?>
<corpus>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2019/feb/10/england-44-8-france-six-nations-player-ratings-from-twickenham" labels="Six Nations player ratings, England rugby union team" title="England 44-8 France: Six Nations player ratings from Twickenham" >
Elliot Daly 8 Getting better at full-back, with the pace to spot gaps and go through them. Kicked well to boot.

Chris Ashton 7 Did not take him long to come off his wing to look for work. Clever grubber for May’s third score and forced the penalty try. Will be disappointed not to get in on act himself though.

Henry Slade 9 Picked up from where he left off. His high kick that led to May’s third try showed he is playing with senses heightened and produced a classy finish.

Manu Tuilagi 7 Used sparingly by England again, often as a decoy runner. Almost created a try on the right and is a reassuring presence in England’s midfield.

Jonny May 8 Twelve tries in 12 matches and eight in his last six in the competition. Will have harder days but again the wing showed just how lethal he is.

Owen Farrell 9 Always looking to kick behind Penaud and excellent with the ball in hand – he is revelling in his captaincy role. Given an armchair ride but made the most of it.

Ben Youngs 8 Box-kicking was on the money and France could just not live with it. It was up to him to set a high tempo and he did so to devastating effect.

Mako Vunipola 8 An injury concern after making way with an ankle injury early in the second half. Was again supreme at loosehead until an ankle injury forced him off.

Jamie George 8 It has taken a little while but now looks at home as England’s starting hooker. One bruising hit on Parra and carried hard as ever.

Kyle Sinckler 7 Powerful and dynamic again, though he crosses the line occasionally. You get the feeling Dan Cole’s recall to the squad was designed to keep Sinckler on his toes.

Courtney Lawes 9 One trademark hit on Guirado in the first half, another on Bastareaud in the second and he carried with real menace. The outstanding lock on show.

George Kruis 7 Not as conspicuous as last week, nor as much as Lawes, but hard to find fault all the same. Deserves to keep his place against Wales.

Mark Wilson 8 Had one gallop in open play and dovetailed well with Curry. His enthusiasm for the hard grunt is clearly rubbing off on teammates. Yet to have a bad game for England.

Tom Curry 9 Teamed up with Lawes for a monstrous hit on Guirado. Bloodied but in no way bowed, he topped England’s tackle count in another superb showing. Easy to forget he is still only 20.

Billy Vunipola 8 Set the tone by walloping Huget into next week inside the first minute. Always gets England over the gain-line, which is such a valuable asset.

Replacements Luke Cowan-Dickie (for George 62) 6; Ben Moon (for M Vunipola 44) Never lets England down 7; Dan Cole (for Sinckler 55) 6; Joe Launchbury (for Kruis 45) Getting back up to speed 6; Nathan Hughes (for B Vunipola 65) 6; Dan Robson (for Youngs 70) At long last 6; George Ford (for Tuilagi 62) Kicked a bit too often 6; Jack Nowell (for Ashton 52) Busy as ever 7.

Yoann Huget 4 A remarkable performance. Bright in attack but showed utter disdain for defensive duties and hooked at half-time. One day England’s opponents will pick a full-back at No 15.

Damian Penaud 4 Took his try well but this was a trying afternoon. England targeted him from the word go and he was often found wanting. May made him look silly for his second try.

Mathieu Bastareaud 5 It was a mistake to turn to him and overlook form centres in the Top 14. It may seem harsh but it felt like a step back in time because he does not represent France’s future.

Geoffrey Doumayrou 6 Is obviously a capable player but could not make inroads into England’s resolute defence. Struggled with chaos going on around him.

Gaël Fickou 3 On of two centres on the wing (not to mention playing alongside a wing at full-back). Is it any wonder France struggled so badly in behind?

Camille Lopez 5 Came up with a clever kick for Fickou in the first half but exerted no control. Not all his fault when England are so rampant.

Morgan Parra 4 Found himself caught in the backfield for far too long, looked shaky under the high ball and must surely be replaced by Dupont now.

Jefferson Poirot 6 Kept on going and got stuck in at countless rucks but could not have the same kind of impact as either of England’s props.

Guilhem Guirado 6 A bad start for the skipper – his knock-on led to England’s first try and his lineout work was messy but made some strong carries thereafter.

Demba Bamba 5 Conceded a silly penalty early on but lined up Ashton and thundered into him. High tackle on Tuilagi was not malicious but clumsy.

Sébastien Vahaamahina 4 At least he does not have to carry the can as much as last week. That won’t be any consolation though. Could not effect proceedings at all.

Félix Lambey 6 Very good off the bench last week and among France’s better forwards this week. Is lightweight but does not let that hold him back.

Yacouba Camara 4 Largely anonymous. One of those players whose absence is often lamented but when he gets his chance he doesn’t really take it.

Arthur Iturria 6 In the thick of it when things boiled over and on the pitch showed his offloading ability once or twice. Swimming against the tide, though.

Louis Picamoles 5 Made his tackles but was given no opportunity to set off on trademark runs. Players of his calibre should catch the eye more than he did.

Replacements Pierre Bourgarit (for Guirado 76) n/a; Dany Priso (for Poirot 65) 5; Dorian Aldegheri (for Bamba 57) 6; Paul Willemse (for Vahaamahina 57) 5; Grégory Alldritt (for Lambey 70) n/a; Antoine Dupont (for Parra 47) Lively and simply has to start from here on in 7; Romain Ntamack (for Lopez 57) Energetic cameo 6; Thomas Ramos (for Huget ht) Should have started 7.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/football/blog/2019/mar/26/france-matuidi-giroud-still-crucial-football" labels="Get French Football News, France" title="France are only getting better, with Matuidi and Giroud still crucial" >
A
s if the internet-breaking Paul Pogba-Antoine Griezmann combination was not enough proof that France remain – the autumn wobbles aside – the prohibitive best side in the world, the win against Iceland on Monday will have offered naysayers little respite. “The party continues,” read L’Équipe’s headline, and on the evidence of this result, and the defeat of Moldova on Friday, that is not an unfair assessment.

But are France really on the same level as the side which won the World Cup? Clearly the calibre of their opposition in these two matches is a mitigating factor, but there is now a growing sentiment that Didier Deschamps’s decision to stick (largely) with the side that won in Russia is not down to nostalgia but results.

Deschamps, as he proved last summer, is as pragmatic as a manager as he was during his playing career, emphasising control, defensive solidity and maximum effort, particularly in the midfield. In playing France’s current 4-4-2/4-3-3 hybrid, he has continued with Blaise Matuidi on the left and the Juventus man, despite missing a few chances in these two matches, proved himself an impressively ageless catalyst.

Deschamps admitted that Matuidi’s place in the starting lineup was down to injury concerns, with both Kingsley Coman and Ousmane Dembélé unavailable. But with Matuidi far more capable than either of those players of putting in a shift, France were able to maintain the same tactical flexibility and solidity that was so key to their success last summer. Matuidi is 32 this year, and while one can see him continuing through the European Championship next summer, Deschamps will need to evaluate his options in this position sooner rather than later. Houssem Aouar, Tanguy N’Dombélé, Corentin Tolisso, Thomas Lemar, and the aforementioned Coman and Dembélé are all attractive enough options, but none have the experience and sheer selflessness of Matuidi, something which has proved key to the team striking a balance between their attacking brilliance and more workmanlike elements.

On the subject of creating a balance, Pogba and N’Golo Kanté’s relationship continues to improve as well. In the summer, Deschamps was accused of misusing Pogba in a midfield two, a criticism that had its genesis in France’s run to the final of the 2016 European Championship. The crux of this (admittedly poorly reasoned) argument centres around Pogba’s role in that system being so deep as to fail to be able to significantly influence play going forward. However, with both Matuidi and the Chelsea player in the fold, Pogba is able to focus his attention on playing the creator, as his sublime pass for Griezmann on Friday aptly demonstrated. In this, then, one can plainly see why Deschamps’s reticence to move on from this summer is justified.

Pogba was not the only player embracing the creator’s role for Les Bleus, however, as Kylian Mbappé delivered a man-of-the-match performance against Iceland, scoring but also adding a pair of superb assists. It was perhaps his best display in terms of his passing acumen in a France shirt, but it was also a performance wrought from his customary continued willingness to run at the opposition, earning corners and pulling players out of position at will, no mean feat given Iceland’s massed defence.

Again, the plodding pace of the opposition’s defence surely will have done much to make Mbappé look that much more jet-heeled, but the fact that he continually placed an emphasis not on looking for his own shot but to foster opportunities for others shows an increased maturity, something that has been perhaps slightly lacking in his play to date for both club and country. More consistency in this department is surely needed but for now, if Mbappé can continue to take a more holistic approach to his play, there may be little that the world can do.

Mbappé was not the only attacking player to distinguish himself in these two matches, however, as Olivier Giroud was on the scoresheet in both games. The Chelsea striker has struggled for minutes under Maurizio Sarri but he clearly has done more than enough for Deschamps to keep faith with him, a trust that was duly rewarded with goals that placed him as France’s third all-time leading scorer. Again, yes, these sides may not have been the sternest test but Giroud’s physicality and work ethic (like that of fellow veteran Matuidi) is all but impossible to ignore, and it makes Deschamps’s decision to opt for his veteran players all the more justified.

There does remain one albatross, however, over Deschamps’s side and how he is choosing (or not) to foster a continuum of development. Hugo Lloris has had more than his share of mistakes this season for Tottenham, and while one would be right to point not only to Spurs’ place in the Champions League quarter-finals and their position in the Premier League table, he is also 33 this year and his deputy, Steve Mandanda, will be 35 by the time the European Championship finals kick off in 2020. Alphonse Areola has definitively moved ahead of Stéphane Ruffier and Benoît Costil in the pecking order for third choice, but does the position require a more holistic rethink?

Benjamin Lecomte was included in the November callups and has done little with Montpellier to suggest he is undeserving of further consideration. Lecomte is 28 next month and may not be as forward-thinking a resolution to this dilemma as one would like, but with Mandanda clearly not up to scratch this season it would behoove Deschamps to create more competition for the places behind Lloris. Lille’s Mike Maignan has had the occasional mistake but his consistent improvement has been instrumental to Les Dogues’ improvement this season and is surely, given his age and form, more worthy than his Marseille counterpart of a place in the 23.

• In addition to the national side’s two wins, another story from France this week was Jean-Michel Aulas’s 70th birthday. The proudly outspoken Lyon chairman has been accused in recent years of focusing too strongly on the bottom line at the expense of potential success, particularly when it comes to his managerial appointments. Even now, though, Lyon continue to rise in Ligue 1, their defeat against Barcelona notwithstanding, and the players this summer who had seemed cut-rate alternatives to more attractive transfer targets (Moussa Dembélé, Martin Terrier, Jason Denayer) are manifesting a level of ability and consistency that could be key as Lyon chase a return to the Champions League. No stranger to criticism given his age and time in charge of the club, Aulas’s milestone birthday is one worth celebrating, the chairman being a true individual and a principled one at that; love him or loath him, he is the type of figure of which the game needs more, and not less.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2019/feb/27/france-fumes-as-dutch-government-takes-stake-in-air-france-klm" labels="Air France/KLM" title="France fumes as Dutch government takes stake in Air France-KLM" >
A minor diplomatic row appears to be building after the Dutch government snapped up a near-13% stake in Air France-KLM, prompting the French government to accuse The Hague of acting like an “unfriendly” corporate raider.

The Dutch finance minister said the Netherlands had spent €680m (£581m) on a 12.7% stake in the company, which was formed in 2004 when the two flag-carrier airlines merged.

The Netherlands said it was prepared to increase its stake to 14% to ensure it can bring Dutch influence to bear on the company, putting it on an even keel with France, which already holds about 14%.

“Buying this stake ensures we have a seat at the table,” said the Dutch finance minister, Wopke Hoekstra, indicating a desire to have more influence over Dutch economic interests and jobs, and the status of Schipol airport, in Amsterdam. Schipol is continental Europe’s second busiest airport, after Charles de Gaulle in Paris.

French president Emmanuel Macron urged the Dutch government to “clarify its intentions” while his finance minister Bruno Le Maire described the Dutch move as “incomprehensible.” Le Maire said the business should be “managed without national public interference”.

French officials said they were upset that they had not been informed in advance of the Dutch stake-building plans.

Local media reports said the the government in Paris was only informed of the share purchase an hour before it was officially confirmed. “The way that the stake was built up was more like that done by a corporate raider, rather than a state shareholder,” a French finance ministry official told Reuters.

The official added that the purchase was an “unfriendly, surprising move that is extremely detrimental to Air France-KLM financially”.

The source declined to say whether the French state would raise its stake in reaction to the Dutch move but said Paris was going to ask France’s financial markets watchdog to examine heavy trading in the airline’s shares prior to the Dutch government’s announcement. Le Maire will meet Hoekstra later this week to discuss the airline.

Shares in Air France-KLM were down by 15% at one point, in the wake of the disclosure of the investment by the Netherlands, prompting the French official to point out that Dutch taxpayers had already seen the value of their investment plummet. They closed down 12%, at €11.24, valuing the airline at €4.82bn, as analysts voiced concerns that the two government’s competing interests could have an impact on the carrier’s strategy and growth.

The row comes amid reports that the Dutch government had waded into discussions about the future of KLM’s chief executive, Pieter Elbers, amid doubts over whether he would keep his job.

Elbers was said to be sceptical about plans by the company’s overall boss, Canadian Ben Smith, to further cement ties between the two airlines, which operate as separate carriers under one holding company.

KLM is the more profitable of the two airlines.

The French budget minister Gérald Darmanin called on states to interfere in the alliance as little as possible.

“We must have good relations with our friends from the Netherlands,” Darmanin told Europe 1 radio.

“It is especially necessary that the states are involved as little as possible in the running of a large company like this. We must let the people of Air France-KLM work.”
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2018/jul/06/uruguay-france-world-cup-quarter-final-match-report" labels="World Cup 2018" title="Uruguay 0 - 2 France" >
Didier Deschamps had no desire to answer a question about whether France could end up as champions. A man who knows what it takes to win a World Cup stubbornly refused to look too far into the distance.

Yet the manager will be able to avoid that subject for only so long after France eased past Uruguay, courtesy of Raphaël Varane’s splendid header and an awful blunder by Fernando Muslera, to reach the World Cup semi-finals for the first time since 2006.

Growing in confidence all the time and blessed with outstanding individuals, there is something ominous about the way France have dispatched Argentina and now Uruguay, scoring six goals in the process and, perhaps most significantly, leaving the impression there is so much more to come. They did, however, get a helping hand and, unfortunately for Uruguay, it was an error that signalled the end of their World Cup.

Uruguay’s goalkeeper made one of those mistakes that tend to live with players for a long time, and only Muslera knows how Antoine Griezmann’s speculative shot ended up almost going through him. The shot dipped and swerved a little but Muslera was right behind it and got two hands to a ball that somehow dropped over the line.

For Uruguay, trailing to Varane’s goal at that point and badly missing the injured Edinson Cavani in attack, there was never going to be a way back. Óscar Tabárez, their 71-year-old manager, was magnanimous enough to admit as much when he talked about “a very big distance between the teams”.

Uruguay will reflect on a potential turning point just before half-time, when Hugo Lloris produced an outstanding save to keep out a powerful downward header from Martín Cáceres and Diego Godín thumped the follow-up wide. Those two chances were rare sights of goal for a team outplayed for much of the game.

Whether the outcome would have been different with Cavani on the pitch is impossible to say but there is no getting away from the fact Uruguay needed him. Luis Suárez chased lost causes and ran himself into the ground but the 31-year-old looked lost without Cavani by his side and offered little threat. Cristhian Stuani, the former Middlesbrough striker, started in Cavani’s place and was a substitution waiting to happen.

France had too much class for Uruguay all over the pitch and the only blemish on a comfortable victory was Kylian Mbappé’s play-acting. He is a wonderful talent and there was a surge of excitement whenever he was on the ball, yet the teenager ought to be embarrassed when he looks back on an incident involving Cristian Rodríguez midway through the second half.

Rodríguez barely touched the 19-year-old as he brushed past him, prompting the Uruguay players to react furiously when the France forward fell to the ground and rolled around in agony after Godín tried to help him to his feet. A melee followed and ended with Mbappé and Rodríguez being booked. Paul Pogba was doing plenty of pushing and shoving, along with several others, and Deschamps admitted he was concerned about the prospect of the Manchester United midfielder picking up the booking that would have ruled him out of the semi-final.

Although Uruguay had threatened to be awkward opponents in more ways than one – they had conceded once in their previous seven matches and play with so much grit and determination – it was a straightforward goal that allowed France to take the lead. Rodrigo Bentancur recklessly brought down Corentin Tolisso after being caught in possession and the punishment extended beyond the yellow card the Uruguay midfielder received.

From wide on the France right, Griezmann approached the ball, retreated and then stepped forward again before delivering an inswinging free-kick that seemed to catch Uruguay by surprise, perhaps because of the stutter in Griezmann’s run-up. Varane, timing his run perfectly, got across Stuani to send a glancing header into the far corner of the net.

It was a terrific goal, perfectly placed, and particularly satisfying for Varane given what happened four years ago in Brazil, when France were eliminated 1-0 at the quarter-final stage and the Real Madrid defender allowed Mats Hummels to beat him to a header that proved to be the defining moment.

Despite dominating possession, France had created little of note before Varane’s goal, although Mbappé should have put them ahead. Olivier Giroud, still looking for his first goal at this World Cup, set up Mbappé for a simple chance. Unmarked and only eight yards out, he seemed to mistime his jump and his header sailed over.

Although Lloris’s excellent save, diving low to his right to claw away that Caceres header from Lucas Torreira’s free-kick, gave France a warning, they were out of sight from the moment Griezmann scored his third goal of the World Cup. In space 25 yards out after receiving a square pass from Tolisso, Griezmann decided to chance his arm. Muslera, getting himself in a terrible tangle, was unable to keep it out and France were on their way to the last four.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/dec/20/france-bans-fracking-and-oil-extraction-in-all-of-its-territories" labels="Fossil fuels" title="France bans fracking and oil extraction in all of its territories" >
France’s parliament has passed into law a ban on producing oil and gas by 2040, a largely symbolic gesture as the country is 99% dependent on hydrocarbon imports.

In Tuesday’s vote by show of hands, only the rightwing Republicans party opposed, while leftwing lawmakers abstained.

No new permits will be granted to extract fossil fuels and no existing licences will be renewed beyond 2040, when all production in mainland France and its overseas territories will stop.

Socialist lawmaker Delphine Batho said she hoped the ban would be “contagious”, inspiring bigger producers to follow suit.

France extracts the equivalent of about 815,000 tonnes of oil per year – an amount produced in a few hours by Saudi Arabia.

But centrist president Emmanuel Macron has said he wants France to take the lead as a major world economy switching away from fossil fuels – and the nuclear industry – into renewable sources.

His government plans to stop the sale of diesel and petrol engine cars by 2040 as well.

Above all the ban will affect companies prospecting for oil in the French territory of Guyana in South America, while also banning the extraction of shale gas by any means – its extraction by fracking was banned in 2011.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/fashion/2019/feb/26/project-loud-france-rihanna-new-fashion-label-name-and-funding" labels="Fashion" title="Project Loud France: Rihanna's new fashion label gets a name – and funding" >
In January, it was announced that Rihanna would become the first black female designer to have a label as part of the LVMH conglomerate. This week, it was revealed that the project has a name and multi-million euro funding.

The title of the venture is Project Loud France – named in honour of the singer’s fifth album, Loud – and it has around €60m (£50m) worth of investment split between Rihanna and the conglomerate, which also owns Louis Vuitton, Celine and Christian Dior. Rihanna will be a 49.99% shareholder.

This information was obtained by The Business of Fashion, who have had access to documents detailing the company’s set-up. This is the first new brand the group has launched since Christian Lacroix in 1987. According to an article on their website, Rihanna has invested €2,998,800 (£2,571,000) while LVMH have brought €30m (£25m). This suggests there are high hopes that a Rihanna fashion brand is a project worth investing in. It has also been reported that Project Loud France is registered at the same address as LVMH Fashion Group, which looks after brands including Celine, Givenchy and Marc Jacobs.

This faith isn’t, of course, just based on the reach of a celebrity. Rihanna’s ability to connect with millennials and Gen Z consumers has been tried and tested in both beauty and fashion. Her Fenty Beauty line – which pioneered diversity by having first 40 and then 50 shades of foundation to cater to different skin tones – had consumers queuing outside stores to buy products. The brand reportedly generated $100m (£75m) in the first 40 days after launch. It was first launched by Kendo, the LVMH initiative to develop beauty brands.

Her Fenty fashion label, launched with Puma in 2015, has also been successful. The first trainers she designed sold out in 35 minutes, and she was credited, in part, with Puma’s profits increasingly 92.2% in 2017. Savage x Fenty, her lingerie line launched in May 2018, has also been well received, with queues outside stores for products. The New York fashion week show in September was praised for diverse, body-positive casting and held up as an example of what a modern lingerie line looks like – compared to Victoria’s Secret.

While her entrepreneurism is impressive, Rihanna’s star power is also part of the package here. She has 67.9m followers on Instagram, where she regularly shares images of herself in outfits including a ruffle cocktail dress or a snakeskin dress and matching bucket hat. The direct connection with her fans saw her crowned “Most marketable celebrity” in 2016. The NPD Group, who conducted the research, judged that Rihanna’s followers would be 3.7 times more likely to buy something seen on her account than that of other celebrities.

LVMH are working on a new brand with French designer Nicolas Ghesquière, too. This is likely to pique fashion insiders’ interests. Ghesquière is also creative director of Louis Vuitton. Like Project Loud France, the date of this launch is unknown.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2019/mar/16/italy-france-six-nations-match-report" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="France survive Italy scare thanks to Damian Penaud’s one-man show" >
Italy’s losing sequence in the Six Nations extended to a record 22 matches but France were pushed all the way and needed a late, try-saving tackle from Damian Penaud.

The form of the Azzurri in the last few years – they have not won in the Championship since 2015 – has led to calls for a relegation system to be implemented in the competition. Yet it needed Penaud, who knocked the ball out of the hands of the debutant Marco Zanon as he went for the line five minutes from time, to secure victory for France.

At the time, France led 20-14 and a converted try would have inched Italy ahead but, with a minute remaining, Penaud crossed for his side’s third score.

The Italy coach, Conor O’Shea, yet to collect a Six Nations victory since taking the job in 2016, was left exasperated. “Normally in a Test it’s easy to remember two or three fundamental moments, but at the end of this match I think there were probably 11 or 12 opportunities that we’ve had,” he said. “It’s very hard at the moment. We believe in everything we’re doing, we believe that this group has a different mentality.

“Today, without looking at the ultimate result, if you look at the match, it’s incredible that we’ve lost. Our execution and precision was the difference today.”

Jacques Brunel, who coached Italy for five years from 2011 to 2016, empathised with his former players. “They have the ability, but it just wasn’t there today,” the France coach said. “From the start of the tournament they’ve shown a lot of presence.”

France, who had not won away from home in the last two years, went 6-0 down after two Tommaso Allan penalties but they went in ahead at the break thanks to Antoine Dupont’s try, converted by Romain Ntamack, who added a penalty.

Yoann Huget’s 47th-minute try gave France some breathing room but Italy responded through Tito Tebaldi before the hour – although some wayward kicking from Allan proved costly.

Italy attacked in the closing stages and Zanon crossed in the left corner, only for the TMO to rule the ball had been taken out of his hands by Penaud before touching down. Penaud then sprinted up the other end to score a try of his own.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/mar/28/france-black-people-art-musee-d-orsay" labels="Opinion, Museums" title="France is addressing black people’s invisibility in art. When will the UK?" >
A
n exhibition taking place at the Musée d’Orsay in Paris is breaking new ground on race and representation in the arts. Black Models: From Géricault to Matisse displays masterpieces by some of France’s most important artists but renamed in honour of the black subjects who are in the pictures, yet absent from their narratives.

The exhibition is a welcome reminder that black people have been indispensable to nations such as France for centuries, even if we have been overlooked. One of the most toxic myths so central in shaping society is that Europe was once white and pure, until the invasion of the dangerous and dark foreigners who have polluted the ideal society. By renaming the pictures, the curators are rightly staking a claim to a society that predates mass migration from the colonies to the “mother country”.

Fine art is perhaps the perfect space to undo this fantasy narrative of empire. Along with science, industry and politics, the production of “high” culture is one of the central claims to European supremacy. Art galleries and museums are the embodiment of whiteness – at times, it seems, conceived solely to prove that “high” culture is the possession of those of European descent. By focusing on the black people who feature in classical pieces, the exhibition reminds visitors that no aspect of western development occurred without the presence of people of colour. Naming the black subjects is also extremely powerful. Black models are dotted around the paintings, and when they are labelled it is with terms such as “mulatresse”, derived from the word “mule”. In the exhibition, Benoist’s Portrait of a Negress is renamed after the model, “Madeleine”, humanising the subject of the drawing. We were not just present, but important enough to be named.

Britain has an identical problem with its art history. By the end of the 18th century there were at least 15,000 enslaved Africans living in Britain, not to mention a black presence on the island dating back to Roman times. Black people appear in literature and art dating back to at least the 16th century, most famously the “blackamoors” who influenced Shakespeare’s work. Black subjects also appear in artworks such as Irish painter Daniel Maclise’s infamous The Death of Nelson (1807), which includes a black sailor and cook in the background. In 1813 the British Institution exhibited a portrait by Joshua Reynolds, now known as A Young Black, under the title The Black Servant of Sir Joshua. The portrait of the Scottish Glassford family painted by Archibald McLauchlan around 1767 is a testament to how black people have been erased. Originally the image included a black child, likely enslaved, but this was later painted over. Glasgow Museum conservators painting the child back into the picture is more than just symbolic.

Britain and France are by no means alone in reifying whiteness in fine art. I will never forget taking my daughter to the Philadelphia Museum of Art, and being almost knocked back by the overwhelming whiteness of the displays. It felt like visiting an art museum in Europe, rather than a city where the largest demographic is African American. We were actually going to see a painting by black artist Jacob Lawrence, Taboo, and after searching in vain were told that it was in a cupboard, rather than on display. I should not have been surprised; there is a reason I stopped visiting art museums long ago. I left being most disappointed in myself for expecting better.

So the French exhibition is a welcome change and something that the British art world should take note of. But in bringing black people to the fore of such art we must be careful to frame the images correctly. Black people were present in this history and paintings, not as equals but as subjects. Renaming them and removing racist epithets does not change the subservient role many of the paintings portray. It is tempting to get carried away celebrating our presence, while forgetting why we were there and continue to be here. In the most part, we remain subjects oppressed to the margins of the canvas. Fully acknowledging the black presence in history is important, but we need to completely redraw new landscapes to imagine a future where the racism embedded in the arts no longer exists.

• Kehinde Andrews is professor of black studies at Birmingham City University
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2019/feb/23/france-scotland-six-nations-match-report" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="France turn screw with late fourth try as Scotland’s losing Paris run continues" >
France have remembered at last. Beautiful rugby is all very well but without the route to victory they have found it empty of late. On a sunny afternoon in Paris they played beautifully and with the bloody-mindedness to make sure that, this time, there would be no forgetting to win.

Scotland arrived with a team stripped by injury. It showed. The scoreline flatters them. They found plenty of scope for expression themselves but each gap taken felt like an isolated flash rather than the sustained coherence of France’s play. After a shaky start Blair Kinghorn looked threatening in attack, as did Peter Horne, the replacements for Scotland’s most high-profile absences, but there was a lack of authority, not least up front, where France dominated the set piece.

“We missed the first 15 minutes,” said Gregor Townsend, “and we knew that was going to be a really important time. After their two defeats the first 20 minutes could either give France confidence or we could put them under more pressure. They played with confidence.”

Indeed, the French were all over Scotland. The TMO denied them a try four times but the home side were not only determined to win; they wanted a bonus point and played until the eighth minute of overtime to secure that fourth try. They could have had it much, much earlier.

It is still difficult, though, to know what to make of them. Proclaimed in some quarters as the worst French side ever seen after their annihilation at Twickenham in round two, they burst into this contest rather as they had against Wales in round one before that record-breaking implosion. They crossed Scotland’s tryline three times in the first half, playing rugby of the gods, but only one of them was to stand for a relatively modest 10-3 lead at the break.

The one they scored was spectacular, originating from their own 22, whence Thomas Ramos, one of the new generation France are feeding into their team, ran with devilry. It was a big day for the 23-year-old Toulouse full-back, invested with the kicking duties after France’s more mature half-back pairing of Morgan Parra and Camille Lopez, both goal-kickers, had been cleared out after their lacklustre start to the championship. Ramos did not disappoint for the most part.

Certainly in attack he patrolled the backline with menace and, when Horne kicked deeply and not without effectiveness into France territory, Ramos gathered and left Sean Maitland for dead. He was away and found Damian Penaud, another richly promising youngster, who found a third, Antoine Dupont, now up at the Scotland 22. A fabulous Nick Grigg tackle cut him down short but Ramos fed a fourth reason for French hope, this the youngest of the lot, 19-year-old Romain Ntamack, son of Emile, and he finished off what will prove one of the tries of the championship.

This was the first half of their match against Wales, and then some. Those two disallowed tries would have been beauties as well, featuring charging, off-loading tight forwards in concert with those brilliant backs and a back row always on hand. Exactly how rugby is meant to be played, in fact. Alas, each was undone by the subtlest of fumbles, spotted by the TMO.

Scotland, too, have an unfamiliar look to them but this was not by choice. They seemed suitably bewildered at times but in flashes showed there were gaps to exploit. The French, though, were conceding penalties as wilfully as ever, culminating in a yellow card for the wing Yoann Huget in the 27th minute.

A flashing Horne break set up Greig Laidlaw for one shot at goal, which he uncharacteristically missed, but a successful one just before Huget’s yellow card was all Scotland could take from the half. They could not score while Huget was away. Indeed, France’s second disallowed try came with France down to 14.

If anyone was expecting another second-half collapse, France responded with another classic. From the resumption they broke out – and nearly everyone had a go. Guilhem Guirado to the magnificent 20-year-old Demba Bamba, hooker to prop – then to wing to scrum-half to Scottish territory. At which point even Mathieu Bastareaud joined the celebration of deftness. He chipped and gathered, setting off another combination of backs and forwards, culminating in a try for Huget, a 12-point lead – and plenty of time in which to lose it.

There would be no surrender. At times in the second half, France had Scotland reeling, even if, as both teams emptied their benches, the Scots found holes aplenty in the final quarter. It was not until the 75th minute that France put the result numerically beyond doubt. Their scrum had been dominant throughout but, even with the mighty Bamba off, they drove Scotland over for Grégory Alldritt to score the first of his late brace.

Ali Price finished Scotland’s only try after Horne’s break with two minutes to go but there was time still for France to score their fourth, Alldritt repeating his trick off an advancing scrum eight minutes after time. It was a brutal way to complete a sublime display.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/02/belgian-couple-charged-with-planning-terrorist-attack-in-france" labels="MEK (People's Mujahedin of Iran)" title="Diplomat arrested over alleged attack plot on Iranian group in France" >
An Iranian diplomat is among four people who have been arrested in connection with what authorities said was a foiled bombing attack targeting a rally organised by an Iranian opposition group in France at the weekend.

Mujahedin-e-Khalq (MEK), a fringe organisation loathed by Iran’s establishment, accused leaders in Tehran of planning the suspected attack near Paris on Saturday, where an event featuring high-profile US politicians, including Rudy Giuliani, Donald Trump’s attorney, was taking place.

On Monday, Belgian authorities said an unnamed Iranian diplomat, who works for Tehran’s mission to Austria, was arrested in Germany, while a married couple – Belgian citizens of Iranian heritage – were detained with “attempt at terrorist murder and preparing a terrorist crime” against the MEK. A fourth suspect was arrested in France.

The arrests come ahead of a rare visit to Europe by the Iranian president, Hassan Rouhani, who is scrambling to salvage the 2015 nuclear deal after Trump said the US would not honour it.

Rouhani arrived in Zurich on Monday and is expected to travel to Austria on Wednesday in an attempt to save the agreement.

A statement by the secretariat of the National Council of Resistance of Iran (NCRI), an umbrella group of the MEK, said: “The conspiracy of the terrorist dictatorship ruling Iran to attack the grand gathering of the Iranian resistance in Villepinte, Paris, was foiled.

“The mullahs’ regime’s terrorists in Belgium, helped by the regime’s diplomat terrorists, had designed for the attack.”

Iran’s foreign minister, Mohammad Javad Zarif, rejected claims of Iran’s involvement and described the accusations as a “sinister false flag ploy”. A visit by Rouhani to Austria in 2016 was cancelled after Iran objected to an MEK rally planned to coincide with his visit.

“How convenient: just as we embark on a presidential visit to Europe, an alleged Iranian operation and its ‘plotters’ arrested. Iran unequivocally condemns all violence and terror anywhere, and is ready to work with all concerned to uncover what is a sinister false flag ploy,” Zarif tweeted.

In May, Iran vehemently denied accusations by Mike Pompeo, the US secretary of state, that its elite Revolutionary Guards carried out “assassination operations in the heart of Europe”.

The Iranian couple were in a Mercedes car when they were stopped by special forces and arrested on Saturday in Woluwe-Saint-Pierre, which is close to EU institutions in Brussels. According to Belgian media, police found 500 grams of TATP explosive and a detonator hidden in a toiletries bag.

Belgium’s federal prosecutor, which never publishes the surnames of suspects, announced in a statement that Amir S, 38, and his wife, Nasimeh N, 33, had been charged with attempted terrorist murder and preparing an act of terrorism.

Belgium’s interior minister, Jan Jambon, said there had been no threat to the country and praised the police, security and judicial services for their “rapid and effective intervention”. The threat level in Belgium, which was reduced earlier this year, remains unchanged, he added.

Tehran considers the MEK as a terrorist organisation – a view shared by the US and the EU until not long ago. The US delisted it in 2012, but the MEK’s animosity with Iran’s rulers has earned it powerful allies in the west, most particularly among Trump associates such as John Bolton, who is the group’s most powerful advocate.

The MEK, a cult-like fringe exiled Iranian opposition group, was once a sworn enemy of the United States. It was responsible for the killing of six Americans in Iran during the 1970s, and enthusiastically cheered the post-revolution seizure of the US embassy in Tehran, when students took 52 American diplomats hostage for 444 days in 1981.

Believed to have between 5,000 and 13,000 members, the MEK was established in the 1960s to express a mixture of Marxism and Islamism. It launched bombing campaigns against the Shah, which continued after the 1979 Islamic revolution, against the Islamic Republic.

In 1981, in a series of attacks, it killed 74 senior officials, including 27 MPs. Later that year, the group’s bombings killed Iran’s president and prime minister.

During the Iran-Iraq war in the 1980s, the MEK, by then sheltered in camps in Iraq, fought against Tehran alongside the Iraqi dictator Saddam Hussein. The US-led invasion of Iraq in 2003 was a turning point for the group, which sought to reinvent itself as a democratic force.

Today, it has little visible support inside the country. The MEK portrays itself as a democratic political institution, although its internal structure is anything but.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/feb/04/french-law-forbids-food-waste-by-supermarkets" labels="France" title="French law forbids food waste by supermarkets" >
France has become the first country in the world to ban supermarkets from throwing away or destroying unsold food, forcing them instead to donate it to charities and food banks.

Under a law passed unanimously by the French senate, as of Wednesday large shops will no longer bin good quality food approaching its best-before date. Charities will be able to give out millions more free meals each year to people struggling to afford to eat.

The law follows a grassroots campaign in France by shoppers, anti-poverty campaigners and those opposed to food waste. The campaign, which led to a petition, was started by the councillor Arash Derambarsh. In December a bill on the issue passed through the national assembly, having been introduced by the former food industry minister Guillaume Garot.

Campaigners now hope to persuade the EU to adopt similar legislation across member states.

The law has been welcomed by food banks, which will now begin the task of finding the extra volunteers, lorries, warehouse and fridge space to deal with an increase in donations from shops and food companies.

Supermarkets will also be barred from deliberately spoiling food in order to stop it being eaten by people foraging in stores’ bins. In recent years, growing numbers of families, students, unemployed and homeless people in France have been foraging in supermarket bins at night to feed themselves. People have been finding edible products thrown out just as their best-before dates approached.

Some supermarkets doused binned food in bleach, reportedly to prevent food poisoning from items taken from bins. Other supermarkets deliberately binned food in locked warehouses for collection by refuse trucks.

Now bosses of supermarkets with a footprint of 400 sq metres (4,305 sq ft) or more will have to sign donation contracts with charities or face a penalty of €3,750 (£2,900).

Jacques Bailet, head of Banques Alimentaires, a network of French food banks, described the law as “positive and very important symbolically”. He said it would greatly increase an already emerging trend for supermarkets to donate to food banks.

“Most importantly, because supermarkets will be obliged to sign a donation deal with charities, we’ll be able to increase the quality and diversity of food we get and distribute,” he said. “In terms of nutritional balance, we currently have a deficit of meat and a lack of fruit and vegetables. This will hopefully allow us to push for those products.”

Until now French food banks received 100,000 tonnes of donated goods, 35,000 tonnes of which came from supermarkets. Even a 15% increase in food coming from supermarkets would mean 10m more meals being handed out each year, Bailet said.

Food banks and charities will, for their part, be obliged to collect and stock the food in properly hygienic conditions and distribute it with “dignity”. This means the food must be given out at a proper food bank or centre, where human contact and conversation is fostered, rather than, for example, simply organised as handoutson the street.

Crucially the law will also make it simpler for the food industry to give some excess products directly to food banks from factories. Until now, if a dairy factory made yoghurts carrying the brand name of a supermarket, it had been a long, complex process to donate any excess to charity. Now it would be faster and easier. “That is very important for food banks because this is a real source of quality products, coming straight from the factory,” Bailet said.

Derambarsh, who is a municipal councillor for Courbevoie, about five miles north-west of Paris, said: “The next step is to ask the president, François Hollande, to put pressure on Jean-Claude Juncker and to extend this law to the whole of the EU. This battle is only just beginning. We now have to fight food waste in restaurants, bakeries, school canteens and company canteens.”

Carrefour, France’s biggest supermarket group, said it welcomed the law, which would build on food donations its supermarkets already made.

France, so far, goes further than the UK, where the government has a voluntary agreement with the grocery and retail sector to cut food and packaging waste in the supply chain and does not have mandatory targets. However, a UK food waste bill, with similar provisions, was introduced to the Commons last September by the Labour MP Kerry McCarthy.

Of the 7.1m tonnes of food wasted in France annually, 67% is binned by consumers, 15% by restaurants and 11% by shops. Each year 1.3bn tonnes of food are wasted worldwide.

A report published in 2015 showed that UK households threw away 7m tonnes of food in 2012, enough to fill London’s Wembley stadium nine times over. Avoidable household food waste in the UK is associated with 17m tonnes of CO2 emissions annually.

• This article was amended on 8 February 2016 to correct the penalty that could be imposed on supermarkets that flout the law. An earlier version gave this as fines of up to €75,000 (£53,000) or two years’ imprisonment.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jul/15/why-does-france-keep-getting-attacked" labels="France" title="Why does France keep getting attacked?" >
So once again, there will be the tricolour flag projected on buildings around the world, a hashtag expressing solidarity with France, and declarations of sympathy.

There will also be the question: why is France suffering a wave of extremist violence that is more intense – certainly more lethal – than any other seen in the west since the 9/11 attacks almost 15 years ago?

Though it is still unclear if the driver of the truck in Nice was linked to any broader network or organisation - prosecutors on Friday said only that his actions were in line with an Isis call to action - his attack is a grim reminder of the bloodshed on Paris just months ago.

One reason that France is a particular target is down to a specific decision by Islamic State to target it. In September 2014, shortly after the beginning of airstrikes by a US-led coalition which includes France, the chief spokesman for Isis, Mohammad al-Adnani, singled out the “spiteful French” among a list of enemies in a speech calling for the group’s sympathisers to launch attacks across the west.

Undoubtedly, the role France has historically assumed as standard bearer of western secular liberalism has also put the nation in the spotlight. Islamic extremists may see the US as a source of moral decadence and economic exploitation, but France is seen as an atheist power which is both defending western ideals such as human rights, free speech and democracy and, in the eyes of jihadis, trying to impose them on the Islamic world.

We know from interrogations of Isis returnees that the group started planning strikes in France even before it seized the Iraqi city of Mosul and declared a caliphate in 2014.

The first big militant attack in France in recent years came earlier however, in 2012, and targeted soldiers and the Jewish community. The next major attack was against the offices of Charlie Hebdo, a satirical magazine which had published controversial cartoons of the prophet Muhammad, deemed insulting by many Muslims. Then came November’s Isis-organised strike against a concert hall, bars and a football stadium – all representative of French life. Finally there is an attack on Bastille Day, with all the history and values it represents.

Successive governments in Paris have also taken a hard – and much publicised – line on issues such as the wearing of full-body coverings and the veil in public, which has been well noted by Islamic militants. So has the increasingly prominent French military role overseas. French forces have made a series of interventions in the Islamic world in recent years – in Libya, in Mali, where its troops rolled back one of the most successful Islamic militant offensives outside Syria or Iraq for many years, and of course in the coalition against Isis.

Other reasons for the violence are rooted in grave problems within France itself which have made the nation vulnerable.

Some of these are failings of the fragmented, bureaucratic and still under-resourced security services. A French parliamentary investigation into last year’s terrorist attacks on Paris highlighted a “global failure” of French intelligence and called for the creation of a single, US-style national counterterrorism agency.

All the extremists involved in the attacks had been previously flagged to authorities, the investigation found. Some had past convictions, or were under judicial surveillance in France or in Belgium when they struck Paris.

A recruitment push aimed at boosting the numbers of French spies was started late, at the end of 2014, and is only now beginning to show results, not least due to the time taken to find and then train new staff.

But France’s security also depends on structures at a European level – which have been repeatedly found wanting. Last years’ attacks in Paris and those in Belgium in March highlighted the yawning gap between the capabilities of the continent’s security services and the gravity of the new threat created by the conflict in Syria. Intelligence sharing had not, experts say, kept up with the new dangers posed by freedom of movement within much of the expanded EU.

The cutting edge of this threat is of course the European nationals who have travelled to fight with Isis or, to a lesser extent, other similar militant outfits. There are now estimated to be more than 600 French citizens or residents currently in Syria or Iraq, of which 400 are fighters.

This does not put France – despite its substantial Muslim population – in the top rank of source countries for fighters, but nonetheless it means there is a big pool of potential attackers on which Isis could draw. Those responsible for the Paris attacks in November were French or Belgian citizens drawn from camps in Syria run by Isis and sent back into Europe. The driver of the truck in Nice was not reportedly known to the security services, only to local police for a series of violent offences and thefts.

France has a history of Islamic extremism reaching back decades. The 1990s saw two waves of attacks. One was linked to the bloody civil war between authorities and extremist groups in the former colony of Algeria. A second involved homegrown militants in the north of France who evolved a particular brand of terrorism mixing armed robbery and jihadism.

Like other western European nations, France imported large numbers of labourers from former or existing colonies to help with post-war reconstruction, without considering that they would stay, or that they would bring their families to join them. The integration of the resulting communities posed challenges all over the continent, but they were particularly acute in France, not least because of the violence and trauma of the Algerian war of independence. In recent years, as elsewhere in Europe and the Islamic world, rigorous and intolerant strands of Islamic observance have made inroads, as well as, more recently, a new, debased, ultra-violent “gangsta Jihad” culture attractive to a young and often marginalised constituency.



Almost all those involved in violence in France in recent years have had similar profiles – aged between 18 and 36, often with a record of involvement in petty crime, known to police if not security services, often served jail sentences, from backgrounds which if not poverty-stricken were far from wealthy, and with insecure, temporary or poorly paid jobs.

The “banlieues” or suburbs where many such men grew up or live are often physically and culturally isolated from more wealthy, integrated neighbourhoods. They are certainly very distant from the France of wine and charcuterie, chateaux and cheese. This gap has not been closed by the French policy of “assimilation” rather than multi-cultural integration into the supposedly secular republique, and has, critics say, created fertile ground for polarisation.

And this may be a final reason why Isis has focused on France. The group has been heavily influenced by both millennial thinking, which stresses the imminent final battle between the forces of belief and unbelief, as well as jihadi strategic thinking, which encourages extremists to use violence to destabilise states or nations to allow their eventual conquest.

Isis thus seeks to terrorise its enemies and mobilise its supporters but above all polarise those communities, which might then turn against one another. In its literature it has specifically pointed to France as a place where “the grey zone” of tolerance and moderation can be usefully targeted and destroyed.

Some observers in France have said the nation has been brought closer together by the recent violence. Not all agree. Patrick Calvar, head of the French Direction Générale de la Sécurité Interieure, recently warned that his country was “on the brink of a civil war between rightwing and Islamist extremists”.

“Extremisms are rising everywhere and … this confrontation, I think it will happen. One or two more attacks, and we will see it,” Calvar said last month.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/live/2019/feb/10/england-v-france-six-nations-live" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="England 44-8 France: Six Nations – as it happened" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/live/2019/feb/01/france-v-wales-six-nations-2019-live" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="France 19-24 Wales: Six Nations 2019 – as it happened" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2018/dec/17/france-alone-new-tax-big-tech-companies-gafa" labels="Facebook" title="France pushes forward alone with new tax on big tech companies" >
France is to press ahead alone with a new tax on big technology companies after struggling to secure agreement for a EU-wide levy.

The French finance minister, Bruno Le Maire, said he believed the tax, which will take effect from 1 January, would raise €500m (£450m) in its first year.

France has been pushing for a EU GAFA tax – named after Google, Apple, Facebook, Amazon – but faced opposition from countries including Ireland, which hosts the European headquarters of several technology companies, including Google and Apple.

The Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), a group of major world economies, has been working on proposals for an international scheme that would regulate taxation on technology companies.

France has also been working with Germany on plans for a 3% tax on EU advertising sales that would begin in 2021.

The plans are a response to the often complex corporate structures set up by several companies that derive huge revenues from major European economies but allow them slash their tax bills by shifting profits to low-tax jurisdictions.

Progress on both the OECD and the Franco-German proposals has been slow, prompting France to move ahead unilaterally.

“The tax will be introduced whatever happens on 1 January and it will be for the whole of 2019 for an amount that we estimate at €500m,” Le Maire told a press conference in Paris.

Several countries, including the UK, have said they are also minded to impose new taxes on technology companies, aware of public frustration at their often meagre contribution to economies from which they make money.

The chancellor, Philip Hammond, promised to introduce a digital sales tax in his budget in October to ensure that “global giants with profitable businesses in the UK pay their fair share”.

He said the UK could no longer wait for “painfully slow” discussions at international level and would instead introduce a 2% tax on certain types of sales, which he claimed would raise £400m a year.

Spain and Italy are also working on national versions of a digital tax, as are Singapore and India.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/travel/france" labels="" title="France holidays" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2019/feb/01/france-wales-six-nations-2019-match-report" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="George North seals thrilling Wales comeback after France throw it away" >
Madness – but is it not always between these two? Or, at the very least, when France play. Still there is no knowing who or where they are. Les Bleus tore Wales apart in the first half – as much as any side can be torn apart in rain like this. The visitors did not know where to turn, their quiet confidence before this tournament shredded, their composure shot.

France went into the break with a 16-0 lead but it could have been more, Morgan Parra missing three kicks at goal. No international side should lose a lead like that at home – not even France. How they laugh in the face of received wisdom. Here they handed Wales the game in the most agonising manner, yielding three tries in the second half, each one softer than the previous, the third just after they had regained a lead they had somehow lost with nearly 20 minutes to play.

And so Wales claimed a 10th consecutive win with this, the biggest comeback in their history. “The big difference between the two,” said Warren Gatland, “is that we’ve become a side that have forgotten how to lose and France are a side still looking for confidence.”

It was unbearable to watch, such had been France’s form in the first half. Wales were braced for a battering by one of the heaviest packs known to rugby, nearly 50kg heavier than their own. When the rain set in an hour or so before kick-off that expectation turned into an assumption. Sure enough, France confounded us all there too. French power up front was the least of Wales’s problems.

Les Bleus had also picked a backline of more traditional elan and they were not afraid to use it. Threats came at Wales from every player, one to 15, and never once from anything so slow or predictable as a rumble up front. Louis Picamoles cut back after one fluent move to score the game’s first try after only five minutes. At the start of the second quarter France had their second.

Damian Penaud cut Wales up down the right, the French midfield conveyed the ball sweetly left where Arthur Iturria, yet another threat, this one unexpected on the flank, released Yoann Huget for the corner and a 10-0 lead. This time two years ago, in the infamous 100-minute match, Wales had been kept in the match by the boot of Leigh Halfpenny. He was absent here, which was a mixed blessing. No reliable marksman but at least Liam Williams could showcase his talents.

As ever he proved Wales’s most threatening player. After one slashing run he was denied only by Picamoles’s tackle. Then another run won Wales a penalty. Gareth Anscombe was given the tee in Halfpenny’s absence and missed that shot at goal and another in the first half, a failing that seemed to spread to the rest of his game. He and his half-back partner, Tomos Williams on his Six Nations debut, endured a torrid time in that first half. On the approach to the break Williams carried over and France won a penalty from the subsequent play, which Camille Lopez converted. On the stroke of half-time Lopez extended the lead with an audacious drop goal.

But this is France. No one is ever quite safe against them, but neither are they ever quite beaten by them. Sure enough, nothing looked on as Wales swung the ball aimlessly back and forth five minutes into the second half, but Josh Adams suddenly waltzed clean through France’s fringe defence to find Williams on hand for the try. Redemption for the young scrum-half just before he was replaced. In between, though, Wales struck again and this time the gift from France was toe-curling.

A nothing kick to the try line from Hadleigh Parkes was fumbled by Huget and George North scooped up the ball to touch it down. Wales, barely 10 minutes into the second half, were within two points. They thought they were ahead just a few minutes after that. Ross Moriarty went over but he was called back for obstruction. Worse, a penalty that might have calmed French nerves was pushed wide by Lopez.

Now it was France’s composure that was shot. And their lead followed. Dan Biggar does not tend to miss and his penalty had Wales ahead on the hour. It had come from a scrum, the very area we had expected France to dominate. Expectation – indeed, reason itself – had left the building. So at the next scrum, penalty, of course, to France and Lopez, with 10 minutes to go, put France back in the lead.

Then the maddest moment of them all. Sébastien Vahaamahina, one of France’s biggest, decided to fling a 30-metre pass as if he were France’s deftest. North again pounced on it to gallop home. Wales got away with this one. France will be, well, mad.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/21/france-urged-to-return-looted-african-art-treasures-macron" labels="France" title="France urged to change heritage law and return looted art to Africa" >
A report commissioned by Emmanuel Macron will call for thousands of African artworks in French museums taken without consent during the colonial period to be returned to the continent.

Unless it could be proven that objects were obtained legitimately, they should be returned to Africa permanently, not on long-term loan, said the authors of the report, the Senegalese writer and economist Felwine Sarr and the French historian Bénédicte Savoy.

They have recommended changing French law to allow the restitution of cultural works to Africa, after Macron announced that he wanted it to begin within five years.

“I cannot accept that a large part of the cultural heritage of several African countries is in France,” the French president said last year in Ouagadougou, the capital of Burkina Faso. “There are historical explanations for this but there is no valid, lasting and unconditional justification. African heritage cannot be only in private collections and European museums – it must be showcased in Paris but also in Dakar, Lagos and Cotonou. This will be one of my priorities.”

The extent to which France, Britain and Germany looted Africa of its artefacts during colonialism is not known, but according to the report, which will be released this Friday, about 90% of Africa’s cultural heritage currently lies outside the continent.

The report’s authors travelled to Mali, Senegal, Cameroon and Benin and looked through the works held by the Musée du quai Branly, a museum focused on non-European cultures in Paris, and found that about 46,000 of its 90,000 African works were “acquired” between 1885 and 1960 and may have to be returned.

The report could pave the way for other former colonial powers to consider the provenance of their own collections. British troops destroyed much of the beautiful city of Benin in 1897, burning the royal palace to the ground and looting 4,000 works of art, including elegant brass heads and intricate plaques depicting war exploits, known as the Benin bronzes.

On Tuesday, the governor of Easter Island in the Pacific tearfully begged the British Museum to return one of its famous statues. The London museum has held the Hoa Hakananai’a, one of the most spiritually important of the Chilean island’s stone monoliths, for 150 years.

The British Museum in London has about 700 articles from Benin, and about 100 of them are displayed in an underground gallery. Several European institutions including the British Museum plan to “lend” works to a new museum in Benin City, in modern-day Nigeria, due to open in 2021. The security of African works is sometimes cited as a reason not to hand them over to African museums.

The systematic looting of African art took different forms: the researchers found that as well as being the spoils of war, theft and pillage, many of the works had been “bought” for fractions of their real value.

A law would need to be passed in France to change the code of patrimony, and then African countries would have to request that their stolen works be returned. They would be better equipped than ever to do so, because the researchers have sent them lists of the objects.

“Travelling in Africa, we saw the effect that these inventories can have, especially on museum directors,” Savoy told Libération. “They never had access to these lists, and never in such a clear and structured way. Highly knowledgeable researchers and teachers were really incredulous when we told them there were so many of their countries’ objects at quai Branly.”

To start with, they have recommended that palace doors, thrones and statues stolen from Abomey be returned – something the modern-day country of Benin has long requested.

“Today it feels as if we’re just a step away from recovering our history and being finally able to share it on the continent,” said Marie-Cécile Zinsou, the daughter of Benin’s former prime minister and the president of the Zinsou Art Foundation in Cotonou.

AFP contributed to this report
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/live/2019/feb/23/france-v-scotland-six-nations-2019-live" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="France 27-10 Scotland: Six Nations 2019 – as it happened" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/mar/13/france-in-car-breathalysers-drink-drive-motorists-disable-motor" labels="France" title="France introduces in-car breathalyser that can disable motor" >
French motorists convicted of drink driving will be allowed to continue using their vehicles by fitting them with a breathalyser machine under a new decree.

The new machines will stop the vehicle motor from starting if the driver has been drinking.

The interior minister, Christophe Castaner, approved the move after a year-long trial of the scheme in seven French departments.

Until now, drink drivers could lose up to six points on their driving licence – in France drivers start with 12 points on their licence, which can be deducted by a maximum of six for each offence – but faced no automatic ban. Once all 12 points are lost, the licence is suspended for six months.

The scheme gives courts the power to order drink drivers convicted of a first offence and with a blood alcohol level of between 0.8 and 1.8 g/l, to install the breathalysers at their own cost, estimated at more than €1,300 to buy and install or €100 a month to rent, for a maximum of six months.

This period could be extended to up to five years by a magistrate who can also impose a maximum fine of €4,500.

Drink drivers will have to blow into the breathalyser to start their vehicle. They will then be required to blow a second time – randomly set at between five and 30 minutes later – to ensure they remain under the alcohol limit and limit the chances of drunk drivers asking someone else to blow into the breathalyser.

The government said the aim was to ensure motorists convicted of drink driving who needed their vehicles for professional reasons could continue to work.

Dr Philippe Lauwick, president of the health committee at the National Council for Road Safety, said the new test was a “very useful tool in the fight against repeat offending”.

More than one in five road accidents in France are caused by drink driving. In 2017, 1,035 were killed in accidents involving drivers who were over the alcohol limit.

The move comes just weeks after the death toll on French roads was found to be increasing. There were 3,448 deaths in 2018 compared with 3,456 the previous year. In the UK, the number of road deaths for the same period was 1,770.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/mar/15/france-repatriates-five-orphaned-children-of-jihadists-from-syria" labels="France" title="France repatriates five orphaned children of jihadists from Syria" >
France has repatriated five orphaned children of French jihadists from camps in north-east Syria, where a five-year offensive against Islamic State is drawing to a close.

Among the children repatriated were the three sons of a French woman who died under Isis rule. Officials retrieved them from a camp in northern Syria where they were being held with as many as 3,000 other children of Isis families.

Al-Hawl camp is one of two detention centres that the British government says is too dangerous to visit. It is home to children of foreign nationals from more than 40 countries.

The newborn son of the British teenager Shamima Begum was among them until his death last Thursday, which provoked outrage over the UK’s reluctance to rescue him or any other children born to parents with links to Isis.

The French intervention is likely to add weight to the criticism, given that Kurdish officials said they had agreed to the repatriation as soon as Paris lodged a request. Residents of the camp said the three children removed were Yasir, Shakhir and Jaffir, the sons of Julie Maninchedda and Martin Lemke, a German national held in al-Roj camp along with other alleged Isis fighters.

The French foreign ministry acknowledged the rescue mission in a brief statement but did not disclose the children’s names. They had been cared for by a South African woman who has also become a caregiver for other vulnerable children. Lemke, who is accused of belonging to Isis’s feared security division, has had no access to his children since his capture. Two more of his wives remain in al-Hawl.

The question of what to do with the children of Isis-affiliated families has vexed foreign governments. Most have been unwilling to repatriate them, primarily because of legal and security issues surrounding their parents. France has said it would bring as many as 130 children back to Paris, in many cases unaccompanied by mothers of fathers who face criminal charges. Maninchedda’s children are likely to be handed over to their maternal grandmother.

The US has reiterated an earlier demand that its allies take back their foreign fighters and families, while at the same time appearing reluctant to heed its own counsel.

The US special representative for Syrian engagement, James Jeffrey, said: “We’re making a major campaign to have other countries take back prisoners to deal with them either through prosecution, through re-education, whatever their constitution and legal system allows, but we do not think it’s fair to keep these people simply under Syrian Democratic Forces control indefinitely.

“We think they’re secure while they’re there, but we think that this is an unfair division of labour, frankly, internationally by putting the burden on the SDF which is essentially a local fighting force. So thus our appeal to countries to take back both the families of fighters and the fighters themselves.”

The Trump administration, however, has said it will not allow the return of the US national Hoda Muthana, who is also in al-Hawl camp, along with a young son born to a Tunisian jihadist.

The UK has so far refused to help to rescue the children of foreign fighters, saying the obligation lies with their parents to seek British consular access outside a war zone.

Jeffrey said the US had received positive responses to its request for allies to provide troop contingents in north-west Syria to help fill the vacuum caused by the withdrawal of some US troops. France and the UK are likely to form the backbone of any additional deployment, he said.

Donald Trump made a surprise announcement in December that the US would reduce its troop presence in Syria from 2,000 to about 400.

The US wants to form a protection zone for Syrian Kurds involved in the SDF. The predominantly Kurdish force has been at the forefront of the battle to defeat Isis, and it fears that without US or allied protection Turkey will attack Kurdish-held villages. Ankara does not distinguish between the Syrian Kurds and their separatist Turkish counterparts.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/live/2019/mar/16/italy-v-france-six-nations-2019-live" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="Italy 14-25 France: Six Nations – as it happened!" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2019/mar/22/euro-2020-qualifiers-roundup-france-portugal" labels="Euro 2020" title="Euro 2020 qualifiers: France turn on the style but Portugal held to draw" >
France turned on the style in their opening Euro 2020 qualifier, winning 4-1 in Moldova. Goals from Antoine Griezmann, Raphaël Varane, Olivier Giroud and Kylian Mbappé made it a comfortable victory for the world champions, with Vladimir Ambros scoring for the home side.

Paul Pogba’s exquisite ball over the top was volleyed home from close range by Griezmann, who turned provider three minutes later as his corner was headed home at the near post by Varane.

Giroud then moved to joint third on France’s all-time top scorers’ list, alongside David Trezeguet on 34 goals, after coolly volleying home Blaise Matuidi’s cross in the 36th minute. Mbappé got on the scoresheet three minutes from time after being teed up by Thomas Lemar.

Elsewhere in Group H, Burak Yilmaz and Hakan Calhanoglu scored as Turkey won 2-0 in Albania, while Iceland beat Andorra by the same scoreline, thanks to Birkir Bjarnason and Vidar Kjartansson.

Cristiano Ronaldo’s Portugal were frustrated by a dogged Ukraine in a 0-0 draw in Lisbon. Also in Group B, Leandro Barreiro and Gerson Rodrigues were on target as Luxembourg came from a goal down to defeat Lithuania 2-1.

England’s Group A rivals Bulgaria and Montenegro drew 1-1 in Sofia, Todor Nedelev’s penalty eight minutes from time ensuring a stalemate after Stefan Mugosa had opened the scoring just after half-time.

Lionel Messi played for Argentina in a friendly but they were embarrassed 3-1 by Venezuela in Madrid, with Newcastle’s Salomón Rondón among the goalscorers.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2018/nov/13/trump-macron-eu-army-german-second-world-war" labels="Donald Trump" title="Trump ramps up Macron spat by mocking France in world wars" >
Donald Trump ramped up his spat with Emmanuel Macron, the French president, with a denigrating tweet in which he said Parisians had started to learn German during the second world war before the US saved them from occupation.

The US president’s Tuesday morning tweet exacerbates his standoff with Macron following his visit to Paris over the weekend that was marred by his controversial behavior.

Trump’s outburst came as France marked the third anniversary of the 2015 Bataclan terror attack in which a coordinated wave of suicide bombings and gun attacks left nearly 130 people dead.

In the tweet Trump repeated his accusation that Macron had called for a European army as protection against the US – an apparent misreading of Macron’s earlier comments.

He followed soon after with a second caustic tweet in which he accused France of unfair trade practices over imports and exports of French and US wine.

The biting words represent an escalation of the attack Trump made on Friday in which he said Macron had been “very insulting” by suggesting Europe needed its own army to protect itself against the US, China and Russia. Trump appeared to be conflating, however, Macron’s desire to strengthen Europe’s military forces – an ambition Trump himself has demanded as he seeks to reduce US contributions to Nato – and comments made by the French president in a radio interview about the threat of cyber-hacking from other countries including the US.

Guy Verhofstadt, the chief representative for the European parliament on Brexit, shot back at Trump.

“What Trump doesn’t seem to realize is that without French money, the USA would not even exist as France financed the American revolution. They even gave you the Statue of Liberty to celebrate this!” Verhofstadt tweeted.

Trump has also been riled by Macron’s warning on Sunday, at a ceremony to mark the 100th anniversary of the end of the first world war, about the thrust of global politics. Macron, clearly with Trump partly in mind, denounced those who embrace nationalism and put “our interests first”, adding that “our demons are resurfacing”.

In a rally in Houston, Texas in the final days of this month’s US midterm elections, Trump called himself a “nationalist”. One of his mantras throughout his political rise has been “America first”.

On Tuesday morning, the president’s tweetstorm continued. He said Macron was suffering low approval ratings while France suffers from high unemployment, then added: “By the way, there is no country more Nationalist than France…”

He finished the sequence by taunting, in capitals: “MAKE FRANCE GREAT AGAIN!”

Asked to comment, the office of the French president said it had nothing to say about the tweets. It said Macron had made his points about a European army and European defence very clear to Trump during talks in Paris.

Macron is not the only French element engaging in a social media dispute with Trump. On Monday the French army waded in, expertly playing the US president at his own game – trolling him.

Alluding to Trump’s decision to cancel a visit to an American cemetery outside Paris during his official visit because of rain, the Armée de Terre posted a picture on its official Twitter feed of a soldier training in a downpour. It said: “Il y a de la pluie, mais c’est pas grave [it is raining, but it is not a big deal].”

Macron’s advisers have a longstanding policy on not commenting on any of Trump’s tweets. In Paris, officials have indicated that Trump’s tweets are different to the real relationship between the French and US leaders.

One adviser to Macron stressed that Trump and Macron speak several times a week by phone on all subjects. Trump was also the first world leader to meet Macron at the Elysée on the weekend of the armistice commemorations – for a bilateral meeting on Saturday – an important gesture that showed the importance of the Paris-Washington relationship, officials said.

In the tweets, Trump lambasted Macron for low popularity ratings. Macron, who was elected president last May after beating the far-right Marine Le Pen, has seen his approval ratings fall to below 30% as French voters complained his promised “transformation” of France was not fixing their daily difficulties in making ends meet. Although Macron’s popularity ratings have fallen in France’s regular flurry of opinion polls, his centrist party still dominates the French parliament and can easily pass all legislation.

Trump’s relationship with Macron – who is the same age as his eldest son, Donald Trump Jr – began last year with Trump repeatedly praising Macron as a “winner”.

An adviser to Macron stressed that the French president hadclearly explained his position on a more integrated European defence system, stressing that France was not making a choice between a European defence mechanism and multilateral organisations such as Nato. In recent months, Macron has warned that Europe can no longer depend on the US for its military defence and called for an urgent new European security policy.

Trump also tweeted about the fact that he didn’t attend the cemetery ceremony in the rain, saying he had suggested driving there but secret service officers advised against it.

• This article was amended on 13 November 2018 to change our translation of “c’est pas grave” from “it’s not serious” to “it is not a big deal”, which is a more idiomatic translation.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2019/mar/21/marseille-falls-apart-why-is-frances-second-city-crumbling" labels="Cities" title="Marseille falls apart: why is France's second city crumbling?" >
I
n her flat in a decrepit 18th-century building in the centre of Marseille, Samira ran her hand over a crack in her kitchen wall. “I worry my building is slowly caving in,” she said. “I’m scared we’ll end up buried alive.”

The stone staircase up to other damp apartments was sloping and wonky and residents felt that it moved as they used it. A crack in one wall was so deep, daylight seeped through. A burly teenager on an upper floor had been regularly told by his father not to step on parts of the increasingly uneven kitchen floor, which he feared was subsiding. Samira’s bathroom ceiling was sodden with mould and damp. After dark, rats made so much noise in her kitchen that it sounded as if she was being burgled.

“I have to take sleeping pills at night, otherwise I’m too scared to close my eyes for fear the ceiling will cave in,” she said.

Marseille, France’s second city, is facing its biggest crisis in decades as city-centre residents fear historical buildings that have turned to slums could crumble and fall. Grief and fury spread through the heart of the city after eight people were killed in November when two buildings collapsed near the picturesque old port.

Citizens’ protests groups are asking how a city that has spent millions in the past decade on high-profile waterfront museum projects and attracting cruise-ship visitors could abandon residents and architecture to fatal neglect. In 2015, a government report warned that 40,000 dilapidated and dangerous homes were a health or security risk to 100,000 people, many in the city centre, but campaigners say little was done.

Hundreds of families in Marseille have been evacuated from flats feared to be unsafe in recent months. Around 1,000 people – many on low incomes – are still sleeping in hotels, waiting to be rehoused.

Samira’s decrepit building was one of those recently evacuated – fire officers told her to grab her medication and a bag of her children’s clothes and flee. Residents spent several weeks in a hotel before the private landlord and a city hall expert declared the building safe to move back to. But families fear renovations weren’t enough. “I don’t feel safe,” said Yassin, 30. “When I hear a neighbour walking around upstairs, I pray my ceiling won’t give way.”

The crisis has highlighted Marseille’s unique makeup. With a population of around 850,000, it is smaller than the likes of Barcelona and Naples, and its diverse society is seen as symbol of modern France. But following industrial decline, a high number of its residents still live in poverty.

Most other cities in western Europe have pushed their poorest to the outskirts, but Marseille still has diverse, low-income, working-class districts in its centre. The city’s rich residents and bourgeoisie have historically retreated to the coast, the outskirts or the villages beyond.

And yet Marseille’s city centre has little social housing and a lot of squalid properties run by slum landlords, while property speculation is increasing.

Housing campaigners have warned of a deliberate policy of neglect. They fear local authorities could use the crisis of crumbling buildings to evacuate and resettle poorer residents in rundown areas of northern Marseille, clearing the city centre for high-profit property deals.

“Marseille has the last remaining working-class city centre in France, maybe even in Europe,” said Carole Lenoble, a local architect campaigning to preserve the centre’s social mix.

“But there’s a strong real-estate pressure. There was a luxury hotel being built 100 metres from the buildings that collapsed in November. With that real-estate pressure comes a lack of will to build social housing. This crisis must not be used as an excuse to accelerate moves to push poorer people out of the centre. More social housing must be built.”

After the two buildings collapsed, on rue d’Aubagne in the Noailles district near Marseille’s picturesque old port on 5 November, it took days of searching through the rubble to find the victims. They included a mother from the Comores who dropped off her son at school that morning but never collected him, a painter, and residents from Tunisia and Algeria who had been living in the bustling, central area known for its food market.

Tenants had warned for weeks that the walls were moving and that cracks had appeared. Less than three weeks earlier, an expert had deemed the first floor of one building unsafe and the building was evacuated, but the residents were told it was safe to go back.

Anissa Harbaoui, 30, who runs an after-school club, knew Simona, an Italian economics graduate who died in the collapse. “She used to tell me she worried her building would fall down,” Harbaoui said. “But I always said: ‘That couldn’t happen here, this is the second biggest city in France.’ And now it feels like this city has left people to be killed in their own homes.”

Harbaoui, a member of the 5 November Collective campaigning for housing rights in the wake of the disaster, is now living in a hotel after being evicted from her own unsafe building. “One day I closed my door and part of the ceiling fell down,” she said. She had lived in two other unsafe buildings, where cracks and shifting staircases were commonplace. “I guess in Marseille, you get used to living like that,” she said.

“This has destroyed and devastated our neighbourhood,” said Gaye Félicité of the Ivoire restaurant in Nouailles. “People are sad and afraid,” said Sarr Elhadjé, a tailor on the street of the collapse.

Angry street protests have targeted Marseille’s right-wing mayor of 24 years, Jean-Claude Gaudin. “The deliberate political choice not to do maintenance on buildings and not to build social housing has brought us to this extreme point of people dying,” said the Socialist Nasséra Benmarnia, a former social worker.

But Gaudin, who said he would not resign, insisted city hall’s approach to housing could not be faulted. “My team and I have an ambitious plan to renovate old and unfit housing,” he said after the building collapse.

Trust in politicians has plummeted after investigative journalists in Marseille revealed that some politicians were themselves renting out squalid and dangerous flats at high prices.

“This could be a turning point, people are now realising how serious the housing crisis is,” said Patrick Lacoste of A City Centre for All, a Marseille campaign group.

“The social mix in the centre must be protected,” said Lucas Olivieri, 29, an accountant waiting to move back into his apartment near the site of the collapse. His 94-year-old grandfather, who was living upstairs from him, was once a docker at Marseille’s port.

Residents and shop-owners live in uncertainty. “I was a cutting a client’s hair when officials came into my shop saying: ‘You’ve got to leave because the building across the road might fall down,’” said Peace Uzoechi, a now working in a temporary shop.

Julia Serres, a mother of six, had been evacuated from a squalid flat that city authorities have since deemed safe to return to. But she feared the stairwell and rundown interior still looked unsafe. She was struggling to pay for a hotel room, afraid to go home. “We’re not animals, we pay our rent, we just want justice,” she said. “I’m so scared. I don’t want to die, I don’t want my children to die.”

Follow Guardian Cities on Twitter, Facebook and Instagram to join the discussion, catch up on our best stories or sign up for our weekly newsletter
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/27/italy-france-refugee-dispute-awakens-dark-colonial-legacy-migration" labels="Refugees" title="Italy and France’s refugee dispute awakens a dark colonial legacy" >
T
he ornate, sculpted facade of Paris’s Palais de la Porte Dorée is a majestic allegory: at its centre is France, symbolising peace, prosperity and abundance, surrounded by her “possessions”, the colonies, offering up their riches.

Today the magnificent art deco palace, built for the 1931 Colonial Exhibition, houses the History of Immigration Museum, a popular venue for school visits. Its director, Hélène Orain, says the museum is a vital reminder of France’s colonial past. “We have a duty to remember. We must say what we did, take responsibility for what was done, including the pillaging and abuses. Our role is to show how we changed the destinies of the countries and continents we colonised.”

For the students queueing outside the museum on a bitterly cold morning last week, the news headlines made their visit particularly pertinent. In an undiplomatic outburst, Italy’s deputy prime minister, Luigi di Maio, had blamed France for forcing poor African migrants to flee their countries by running them as de facto colonies.

“France has never stopped colonising tens of African states,” said Di Maio, leader of the populist Five Star Movement. “The EU should sanction France, and all countries like France, that impoverish Africa and make these people leave, because Africans should be in Africa, not at the bottom of the Mediterranean.”

His comments came after two boats carrying migrants sank, one off the coast of Libya and a second in the Mediterranean, drowning an estimated 170 people.

Quick to put the boot into Emmanuel Macron ahead of May’s European elections, Matteo Salvini, head of the far-right League party and Italy’s other deputy prime minister, said France had a “very bad government and president”. The language was hostile and on a subject always guaranteed to raise hackles in France: colonialism.

During the 2017 presidential election campaign, Macron caused the French right to hyperventilate after describing colonialism as a “crime against humanity” during a trip to a former colony, Algeria. Historian Gilles Manceron noted at the time that colonialism continued to haunt the collective French memory. “It’s an embarrassing question”, he wrote, that prompts “a form of denial” as well as “nostalgia in certain regions”.

But Di Maio went further than what L’Express magazine called “French bashing … à l’Italienne” and accused France of manipulating the economies of African countries that use the CFA franc as their currency, stifling their development.

The CFA franc – made up of two distinct but interchangeable currencies – is used in 14 central and west African countries. It is pegged to the euro at a fixed exchange rate and is guaranteed by the French treasury. To its proponents, it offers stability and control over inflation for the poorer nations that use it; to its critics, it is a symbol of French imperialism that hampers growth.

Patrick Smith of the Africa Report, an English-language magazine focusing on African economies and politics, said: “There are advantages for some and disadvantages for others, and individual countries have to assess it for themselves.”

Roland Marchal, an Africa specialist at the Paris-based National Centre for Scientific Research, agreed. “We can criticise France, and I often do, but Italy seems to be forgetting how it behaves in its former colonies, like Libya.

“Having the CFA is voluntary, so it’s for African economists to decide; it might be good for some countries and not for others.” He said Di Maio’s and Salvini’s comments were “utterly risible”.

At the heart of the ongoing Franco-Italian row, however, are the migrants themselves. Since the Five Star and League parties came to power in Rome last June, France and Italy, both hampered by the absence of a unified EU policy on mass migration, have been squabbling over where the thousands of desperate people saved in the Mediterranean should go.

Macron accused Italy, which has closed its ports to rescue vessels, of being “inhumane”. Rome accused Paris of “hypocrisy” after France tightened security along the French-Italian border to halt migrant crossings and refused to allow the migrant rescue ship Aquarius to dock at Marseille last September.

Smith said Di Maio’s and Salvini’s recent comments were just rhetoric. “They’re trying to keep up the pressure over migration, and Macron is an easy target,” he said. “When we look at the origin of the migrants in this latest wave, we see very few from CFA-zone countries.”

He added: “Europe’s relationship with Africa is dysfunctional for many reasons, but that’s down to all 28 countries, not just France.”

At the museum, Orain points out what some in the Italian government appear to have forgotten: that around 24 million Italians emigrated in the 19th and 20th centuries, many to France. “During that period Italy was a poor country and there was a massive wave of emigration … you can go to the end of the world and find Italian communities there,” she said.

And she thinks France should be more welcoming to those who seek to make a life in the country. “For a long time we wanted people from our colonies to come to France: we asked them to come here and used them in manufacturing, mining, textiles and as soldiers who were excellent cannon fodder in our wars.

“This story was never told. When people spoke about the ‘real France’ they talked about villages, the curé, the town hall, the church bells, the fields … They forgot that from a very early time there were immigrants working in those fields.

“We pillaged our colonies for human resources, and that was not positive. What we try to show here in the museum is how immigration has been positive for France and its history.”
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/27/spanish-pm-warns-may-brexit-delay-with-no-plan-not-reasonable-or-desirable" labels="Brexit" title="France will block Brexit delay without 'new choice' by UK" >
Emmanuel Macron has said France will block a Brexit delay unless there is a “new choice” by Britain, as Spain’s prime minister said that merely postponing the no-deal deadline would not be “reasonable or desirable”.

In a sign of the heightened risk of an accidental crash-landing for the UK, both leaders signalled their disapproval of Theresa May’s suggestion of a last-minute request for a two-month extension if her deal is voted down again.

The French president said there would need to be a clear purpose to delaying the UK’s exit from the EU, in comments that will inevitably raise cross-party concerns among those seeking to take no-deal Brexit off the table.

“We would support an extension request only if it was justified by a new choice of the British,” Macron said at a joint press conference held with the German chancellor, Angela Merkel. “But we would in no way accept an extension without a clear objective.

Merkel offered a more compromising tone. “We are absolutely in agreement, and I have talked to Theresa May about this in Sharm el-Sheik a couple of days ago, the exit agreement is valid,” Merkel said. “If Great Britain needs more time we will not oppose it but of course we are seeking an orderly exit. We regret this step, but it is reality and we now have to find a good solution.”

The Spanish prime minister,Pedro Sánchez, who has been a thorn in the UK prime minister’s side in recent months, told his parliament in Madrid that there would be conditions attached to an extension of the article 50 negotiating period.

May had suggested in the Commons on Tuesday that the UK could seek a short two-month extension for further talks should parliament not ratify the Brexit deal by 13 March.

But Sánchez, who is facing a general election in late April, said he would want to be clear that it was not merely delaying an inevitable crash-landing for the UK out of the EU.

The Spanish premier also insisted that there was no prospect of the EU softening in its rejection of a time limit on the Irish backstop or unilateral exit mechanism should the government wish to leave the shared customs territory it envisages to avoid a hard border on the island of Ireland.

Sánchez said: “The position of Spain, as I have conveyed to Prime Minister Theresa May in different telephone conversations, is the same: it is not possible to temporarily limit the backstop or to allow a unilateral exit from it.

“Due to its nature as a security mechanism, it is not possible to set a term for it. It is not only a matter of solidarity with one of our partners, Ireland, but also of preserving the peace that was achieved in Northern Ireland decades ago.”

Sánchez, who at one point threatened to veto the Brexit deal unless the UK offered some assurances that Gibraltar will only be covered with Madrid’s consent, added: “It cannot be ruled out that the British prime minister requests an extension of article 50 of the EU treaty as she said yesterday.

“And I want to make clear before this possible position of the British government, that although Spain is not going to oppose the concession of an eventual extension, it must have a certain perspective of resolution. Prolonging uncertainty by postponing deadlines is not a reasonable nor desirable alternative.”

An extension of article 50 requires unanimous support of all 27 heads of state and government. While all leaders would be under pressure to assent to a request by the UK, of whatever length, many leaders would favour a lengthier extension if there is no clear prospect of a deal getting through parliament in the coming months.

In Brussels, there is a debate on how best to respond to an expected request, with some senior officials warming to the idea of an extension of up to 21 months to allow the UK to fully develop its plans for the future.

Such a lengthy delay is opposed by others, however. The European parliament’s Brexit coordinator, Guy Verhofstadt, tweeted on Wednesday: “If the UK parliament rejects her deal, Theresa May would like to extend the negotiating period.

“In my firm opinion, if this happens, this can never be longer than a couple of months so that a cross-party majority can be found. But certainly not 21 months!

“The union has been taken hostage by the Brexit already for too long. The UK has had almost two years to make up its mind, now it is time to decide: A deal, no deal or stay. For the union it is high time that we can spend our energy on more positive projects and the in-depth reforms Europe desperately needs.”

Speaking to parliament for the last time before the general election, Sánchez said his cabinet would use a royal decree this Friday to introduce legislation to “cope with all the consequences of a no-deal Brexit”. The fast-tracked legislation would then be put before parliament for approval within 30 days.

Meanwhile, the EU’s chief negotiator, Michel Barnier, said he believed he could “save” the deal. “It is not accurate to say that the no-deal is the most likely scenario,” Barnier told France Info radio. “It’s a possibility. This is not yet a probability.”

EU and British negotiators are currently drafting a protocol on the backstop which the hope will allow the attorney-general, Geoffrey Cox, to revise his legal advice to parliament and suggest that the backstop would only be a “temporary” arrangement if triggered.

There are serious doubts in Brussels, however, that the assurances that will be offered can persuade sufficient MPs to back the deal. EU leaders have recently implored May to engage with Jeremy Corbyn on his offer to throw Labour’s support behind the deal in return for backing a customs union with the bloc.

“This treaty is not renegotiable, it can’t be reopened,” Barnier said. “But beside that we have another document, which is the political declaration, which is very precise and fixes the rules of the game for our future partnership – that’s the most important, what partnership for trade, fishing, transport, university, research, Erasmus, internal security, foreign policy, defence. That can perhaps be improved.”

He added: “If the Brits want it tomorrow morning to be more ambitious and for example not stop at a free trade agreement, but instead have a customs union, or even more, we’re ready to renegotiate that relationship.”
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/oct/02/france-blames-iran-for-foiled-bomb-attack-near-paris" labels="Iran" title="France blames Iran for foiled bomb attack near Paris" >
France has concluded that Iran’s ministry of intelligence was behind a foiled bombing attack that targeted a rally organised by an Iranian opposition group near Paris in June.

The Mujahedin-e-Khalq (MEK), a fringe organisation loathed by Iran’s establishment, had accused authorities in Tehran of planning the attack near Paris. An Iranian diplomat was among six people who had been arrested for allegedly plotting the bombing of the MEK event, which featured among its guests senior US politicians, including Rudy Giuliani, Donald Trump’s attorney.

French diplomatic sources said on Tuesday that they believed a ranking official from within the Iranian ministry of intelligence had ordered the attack. He was named as Saeid Hashemi Moghadam, a deputy minister and director general of intelligence.

Belgian authorities said in July that an Iranian diplomat, who works for Tehran’s mission to Austria, was arrested in Germany, while a married couple – Belgian citizens of Iranian heritage – were detained with “attempt at terrorist murder and preparing a terrorist crime” against the MEK.

It emerged on Tuesday that the Iranian diplomat Assadollah Assadi is poised to be extradited from Germany to Belgium for prosecution. The Belgian-Iranian couple were in a Mercedes car when they were stopped by special forces and arrested in Woluwe-Saint-Pierre, which is close to EU institutions in Brussels. According to Belgian media, police found 500 grams of TATP explosive and a detonator hidden in a toiletries bag.

On Tuesday France said it had frozen the assets of Assadi and Hashemi Moghadam, who it described as operatives acting on behalf of Iranian intelligence.

A joint statement from France’s interior, economic and foreign affairs ministries, said: “A planned bomb attack was foiled at Villepinte on June 30. This extremely serious attack that was to take place on our territory cannot go without a response.”

It went on: “Without prejudicing the results of a criminal proceedings taking against the initiators, the perpetrators and the accomplices of this planned attack, France has taken targeted and proportionate preventative measures in the form of adopting national measures to freeze the assets of Mr Assadollah Assadi and Mr Saeid Hashemi Moghadam, Iranian nationals, as well as the Internal Security Directorate of the Iranian Ministry of Intelligence,” the official statement read.

The asset freeze was published in France’s Official Journal on Tuesday and will last for six months. Jean-Yves Le Drian, foreign affairs minister, said the foiling of the bomb plot “confirms the need for a tough approach in our relations with Iran”.

Iran denied the allegations which it called a conspiracy to “sabotage Iran’s ancient and long-standing relations with France and other significant European countries”.

“We deny the accusations and forcefully condemn the Iranian diplomat’s arrest and call for his immediate release,” the foreign affairs ministry said in a statement.

But Tuesday’s news puts further strain in relations between Iran and France, which is among European countries defending the 2015 nuclear accord against Trump’s attempts to tear it up. France has postponed sending a new ambassador to the Iranian capital and has advised diplomats and other officials to postpone visits to Iran.

The foiled attack came ahead of a rare visit to Europe by the Iranian president, Hassan Rouhani, who was travelling to the EU to lobby officials to salvage the 2015 nuclear deal after Trump said the US would not honour it.

Iran has two parallel intelligence services, often competing and at times at odds with each other. Tuesday’s accusations were directed at the ministry of intelligence, which is nominally part of Hassan Rouhani’s government, but in fact heavily controlled by the supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.

The elite Revolutionary Guards, which act independently of Rouhani’s government, also has a powerful intelligence arm.

Tehran considers the MEK as a terrorist organisation – a view that until recently was shared by the US and the EU. The US removed it from its list of terror groups in 2012, but the MEK’s animosity with Iran’s rulers has earned it powerful allies in the west, most particularly among Trump associates such as John Bolton, who is the group’s most powerful advocate.

The bomb plot was discussed by Le Drian and his Iranian counterpart, Mohammed Javad Zarif, in a bilateral meeting during the recent United Nations general assembly.

A French diplomat told Le Monde it was an occasion to “mention the very heavy suspicions concerning the Iranians and the seriousness of those suspicions”.

In a separate operation, French anti-terrorist police arrested 11 people during raids on a pro-Iranian Shia Muslim association based in Grande-Synthe, a suburb of Dunkirk. Police said the arrests were not linked to the June bomb plot.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/mar/11/germanys-cdu-leader-denies-rift-with-france-over-vision-for-europe" labels="Germany" title="Germany’s CDU leader denies rift with France over vision for Europe" >
The leader of Germany’s governing party has denied a rift with France after she replied to Emmanuel Macron’s plans for a “European renaissance” making it clear Berlin’s enthusiasm remains limited mainly to further integration in the fields of industrial policy and defence.

In an opinion piece for the Welt am Sonntag newspaper, the Christian Democratic Union (CDU) leader, Annegret Kramp-Karrenbauer, backed the French president’s proposal to coordinate European defence policy with the UK even after its departure from the EU, calling for a “European security council involving Great Britain”.

The 1,900-word essay Getting Europe Right, published just days after Macron outlined plans for a raft of new European agencies and initiatives in an open letter, also suggests setting up a “symbolic project” of building a common European aircraft carrier, to “express the global role of the European Union as a power ensuring security and peace”.

But Kramp-Karrenbauer poured cold water over the social aspects of the French leader’s reform proposals, stating that “the communitarisation of debts, the Europeanisation of social systems, and the minimum wage would be the wrong approach”.

At least two of the German counterproposals run directly against the French national interest: the CDU leader implies that the European parliament’s second seat in Strasbourg is an “anachronism” to be abolished, and calls for the EU to have a permanent seat on the United Nations security council – something that can likely only be achieved by France giving up its own seat.

Kramp-Karrenbauer on Monday tried to squash any rumours of a Franco-German fallout. “There’s no rift,” she told Welt television. “The fact that the CDU has a different political view on the issue of redistribution, on the issue of completely uniform social standards … than the French is nothing new,” she said.

The detailed riposte to the French leader’s letter was unusual because it was authored by a politician who, while mooted as Angela Merkel’s likely successor, does not hold a post in the German government. The chancellor last week declined to comment in detail on Macron’s proposal.

Germany’s Social Democratic party, junior partners in Merkel’s current government, on Monday criticised the CDU leader’s restraint on the social policy dimension of Macron’s proposal.

The foreign minister, Heiko Maas, said the Christian Democrats risked “missing out on great opportunities out of diffidence”, and his SPD party colleague Achim Post pointed out that the aim to create framework conditions for an EU minimum wage were part of the two parties’ coalition treaty.

French media noted that Kramp-Karrenbauer’s response did not carry the same weight as one from Merkel, and should be considered as much a domestic play by the CDU leader as a fully fledged European strategy. Kramp-Karrenbauer was plainly playing to the conservative wing of her party, Le Monde suggested, and putting clear water between the CDU and the Greens and Social Democrats.

Nonetheless, some fundamental policy differences on Europe were evident, the paper said. “AKK shares the view of the French president that Europe must act urgently” in the face of multiple threats, it observed. “But she envisages different means to arrive at that end. For AKK it is a strong economy, not politics, that will guarantee a strong EU.”

But even if some of the CDU leader’s standpoints, including her call for a permanent German seat on the UN security council, would “annoy France”, it added, the two visions “share much common ground … What is at any rate clear is that a desire to advance the debate on Europe’s future has now been expressed, on both sides of the Rhine.”

Lucas Guttenberg, deputy director for Berlin’s Delors Institute thinktank, said it was noteworthy how little mention was made of the European commission in either Macron’s or Kramp-Karrenbauer’s proposals.

“If you read both proposals closely, there are some convergences and overlaps where you might not expect them,” Guttenberg told the Guardian. “The message seems to be: if more Europe, then through an intergovernmental approach. If I was in Brussels, I would be worried about that.”
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/football/france" labels="" title="France" >

</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/dec/19/france-orders-whatsapp-stop-sharing-user-data-facebook-without-consent" labels="WhatsApp" title="France orders WhatsApp to stop sharing user data with Facebook without consent" >
WhatsApp has been ordered to stop sharing user data with parent company Facebook or face sanctions.

The French data protection agency, Commission Nationale de l’Informatique et des Libertés (CNIL), said on Monday that WhatsApp did not have a legal basis to share user data under French law for “business intelligence” purposes. The messaging app must cease data sharing within a month, paying particular attention to obtaining users’ consent.

The watchdog said WhatsApp had violated its obligation to cooperate with CNIL and had not properly obtained users’ consent to begin sharing their phone numbers with Facebook.

“The only way to refuse the data transfer for ‘business intelligence’ purpose is to uninstall the application,” the CNIL said in a statement.

CNIL said that it considers the transfer of some data for security purposes to be legal, but that the sharing of non-essential information to improve the function of the app was not as users were not given the possibility to opt out.

Facebook bought WhatsApp in 2014, stating that it would begin sharing data from the messaging app to the wider social network’s ecosystem in 2016.

The move, which Facebook said was not possible at the time of acquisition of the messaging app, drew warnings from data regulators over explicit consent.

In October, European Union privacy regulators rapped WhatsApp for not resolving their concerns over the sharing of user data with Facebook a year after they first issued a warning.

The European Commission fined Facebook €110m (£94m) in May for providing incorrect and misleading information on its takeover of WhatsApp.

Only small fines can be issued by European data protection authorities currently, but from May 2018 the new EU General Data Protection Regulations will come into force, permitting fines up to 4% of global turnover, which translates as €20m.

CNIL said it had repeatedly asked WhatsApp to provide a sample of French users’ data transferred to Facebook but the company had explained it could not do so as it is located in the United States and “it considers that it is only subject to the legislation of this country”.

WhatsApp said in statement: “Privacy is incredibly important to WhatsApp. It’s why we collect very little data, and encrypt every message.

“We will continue to work with the CNIL to ensure users understand what information we collect, as well as how it’s used. And we’re committed to resolving the different, and at times conflicting, concerns we’ve heard from European Data Protection Authorities with a common EU approach before the General Data Protection Regulation comes into force in May 2018.”
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/dec/21/british-cocaine-smuggler-jailed-for-22-years-in-france" labels="Drugs trade" title="British cocaine smuggler jailed for 22 years in France" >
A Briton accused of being one of Europe’s biggest drug traffickers has been jailed for 22 years for smuggling more than a tonne of cocaine with a street value of €240m (£220m) into France in suitcases stashed on an Air France flight.

Robert Dawes, 46, was told he would have to serve at least 15 years with no possibility of parole over the 2013 drugs shipment from Venezuela to Paris.

Dawes, who had denied the charges, was arrested at his luxury villa on the Costa del Sol in 2015 after a lengthy investigation by authorities in Britain, France, Spain and South America.

“I continue to claim my innocence,” he said on Friday morning in his final statement to the special non-jury court in Paris. The case was tried by five judges who ordered Dawes and four accomplices – three Italians and one Briton – to pay a €30m fine.

“Far from a small-time fall guy, today we are judging men in the highest ranks of organised crime who supplied European networks,” the prosecutor, Isabelle Raynaud, told the court during the week.

Hailing the verdict, the deputy director of Britain’s National Crime Agency, Matt Horne, described Dawes as “one of the most significant organised criminals in Europe with a network that literally spanned the globe”.

“Dawes was prepared to use extreme levels of violence in order to further his reputation and take retribution against those who crossed him. Members or associates of his criminal group are known to have been involved in intimidation, shootings and murders,” Horne said.

The net tightened on Dawes after Spanish police secured a video showing him bragging to a member of a Colombian drugs cartel about his ownership of the cocaine found stuffed in 30 suitcases registered to ghost travellers. Spain extradited him to France shortly after his arrest.

Dawes had hoped to get the video dismissed on legal grounds, but a document submitted by his defence team in support of that claim turned out to be a forgery.

Dawes himself then surprised the court – and evidently his lawyers – by saying his claims in the video were “just a made-up story” intended to provoke the police into arresting him so that he could prove his innocence.

The court passed sentences ranging from five to 13 years for four accomplices: Briton Nathan Wheat, and Vincenzo Aprea, Carmine Russo and Marco Panetta of Italy.

The four were arrested after undercover officers tricked them into trying to transport some of the cocaine to Italy shortly after its arrival at Charles de Gaulle airport in Paris in September 2013.

A sixth defendant, Briton Kane Price, was acquitted.

The discovery of the cocaine on a flight from Caracas caused a stir in Venezuela, where the interior minister admitted the suitcases had gone through security scanners that had clearly showed the presence of drugs.

Venezuelan police arrested 25 people, including members of the military and an Air France manager.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/27/how-the-murders-of-two-elderly-jewish-women-shook-france-antisemitism-mireille-knoll-sarah-halimi" labels="The long read" title="" >
T
he body landed in the courtyard, not far from the building’s bins. Shortly before 5am on 4 April 2017, a 65-year-old woman was hurled from the third-floor balcony of a social housing project in the 11th arrondissement of Paris, a rapidly gentrifying area on the eastern side of the French capital. An hour earlier, that same woman – a retired doctor and kindergarten teacher – had been asleep in the small apartment where she had lived for the past 30 years. When she woke up, she saw the face of her 27-year-old neighbour in the darkness. The man, who still lived with his family on the building’s second floor, had first stormed into another apartment, whose tenants had locked themselves in a bedroom and called the police. By the time he climbed up the fire escape into his victim’s apartment, three officers were present in the building.

The autopsy would later reveal that the woman’s skull had been crushed, most likely with the telephone on her bedside table. Before and after his victim lost consciousness, the assailant beat her until the nightgown she was wearing – white, with a blue floral pattern – was soaked with her blood. He then dragged her body to the balcony of the apartment, and threw her over the railing – exactly the same way, he told prosecutors, as John Travolta does in The Punisher, the film he had been watching before the attack. “I killed the sheitan!” he yelled from the balcony, according to testimonies given by neighbours. “Sheitan” is an Arabic word for “devil”. Neighbours heard him repeatedly chant “Allahu Akbar”.

The victim was Lucie Attal, an Orthodox Jewish woman who sometimes used the name Lucie Attal-Halimi. The perpetrator, who confessed to the crime, was Kobili Traoré, a Franco-Malian Muslim. He later told authorities he knew that his victim was Jewish. According to her family, Attal had long felt afraid of Traoré. Her brother, William Attal, told me that Traoré had verbally abused her in the building’s elevator, and she had said she would only feel safe if he were in prison. In fact, Kobili Traoré may never go to prison for the killing: he has been in psychiatric detention since the night of the crime, and a French judge could rule that he is mentally unfit to stand trial.

In the immediate aftermath of Attal’s death, there was virtually no public discussion of her killing. With the upcoming presidential election dominating headlines, the defenestration of a Jewish woman in the 11th arrondissement of Paris was treated by the mainstream French press as a fait divers, the term used to describe a minor news story, which led to considerable outcry in the Jewish community. But after the victory of Emmanuel Macron, the case returned to the forefront, becoming a new frontline in France’s culture wars, among the most explosive in Europe.

The French Republic is founded on a strict universalism, which seeks to transcend – or, depending on your viewpoint, efface – particularity in the name of equality among citizens. In a nation that tends to discourage identity politics as “communautaire” and therefore hostile to national cohesion, the state not only frowns on hyphenated identities, but does not even officially recognise race either as a formal category or a lived experience. Since 1978, it has been illegal in France to collect census data on ethnic or religious difference, on the grounds that these categories could be manipulated for racist political ends.

But eliminating race did not eliminate racism or racist violence. In the case of Lucie Attal, the inescapable fact of the matter is that a Muslim killed a Jew in a society where those distinctions are supposed to be irrelevant. More than a year after the fact, exactly how to label Attal’s death remains a matter of bitter, and perhaps unresolvable, debate. To examine the case is to examine the fractures of the French Republic, the contradictions in the stories a nation tells itself.

Traoré has vehemently denied that antisemitism played a role in his crime, claiming instead that he acted in the throes of a psychotic episode triggered by cannabis. But for William Attal, the only way to understand his sister’s death is as an act of antisemitic violence. “He knew very clearly that Judaism was the motor of her life, that she had all the external signs of Jewishness,” Attal said. When we met in a cafe in the Paris suburb of Nogent-sur-Marne, he wore an anonymous red baseball cap instead of anything that might identify him as Jewish. “We have the obligation to cover the head, but we do not have the obligation to wear a kippa,” he said. “Understand?”

In February 2018, after considerable public outcry from Jewish organisations, who accused the criminal justice system of a cover-up, a French judge added the element of antisemitism to the charges against Traoré. But the case is far from closed. In July 2018, a second court-ordered psychiatric examination declared that the perpetrator was not of sound mind and was unfit to stand trial; a third examination is forthcoming. If he cannot be held accountable for his actions, Traoré cannot, legally speaking, be said to have had a motive. There is the possibility that Attal will have officially died in a random act of violence, as if she had simply been in the wrong place at the wrong time.

During the months of confusion, indecision and silence that followed the killing, people from every side of France’s political debate seized upon the case as evidence of whatever position they already held. In time, the story of Lucie Attal would become the inspiration for any number of politicised narratives, hardly any of which took into account the woman who had died, or even her actual name.

O
n 10 April – one week after the killing and three weeks before the presidential election’s first round – Marine Le Pen sat down for an interview with the newspaper Le Figaro. Two days earlier, Le Pen had shocked much of the country by claiming that the Vichy government’s participation in the Holocaust “was not France” and insisting that France was “not responsible” for the so-called Vel d’Hiv roundup of Parisian Jews in 1942. It was time, she said, for the French to be “proud to be French again”.

The Vel d’Hiv roundup ranks among the darkest days in modern French history, and is known even to schoolchildren as a synonym for national shame. On 16 July 1942, approximately 13,000 Jews were arrested and detained in the now-demolished Vélodrome d’Hiver racing arena in the shadow of the Eiffel Tower. From there, they were deported to Nazi concentration camps. Few of the deportees ever returned. What lingers in public consciousness is this: it was French police officers who carried out this assault on their fellow citizens, not their Nazi occupiers.

Pressing Le Pen on her Vel d’Hiv comments, the journalist from Le Figaro asked how she would respond to the condemnations her remarks had elicited from Jewish groups and the state of Israel. For the daughter of a convicted Holocaust denier trying to “de-demonise” her party, these kind of questions risked giving Le Pen precisely the kind of publicity she was desperate to avoid. So she changed the subject.

“What I’d rather we talk about is Islamist antisemitism,” Le Pen said. She had an anecdote ready. “Several days ago, a 61-year-old woman was thrown, defenestrated from the third floor, because she was Jewish. She was threatened and called a ‘dirty Jew’ by her neighbour, for several days – and that we never talk about.”

During a presidential election campaign that revolved around questions of national identity, Le Pen became the first public figure to discuss the killing of Attal. Yet Le Pen did not mention Attal by name, and she was wrong about her age. During the interview, Le Pen’s Twitter account mentioned that the victim – again unnamed – had been 70. In fact, she had been 65, but the details about the actual woman who had been killed were never the point.

On one level, Le Pen’s rhetorical pivot to “Islamist antisemitism” was an attempt to distance herself from her party’s history of Holocaust denial and to court Jewish voters anxious about the rise of Islamist terrorism. But for Le Pen, the killing of Attal – even before any of the details were known – served a much broader purpose. It was perhaps the most emotive example of what had been the Front National’s underlying message throughout the campaign, and which of late had trickled into the mainstream right: that the French Republic and Islam were fundamentally incompatible.

O
n 10 July, Kobili Traoré was formally interviewed by the judge investigating the case. Three months earlier, on the night of the crime, he had been taken into custody, and police discovered that he already had a considerable criminal record, having served time for aggravated violence and drug dealing. But when police tested him that night, the toxicology report showed a high level of cannabis in his bloodstream, and his behaviour was erratic enough that he was immediately sent to a psychiatric hospital. There he was examined by a respected psychiatrist, Daniel Zagury, who concluded that he was not of sound mind and was therefore not in a fit state to be interviewed by prosecutors. In the months that followed, Traoré remained in the hospital, under warrant but without being formally charged.

When the investigative judge finally interviewed Traoré in July, the young man insisted that antisemitism had not been his motive. “I have never had problems with Jews before,” Traoré said. He claimed that the killing had happened during a bout of temporary insanity. On the night of 4 April he had been with a friend, he said, watching The Punisher. Before turning on the television, the two had gone to evening prayers at the Omar mosque in the rue Morand, according to an investigative account by the French journalist Noémie Halioua. (Mohammed Hammami, that mosque’s former imam, was expelled from France in 2012, when Traoré was a teenager, for having allegedly incited hatred in sermons.) Traoré, who by all accounts was not a particularly observant Muslim, told the judge that he and a friend had gone to pray that night because he had not been feeling well. “I was feeling like I’d been oppressed by an exterior force,” he said in his interview, according to the transcript. “A demonic force.”

The young man defined that “demonic force” as a kind of delirium over which he had no control, induced by the several joints he had smoked. (According to Le Monde, Traoré smoked between 10 and 15 joints a day.) Asked why he had entered Attal’s apartment, he had no answer: “I still do not know,” he said. “It could have fallen on anyone – the Diarras, my family,” Traoré claimed, referring to the family whose apartment he had first entered, before climbing up from their balcony to the apartment of the woman he killed. Yet “it” did not fall on anyone else; it fell on Lucie Attal.

At one point in Traoré’s interview with prosecutors, he was interrogated about what he had said at the scene of the crime.

Investigator: Your family heard, and your sister and your mother have confirmed that you were not feeling well and that you were repeating “Sheitan, sheitan.” What does that mean?

Traoré: It’s “the demon”, in Arabic.

Investigator: Do you speak Arabic?

Traoré: No.

Investigator: Doesn’t it seem bizarre that you would designate [Attal] as the devil in a language you don’t speak?

In Zagury’s report, seen by Le Monde, the psychiatrist concluded that it was unlikely the killing was a premeditated antisemitic hate crime. However, the psychiatrist saw plenty of antisemitic mechanisms at work, including Traoré’s own confessions that he had somehow been triggered by the Torah and the menorah he saw in Attal’s apartment.

In his report, Zagury pointed out that the particular form delirious episodes take is always shaped by “society’s atmosphere and world events”. “Today, it is common to observe, during delirious episodes among subjects of the Muslim religion, an antisemitic theme: the Jew is on the side of evil, the evil one,” he wrote. “What is normally a prejudice turns into delirious hatred.”

This, he concluded, is precisely what happened once Traoré broke into Attal’s apartment. “The fact that she was Jewish immediately demonised her, and amplified his delusional experience … and caused the barbaric surge of which she was the unfortunate victim.”

L
ucie Attal’s apartment block – No 30, rue de Vaucouleurs – is a classic habitation à loyer modéré, or HLM, one of the many social housing projects developed in this part of Paris in the early 1980s to provide residents, many of them immigrants, with affordable housing in a fairly central location. In recent years, the neighbourhood has become the kind of place where trendy cafes, natural wine bars and experimental restaurants with months-long waiting lists seem to anchor every block.

A squat, angular structure plastered with grimy grey tiles on a short, treeless street, the apartment block is as far as central Paris gets from 19th-century grandeur. But the rue de Vaucouleurs is hardly an example of the “social and ethnic territorial apartheid” decried by then prime minister Manuel Valls in January 2015, as he lamented the rise of homegrown Islamist extremism following the Charlie Hebdo attack. It is also a remarkably diverse neighbourhood, which appears at first glance to be a testament to the success of the French social model of integration, not its failures. Local residents describe a far more complex reality than often appears in public discussions of the killing.

One of Attal’s neighbours, Faim Mohamed, 50, told me he had lived in the building since 1997. “Life was cool,” he said, insisting that the only tensions he has ever felt came after Attal’s death, not before. “Since the murder, everyone is suspicious. They’re worried if someone is following them when they enter the building.”

Another man, from Morocco, who declined to give his name, was Attal’s neighbour on the third floor. I met him as he was bringing in groceries one afternoon, and his eyes filled with tears when I asked him if he knew the woman who had been killed. “She was someone who was very good,” he said, adding that she had designated him her “Shabbos goy”, because he would do little household tasks for her on Shabbat that she could not do for herself. He said he had been on vacation when the killing happened, visiting family in Morocco. “If I were there, I would have intervened. But I was not,” he said. A Muslim himself, he was adamant on one point: “A Muslim would not do this.”

But one reason the case became so notorious is that it fit into what has become a common narrative. France is the only country in Europe where Jews are periodically murdered for being Jewish. No fewer than 12 Jews have been killed in France in six separate incidents since 2003: Sébastien Selam, Ilan Halimi, Jonathan Sandler, Gabriel Sandler, Aryeh Sandler, Myriam Monsonégo, Yohan Cohen, Philippe Braham, François-Michel Saada, Yoav Hattab, Lucie Attal and Mireille Knoll.

In each of these cases, at least one of the perpetrators was from what the French call minorités visibles, or “visible minorities”, which typically refers to those of north African or west African descent; in most cases, the perpetrators have been linked with some form of extremist Islam. In nearly every case, the victims have been either identifiably Jewish or personal acquaintances of the perpetrator. Almost all perpetrators and victims have been lower middle-class, residing in the same diverse neighbourhoods, the same streets, or even the same buildings.

In 2006, for instance, there was the notorious murder of Ilan Halimi, in which the so-called “Gang des barbares” – a band of French-born children of Muslim immigrants from west Africa and north Africa – lured the 23-year-old Halimi, who sold mobile phones off the boulevard Voltaire, on a date with a pretty girl. They had hoped to extract €450,000 in ransom money from Halimi’s parents, whom they assumed to be rich because they were Jews. But the Halimis lived in Bagneaux, the same low-income banlieue as the gang members themselves. Ilan Halimi was imprisoned and tortured in the basement of a public housing project for three weeks. He was found on the train tracks in Sainte Geneviève de Bois, to the south of Paris, his body naked and burned.

For Rachid Benzine, a scholar of Islam and a well-known French public commentator, these killings are best understood in the context of what he calls postcolonial antisemitism. “For me, this is a holdover from the colonisation of Algeria, linked to the treatment of Algerian Jews compared with Muslim natives,” he said. In 1870, for instance, the so-called Crémieux decree secured full French citizenship for all Jewish subjects residing in Algeria, whereas Arab Muslims remained under the infamous code de l’indigénat, which stipulated an inferior legal status, essentially until 1962. The legal disparity continued even after Algeria won independence, when hundreds of thousands of former colonial subjects from North Africa continued to arrive in metropolitan France. Jews like the Attal family, originally from the Algerian city of Constantine, arrived in France as citizens. Muslims, however, had to apply to the government for the privilege of citizenship.

Benzine also noted “the unfortunate reality that the Palestinian tragedy fuels the perception among many Muslims that we somehow have the Jews of France to blame”. Another factor, he said, is the so-called concurrence des mémoires. “We have this competition of who’s suffering most,” Benzine said. Many French citizens of west African origin, for instance, argue that while the French state has invested fully in preserving the memory of the Holocaust, it has made little effort to preserve the memory of slavery. “The disparity is a fact, and it’s true that many black people say, ‘look what they do for Jewish people, and there’s nothing for us,’” Louis-Georges Tin, an activist and the former director of the Representative Council of France’s Black Associations (CRAN), told me recently. Paris is home to one of the world’s premier Holocaust museums and research centres, and a black plaque adorns the façade of nearly every building in the city from which a Jewish child was deported during the second world war. All that commemorates slavery in Paris, the capital of a former slave-trading nation, are two small nondescript statues. The only museum that documents this history is in the overseas department of Guadeloupe, nearly 7,000km from mainland France.

But the concurrence des mémoires has also become a trope in contemporary French antisemitism, with those such as the Franco-Cameroonian “comedian” Dieudonné M’Bala M’Bala engaging in Holocaust denial supposedly as a means of attacking “Jewish power” and insulting what they see as establishment narrative of the past. Tin said he could understand that frustration, but not its expression. “The anger should not be targeted toward Jewish people,” he said, “but against the state.”

T
he battle over antisemitism in contemporary France often comes down to a war of words. Few would dispute the existence or even the virulence of antisemitism. According to statistics announced by the prime minister, Edouard Philippe, on the 80th anniversary of Kristallnacht earlier this month, antisemitic incidents in France have increased by 69% in the first nine months of 2018. Among those incidents were the torching of two kosher shops in the Paris suburbs and a Jewish teenager being slashed in the face with a utility knife. For Philippe, this significance of the problem is not up for discussion: “Every aggression perpetrated against one of our fellow citizens because they are Jewish resounds like a new shattering of glass,” the prime minister wrote. But when it comes to naming the perpetrators, or labelling particular acts, this certitude collapses. Much of the French government and the French press can seem at a loss for words.

For many on the political right, antisemitism is essentially a straightforward problem, which the left strategically ignores, downplays or denies. “It’s very simple,” Alain Finkielkraut, one of France’s most prominent public intellectuals, told me earlier this year. “The new antisemitism is an import. It comes to us from the exterior. It’s among the gifts, the contributions, of immigration to French society.” (This is not entirely accurate: if the perpetrators in antisemitic crimes are often from immigrant backgrounds, they are almost always also French citizens, a distinction often lost in the public debate.)

Finkielkraut, now 69, is himself the son of immigrants, Polish Jews who came to France to escape persecution and who eluded the roundups of the early 1940s. A member of the Académie française, France’s most elite literary circle, he is now something of a public contrarian, a former leftist who uses his bestselling books and radio presence to bemoan what he sees as a nation in inexorable decline. What particularly aggravates Finkielkraut and his conservative allies about the debate around antisemitism in France is what they see as a widespread refusal to “name the problem” – that is, to declare unambiguously that the primary threat to France’s Jews comes from France’s Muslims.

For much of the left, this amounts to a dangerously crude generalisation about France’s largest minority group, which itself is the target of a constant stream of hateful rhetoric, from the covers of Charlie Hebdo to the regular pronouncements of sitting members of the French government. Muslims, too, are frequent victims of hate crimes. In June 2018, French authorities thwarted a rightwing plot to kill veiled women, imams and other Muslims at a network of halal groceries, mosques and community centres across France. Authorities have charged a group of 10 conspirators – one woman and nine men – for terrorist activity; the alleged ringleader was a former police officer.

Cécile Alduy, a scholar who has written extensively on political rhetoric, puts the question this way: “How can you denounce a ‘new’ form of antisemitism that would be perpetuated only by Muslims, without targeting all Muslims as a threat to society?”

Even the phrase “the new antisemitism” is contested. If the old antisemitism was associated with France’s Catholic far right, which has hardly disappeared, the “new antisemitism” is today used almost exclusively to describe Muslim hatred of Jews. In that sense, many on the left believe that “naming the problem” actually makes it worse, enshrining difference in a society that officially recognises none, and repeating the kind of racial stereotypes that only exacerbate social divisions. But others, both on the right and in the Jewish community, ask whether Attal and the other French Jews who have been killed since 2003 are collateral damage in an egalitarian social project that was always doomed to fail. They often decry what they call “ostrich politics”, what they see as the wilful blindness of the left with regard to Islam.

One conservative I spoke to, the Jewish historian Georges Bensoussan, echoed this point. He has been embroiled in a debate about racism and Islamophobia since 2015, when, in the course of a heated debate on a radio show hosted by Finkielkraut a month before the Paris attacks, he said: “In Arab families in France – and everyone knows it but no one wants to say it – antisemitism is something babies drink in with their mothers’ milk.” Under France’s stringent hate speech laws, a number of claimants charged Bensoussan with inciting racial hatred by using reductive blanket statements. He was acquitted in March 2017 – one month before Attal’s death – but during the period that French authorities were struggling with how, exactly, to label the killing, the Bensoussan trial was constant point of reference.

For Bensoussan, his recent trial was “a symptom of the much larger problem, the hesitation to acknowledge the truth”. He noted that despite the persistence of antisemitism among Front National members and supporters, “none of the antisemitic murders we’ve seen [in France in recent years] have been committed by the extreme right. All were perpetrated by Muslims, even as most journalists continue to blame the extreme right.”

Bensoussan is correct that mainstream media outlets refrained from emphasizing the Muslim background of Kobili Traoré, but it is hardly the case that they blamed the far right. It is also hard to defend the claim that French Muslims are somehow spared public scrutiny. To take one example, what Muslim women wear outside their homes has been among the most frequently debated questions in France over recent years. Meanwhile, political rhetoric around Islam has become increasingly extreme. Nearly every major candidate for the French presidency in 2017 had an official position on Islam, and Emmanuel Macron is still slated to announce a proposal to “reform” the practice of Islam in France.

When it comes to antisemitism, members of the French government have emphasised that they find themselves in something of an impossible situation: ensuring the safety of certain citizens while preventing the collective demonisation of others. The state takes the security threat very seriously, dispatching heavily armed reserve officers to guard nearly every major Jewish school, temple and community centre in the country. But for politicians, finding the right words to describe this situation remains acutely difficult.

“To identify the phenomenon and to understand the different ways it works is not the same thing as identifying potential authors of future attacks. We should pay real attention to the Muslims who feel stigmatised by this,” Frédéric Potier, the head of the French government’s interministerial delegation against racism and antisemitism, told me recently. “You have to pay very close attention to the words you choose, and how you say them. But at the same time, we have to say something.”

O
n 16 July 2017, France’s new president Emmanuel Macron gave a speech at a ceremony to mark the 75th anniversary of the Vel d’Hiv roundup, speaking at length about France’s complicity in Nazi crimes. Standing alongside his invited guest, the Israeli prime minister Benjamin Netanyahu, Macron then turned to the present day, mentioning the name of the woman whose case Jewish groups and public intellectuals had, for months, been citing as the latest example of France’s indifference to antisemitism. But the name he used was not Lucie Attal.

“Despite the denials of the murderer, judicial officials must now search for full clarity on the death of Sarah Halimi,” Macron said. Calling her “Sarah Halimi” was not a novel choice. Ever since the killing first made headlines, that had been the name most commonly used to identify the victim. Yet Sarah Halimi was not necessarily the way she was known to her family, or in official documents. “Sarah” was Lucie Attal’s Hebrew name, while the surname “Halimi” came from her former husband, Yaacov Halimi, a psychologist she had divorced decades earlier.

How the woman known in her lifetime as Lucie Attal became Sarah Halimi after she died is a detail no one can quite explain. But the name only intensified the symbolic resonance of her case. The name “Sarah” happens to be the label the Nazis uniformly used to identify their female Jewish victims, who were stripped of their individuality along with their lives. “Halimi” also carried its own grim associations. In 2006, the torture and murder of Ilan Halimi became a national scandal, not only because of the brutality of the crime, but also because French authorities at the time had initially refused to acknowledge that his killers had antisemitic motivations.

Thus, by the summer of 2017, Sarah Halimi had come to be seen by many as a new Ilan Halimi, the latest victim not only of Islamist antisemitism but also of government silence, and possibly even indifference. “I think ‘Sarah Halimi’ was the most resonant for the Jewish community, the most Jewish name,” Haïm Korsia, France’s chief rabbi, told me. “For some, the recurrence of the two names was striking.”

Gilles-William Goldnadel, the lawyer for Attal’s family and a well-known hardline rightwing columnist, disputes that the association between his client and Ilan Halimi was a calculated political move. But he acknowledges that names can be powerful public symbols. “We can consider that ‘Sarah Halimi’ is the name of the syndrome for the ideological reticence to recognise reality,” he said when we met in his office earlier this year.

Like Ilan Halimi before her, Sarah Halimi soon became less a real human being and more a metaphor put to use in France’s culture wars. In most accounts, she was portrayed without nuance or individuality. In April 2018, Sarah Halimi – rather than Lucie Attal – became the centrepiece of a widely publicised book entitled Le Nouvel Antisémitisme en France, a collection of essays by prominent journalists and public intellectuals. “We have to ask ourselves if her death was only an accident or whether it testifies to the spirit of the times,” says the preface. Again, the allusion to the earlier Halimi case was clear: “Such a convergence of silences will have represented a perfect model of public denial.”

O
f all the events on the Parisian social calendar, none quite compares to the annual dinner of the Representative Council of French Jewish Institutions, or Crif. Not merely a gathering of Jewish leaders or a chance to take a selfie with the aging Nazi hunters Serge and Beate Klarsfeld, the dinner is a gathering of virtually everyone who matters in French public life, including nearly every sitting government minister. Although the main event is always an address by the French president, the point of the evening is to demonstrate that even the most universalist of republics can recognise that its citizens have their particular attachments.

In keeping with Macron’s taste for setting and spectacle, the first Crif dinner of his presidency, on 7 March 2018, was held beneath the Louvre pyramid. Once again, Macron used the Attal case to show he took the issue of contemporary antisemitism seriously. “I took a stand by calling for the justice department to make clear the antisemitic dimension of Sarah Halimi’s murder,” he said, not without a tone of self-congratulation.

By that point, the Paris prosecutor, François Molins, had ultimately decided to consider the killing as antisemitic. In his speech, Macron did not go on to discuss the Attal case in any more detail, falling back on abstract platitudes: “We must never falter, we will never falter, in the denunciation of antisemitism and in the fight against this scourge.”

But two weeks later, on 23 March 2018, Mireille Knoll, 85, another elderly Jewish woman – and a survivor of the Vel d’Hiv roundup – was stabbed 11 times in her apartment and left to burn in a failed arson attempt.

The similarities to the Attal case were immediately striking. Knoll also lived alone in a public housing project in the 11th arrondissement. Authorities later confirmed that one of her alleged assailants was also a neighbour, also a young man in his late 20s, and also a Muslim, this time of north African heritage. Members of Knoll’s family later confirmed that she had known the young man, identified as Yacine Mihoub, since he was a boy and that he had been in her apartment drinking port and chatting with Knoll earlier on the day of the murder. Mihoub was a known alcoholic with a history of psychiatric problems, but he had long enjoyed a good relationship with his elderly neighbour. Knoll’s daughter-in-law, Jovinda, told me that in years past, when her mother-in-law was unwell, Mihoub had helped her “a lot”. “He was the one who’d helped put her to bed,” she said.

The news of Knoll’s death broke the next day, via a small item in Le Parisien noting that an 85-year-old woman had died in a “mysterious fire”. The day after that, on Sunday 25 March, two things happened that transformed a small fire in eastern Paris into a national scandal. The first was Paris mayor Anne Hidalgo announcing on Twitter that the victim had been a Holocaust survivor. The second was a Facebook post by Meyer Habib, a confidante of Benjamin Netanyahu’s and a rightwing member of the French parliament. Before authorities had released any information about the identities of the killers, Habib cast Knoll as a victim of “the barbarism of an Islamist”. He then situated her killing in the context of France’s recent struggle with Islamist terrorism. “It’s the same barbarism that killed several Jewish children in Toulouse, slit the throat of a priest in Saint-Etienne-du-Rouvray or a gendarme officer in Trèbes,” Habib wrote. The Trèbes attack, in which four people were killed by a terrorist, including the gendarme Arnaud Beltrame, happened on the same day as Knoll’s killing and was still receiving wall-to-wall coverage on all major networks.

Knoll’s family, meanwhile, had also retained Gilles-William Goldnadel as their lawyer. He immediately sought to link the two alleged perpetrators: “The two are Muslims who attacked with barbarity women who haven’t done anything,” he told me at the time.

This time, the French state’s response was different. By midday on 26 March, François Molins announced that the Paris prosecutor’s office would investigate the death of Mireille Knoll as an act of antisemitic violence. On 28 March, Macron went even further, closing the investigation in the court of public opinion: Knoll, he said, “was murdered because she was Jewish”.

In the days and weeks that followed the killing, there emerged a string of facts that did nothing to undermine the cruel intimacy of Knoll’s killing, but that did complicate the motive long since ascribed to her alleged murderer – especially the allegation of “Islamist” antisemitism. For starters, Knoll had two assailants, the second of whom, Alex Carrimbacus, was neither Muslim nor of North African origin. Second, Mihoub had no links to any jihadist organisation. In much of the French press, he has been treated as the principal suspect, although both he and and Carrimbacus have since accused the other of having committed the actual murder, while each claiming to have only acted as the other’s accomplice. Both are currently in prison, awaiting the conclusions of an ongoing investigation.

Further complicating matters was the story that emerged about Mihoub’s personal history with Knoll. In February 2017, Mihoub was imprisoned for having sexually assaulted the 12-year-old daughter of Knoll’s live-in carer. Mihoub was released from prison in September 2017 on a suspended sentence, and Carrimbacus, who he had met in jail, later told a panel of investigative judges that Mihoub was out for revenge, a claim authorities have not corroborated. “He told her: ‘You will pay, I wasn’t at the burial of my sister’,” Carrimbacus reportedly said. But revenge seems an unlikely motive, as Knoll had never filed a complaint against him; it was Knoll’s carer, the child’s mother, who filed the complaint that ultimately landed Mihoub in prison.

Even if Mihoub did kill Knoll out of some form of revenge, under the influence of alcohol, there may still have been an element of antisemitism to the act – what Zagury, the psychiatrist in the Attal case, interpreted as the tragic influence of “society’s atmosphere and world events”. One of Knoll’s sons, Daniel, believes there was, saying that the authorities would not have investigated the case as such if they did not have some evidence along those lines. In his interview with the judges, Carrimbacus also reportedly said that Mihoub had antisemitic motivations and had screamed “Allahu Akbar” during the attack – an allegation widely reported in the French press as fact, despite the dubious source. Mihoub’s lawyer, Fabrice de Korodi, vehemently denies the charge, claiming that Carrimbacus was trying to shift the blame. “The one motive that we can be sure was not involved was that of antisemitism,” de Korodi told me.

Unlike Lucie Attal, Mireille Knoll became an instant national martyr. On 28 March, the Crif, along with several other Jewish organisations, planned a march in Paris in Knoll’s honour, from the Place de la Nation to her apartment in Avenue Philippe Auguste. It was an astounding sight: in a country often accused of indifference to the fate of its minority populations, here were tens of thousands of people marching down the Boulevard Voltaire, wearing buttons and brandishing signs that bore the face of a murdered Jew. In the crowd, I happened to bump into Finkielkraut, who was moved by the remarkable diversity we saw on the street. “Many Jews felt abandoned by the national community as a whole,” he told me then. “But I believe today there will be people of all faiths here. That’s very important.”

But a different, less harmonious narrative soon emerged. The month after the killing, the cases of Mireille Knoll and the woman now known as Sarah Halimi became the catalysts for a blistering “manifesto” against “the new antisemitism.” This was an open letter signed by more than 250 French luminaries, including one former president, calling for French Muslims to demonstrate their fealty to the Republic and arguing that portions of the Qur’an should be “banished to obscurity”, which many took to mean redacted altogether. In response, 30 imams published a response in Le Monde, denouncing antisemitism, but also what they saw as the normalisation of Islamophobia. “Some have already seen a chance to incriminate an entire religion,” the imams wrote. “They no longer hesitate to say in public and in the media that it is the Qur’an itself that calls for murder.” (Korsia, France’s chief rabbi, later told me that he regretted the phrasing of the original manifesto, which he signed. “What I would have preferred is that we would have made clearer the need for contextualisation and interpretation rather than the total abrogation of this or that verse,” he said, referring to the call to edit portions of the Qur’an.)

Looking back on the affair, Daniel Knoll feels that an opportunity was missed. On a rainy October afternoon, he received me for tea at the small apartment he shares with Jovinda, his Catholic, Filipina wife, in a suburb of Paris not far from Orly airport. I asked him how he felt seeing his mother transformed into a national symbol, a metaphor for the threat of Islamist antisemitism – even if there was little evidence her killer had been an “Islamist”.

“The culprit was a Muslim, but he doesn’t represent the entire Muslim religion,” Knoll said. He was particularly moved by the diversity of the crowd at the march, and what he saw as a collective sense that his mother could be anyone’s grandmother. “But to say she’s a symbol? I’m not sure about that.”

Knoll has attempted to take back control of the narrative, publishing a book in November that explores the values by which his mother lived rather than the circumstances in which she died. It is anything but a testament to the incompatibility of Islam with the French Republic, and he refuses to allow his mother’s death to be presented as the failure of “vivre ensemble”, the goal of greater social cohesion in an increasingly diverse society, which, as he sees it, corresponds to how his mother – the person, not the victim – understood the world. The Knoll family, he writes, has Jewish and non-Jewish members from France, the Philippines, Canada and Israel: “‘Vivre ensemble’ could be the title of our family album.”

To honour his mother’s memory, he is also in the process of founding the Mireille Knoll Association, an organisation that will combat loneliness among the elderly and seek to tackle hatred among young people. The association’s vice president, he told me, is a Moroccan woman, and a Muslim. “Our parents taught us one thing, which can seem naive, but which we continue to cherish,” he writes in his book. “There are no borders for the heart, least of all religion.”

• Follow the Long Read on Twitter at @gdnlongread, or sign up to the long read weekly email here.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/01/france-burqa-ban-upheld-human-rights-court" labels="French burqa and niqab ban" title="France's burqa ban upheld by human rights court" >
Judges at the European court of human rights (ECHR) have upheld France's burqa ban, accepting Paris's argument that it encouraged citizens to "live together".

The law, introduced in 2010, makes it illegal for anyone to cover their face in a public place. While it also covers balaclavas and hoods, the ban has been criticised as targeting Muslim women.

The case was brought by an unnamed 24-year-old French citizen of Pakistani origin, who wears both the burqa, covering her entire head and body, and the niqab, leaving only her eyes uncovered.

She was represented by solicitors from Birmingham in the UK, who claimed the outlawing of the full-face veil was contrary to six articles of the European convention. They argued it was "inhumane and degrading, against the right of respect for family and private life, freedom of thought, conscience and religion, freedom of speech and discriminatory".

The French government asked the court to throw out the case, claiming that the law was not aimed at the burqa or veil but any covering of the face in a public place, and also applied to hoods and helmets when not worn on a motor vehicle.

The court heard that out of an estimated five million Muslims living in France – the exact figure is unknown as it is illegal to gather data by religion or ethnic group – only about 1,900 women were estimated to be affected by the ban, according to 2009 research. French officials told the judges this figure had since dropped by half "thanks to a major public information campaign".

The complainant, named only by the initials SAS, was described as a "perfect French citizen with an university education …who speaks of her republic with passion".

Her lawyer Tony Muman told the ECHR last November: "She's a patriot" adding that she had suffered "absolutely no pressure" from her family or relatives to cover herself. While she was prepared to uncover her face for identity checks, she insisted on the right to wear the full-face veil, Muman said.

The European judges decided otherwise, declaring that the preservation of a certain idea of "living together" was the "legitimate aim" of the French authorities.

Isabelle Niedlispacher, representing the Belgian government, which introduced a similar ban in 2011 and which was party to the French defence, declared both the burqa and niqab "incompatible" with the rule of law.

Aside from questions of security and equality, she added: "It's about social communication, the right to interact with someone by looking them in the face and about not disappearing under a piece of clothing."

The French and Belgian laws were aimed at "helping everyone to integrate", Niedlispacher added.

The ECHR has already upheld France's ban on headscarves in educational establishments, and its regulation requiring the removal of scarves, veils and turbans for security checks.

Tuesday's legal decision came a few days after France's highest court, the cour de cassation, upheld the firing of a creche worker for "serious misconduct" after she arrived for work wearing a veil. The woman has said she will appeal to the ECHR.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2019/mar/10/ireland-france-six-nations-match-report" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="Johnny Sexton back to his best as Ireland batter France into submission" >
Ireland confirmed their recovery from their chastening defeat by England on the opening Six Nations weekend to retain an interest in the title. The champions have to win in Cardiff on Saturday against opponents chasing a grand slam but even a bonus-point victory would not be enough should England complete their customary victory over Scotland at Twickenham.

The finish should hold more drama than the tournament itself, which has revealed a significant gap between the top and bottom three. France were not as abject here as they had been at Twickenham a month before but Ireland’s weaponry was blunter than England’s. Les Bleus were 26 points down with 14 minutes to go and their final flourish did not camouflage the deficiencies of a side which not long ago habitually contested the title.

“To still be in contention for the championship after the first weekend shows the character of the team,” said the Ireland head coach, Joe Schmidt, after his last home match in the Six Nations – which is not to mention the mediocrity of the teams they have beaten since. If Ireland were dominant here until they emptied their bench to rest players for Cardiff, they will need more polish if they are to deny Wales the grand slam and give England a tilt for the title.

The fixture between Ireland and France has for much of this decade held little interest for neutrals. Ireland scored three tries in 36 minutes and were denied two more on review in an embarrassingly one-sided opening half, 89% of which was played in the half of France, who had cause to attempt 98 more tackles than their opponents.

When Ireland, who had to replace Rob Kearney before the game because of a calf injury, secured the try bonus point 15 minutes into the second half, they immediately made five substitutions. Jonathan Sexton, Conor Murray, Tadhg Furlong, Rory Best and Iain Henderson went off to mitigate in part the extra day’s rest Wales will have. The dejection that set in after the opening round defeat by England here lifted and, if the prospect of Schmidt signing off with a fourth title hinges on Scotland winning at Twickenham for the first time in 36 years, finishing second would generate momentum before the World Cup.

Much was made in the buildup of how France were tapping in to Toulouse’s handling, offloading game but, when they did have the ball, they were hustled off it. Their discipline collapsed under pressure, although this was another afternoon that showed up the contradictory nature of the game: players entering a breakdown from the side to force a turnover were penalised but those who did so to prevent a turnover were tolerated by the referee.

As the team in possession Ireland had a liberal supply of penalties. From the opening minutes they opted to kick for touch rather than go for goal and scored a try at the first attempt when Henderson took the ball at the front. As France set up to hold the drive, the ball was smuggled to Best on the left wing for the hooker, playing in his last competitive Test here, to score.

France responded through Thomas Ramos after a cross-kick but a review found the ball had brushed the fingers of Damian Penaud and bounced forward. They were not to sight their opponents’ line again until the second half as Ireland took an iron grip on the game, keeping it simple and controlling the gainline.

Sexton scored their second try after another penalty lineout, looping round Garry Ringrose after Demba Bamba had entered the maul from the side and the referee played advantage. Cian Healy had earlier been denied an opportunist try as France dithered at a ruck on their line, the prop deemed to have knocked on rather than apply downward pressure, and the excellent Ringrose lost control of the ball near the line after beating Thomas Ramos to a high kick.

France were hanging on, if unable to hang on to what little possession they enjoyed, and the replacement back-row Jack Conan made the interval score 19-0 when he broke two tackles after a multi-phase move. France started the second period as if they had been told they would be making their own way home and there was an improvement, but Ireland were soon back on the attack with another lineout.

As CJ Stander peeled round the back of it, he slipped an inside pass to Keith Earls who had come off the right wing. It was a staple Ireland move but Bamba was unfamiliar with it. The prop stood too wide and the wing stepped into the space to secure the bonus point. Ireland eased off as their attention switched to Wales. France survived the 68th-minute yellow card shown to the prop Dorian Aldegheri for persistently collapsing scrums and finished with tries from Yoann Huget and Camille Chat in the final reckoning to dent Ireland’s points difference, a factor that is unlikely to come into play on Saturday.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/feb/05/apple-to-pay-10-years-of-back-taxes-to-france" labels="Apple" title="Apple to pay 10 years of back taxes to France" >
Apple has agreed to pay 10 years of back taxes to France, marking the latest victory for European governments pushing tech multinationals to pay their fair share in local markets.

The iPhone and iPad maker reportedly shelled out close to €500m (£440m) after reaching a confidential settlement with French authorities in December, according to the French news magazine L’Express.

Apple has not disclosed the size of the settlement, but said in a statement: “The French tax authority recently concluded a multiyear audit of our French accounts and the adjustment will be reflected in our publicly filed accounts.

“We know the important role tax payments play in society and we pay all that we owe according to tax laws and local customs wherever we operate.”

American tech firms such as Apple have been heavily criticised for the small amounts of tax they pay in EU countries including France and the UK relative to the billions of pounds in sales they report in these states.

The chancellor, Philip Hammond, recently announced plans to introduce a special digital services tax by 2020 on online firms making more than £500m globally per year. It’s expected that the tax would raise more than £400m annually for government coffers.

France is also introducing its own “GAFA tax” – referring to Google, Apple, Facebook and Amazon – which would affect tech companies with global sales of more than €750m and €25m in France. That law would be retroactive to 1 January and is expected to raise €500m this year.

The country’s settlement with Apple follows a spate of successful challenges launched by European authorities over unpaid tax in recent years.

In 2016, Apple was ordered to pay €13bn in back taxes to Ireland by the European commission, which said the company paid a tax rate of just 0.005% on its European profits two years earlier.

Amazon also ended a protracted battle with France in 2018 after agreeing to pay the state €200m and saying it would start to declare all its earnings in the country.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2019/feb/10/england-france-six-nations-2019-match-report-rugby" labels="Six Nations 2019" title="Jonny May hat-trick spearheads England’s crushing win over France" >
Those wanting to know if England’s opening win in Dublin was a one-off now have their answer. Once again there was no stopping Eddie Jones’s rampant team from securing a convincing bonus-point victory, an outcome that sets up a tasty Six Nations grand slam eliminator with a similarly unbeaten Wales in Cardiff on Saturday week.

English optimism has a long history of dissolving across the Severn Bridge but a serious Wales performance will be required to diminish England’s current confidence levels. The same collective pace, power and intent they showed in Ireland was evident on a blustery, occasionally damp afternoon, with Jonny May the main beneficiary. The Leicester wing’s hat-trick of tries in the opening 29 minutes made him the first Englishman to achieve the feat against France since Jake Jacob in 1924.

The home team were superior in all departments, kicking cleverly, hitting hard and finding acres of space in behind a slow-witted defence. “Very painful,” was the verdict of the French captain, Guilhem Guirado, and, from a Gallic perspective, he was not wrong. This was France's worst defeat to England since 1911. Jones was careful not to go overboard, clearly determined to keep his players’ feet on the ground, but similarities with the plodding England team beaten 22-16 in Paris a year ago are increasingly hard to find.

Few players in world rugby are more improved than May, with Elliot Daly also enjoying a productive afternoon and Courtney Lawes further underlining the strength in depth at Jones’s disposal. If there was a nagging sense that New Zealand, for example, might have stuck 50 or 60 points on their opponents, the fact England still have obvious room for improvement will concern all their rivals.

The galloping advances the team are making under the leadership of Owen Farrell, who scored 17 points, including his side’s sixth and final try, have not been so thrillingly obvious since England’s heyday in the early 2000s, not least in 2001 when they went to Cardiff and won 44-15. No one would be silly enough to predict a similarly one-sided contest this time but even a scrappy away win would leave Italy and Scotland standing between a second grand slam in four years under Jones.

The most immediate priority for their opponents will be to end England’s remarkable record of early tries, which has now seen them score within three minutes of kick-off in their past five Tests. Inside 66 seconds May had his first try on the board, touching down Daly’s intelligent left‑foot grubber after the Saracens-bound full-back had made swift ground following a midfield turnover.

Almost every day is currently a May Day at Twickenham and before the half-hour mark the 28-year-old had extended his tally to 12 tries in his last 12 Tests. First, he showed dazzling footwork to outwit Damian Penaud to score in the left corner before successfully scooping up Chris Ashton’s chip ahead to complete his hat-trick. May possesses a unique talent, but even the quicksilver ex-Wales wing Shane Williams would have been proud of this particular treble.

Penaud did make slight amends with a 35th-minute try set up by Yoann Huget but when the classy Henry Slade dummied his way past Guirado to claim his side’s bonus-point try just before half-time the game was effectively over. While France squandered a 16-0 point half-time lead against Wales in Paris, England were never going to surrender their 30-8 interval advantage here.

A penalty try and a yellow card for Gaël Fickou when a sprinting Ashton was tackled without the ball with the line beckoning merely added to French woe and the last half-hour was largely a question of how much damage England would ultimately inflict. In the event there was only one more try, for Farrell after May, for the umpteenth time, had burned off the cover.

If there was a slight debate as to whether the last defender, Antoine Dupont, was impeded by England’s flier as he vainly tried to gather the rolling ball, there was no disputing Farrell’s fitness or desire that ensured he was first to the rebound.

Even a brief touchline scuffle sparked by Kyle Sinckler throwing an arm at Arthur Iturria did little to rouse the less than irresistible visitors. It was another of those days for France, who had travelled without much in the way of hope and ended up largely stripped of their dignity. They have now won three of their past 19 Tests and their head coach, Jacques Brunel, is edging into the kind of uneasy territory that cost his predecessor, Guy Novès, his job. Typing Brunel’s name always reminds some of us of his near namesake Jean-Jacques Burnel, the bass guitarist of The Stranglers. Forty years on, sadly, we are also reaching the point where French rugby has no more heroes any more.

On this evidence it will certainly rank among the more startling about-turns if this result is somehow reversed when the two sides meet again in their World Cup pool game in Yokohama this autumn. The final score was England’s record margin of victory against Les Bleus in the Six Nations and will be particularly fondly remembered by the Wasps scrum-half, Dan Robson, who finally made it off the bench for the last 11 minutes to earn a long-awaited first cap as a replacement for Ben Youngs.

With the possible exception of the prop Mako Vunipola, who sat out the closing stages with an enormous ice pack on his ankle, England could hardly be in healthier shape for their tournament-defining visit to Cardiff.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2017/jul/06/france-ban-petrol-diesel-cars-2040-emmanuel-macron-volvo" labels="Automotive industry" title="France to ban sales of petrol and diesel cars by 2040" >
France will end sales of petrol and diesel vehicles by 2040 as part of an ambitious plan to meet its targets under the Paris climate accord, Emmanuel Macron’s government has announced.

The announcement comes a day after Volvo said it would only make fully electric or hybrid cars from 2019 onwards, a decision hailed as the beginning of the end for the internal combustion engine’s dominance of motor transport after more than a century.

Nicolas Hulot, the country’s new ecology minister, said: “We are announcing an end to the sale of petrol and diesel cars by 2040.” Hulot added that the move was a “veritable revolution”.

He said it would be a “tough” objective for carmakers but France’s industry was well equipped to make the switch. “Our [car]makers have enough ideas in the drawer to nurture and bring about this promise ... which is also a public health issue.”

Hulot insisted that the decision was a question of public health policy and “a way to fight against air pollution”. The veteran environmental campaigner was among several political newcomers to whom Macron gave top jobs in his government.

Pascal Canfin, the head of WWF France and a former Green politician who served in François Hollande’s government, said the new policy platform to counter climate change went further than previous administrations in France. “It places France among the leaders of climate action in the world,” he told France Inter radio.

Prof David Bailey, an automotive industry expert at Aston University, said: “The timescale involved here is sufficiently long term to be taken seriously. If enacted it would send a very clear signal to manufacturers and consumers of the direction of travel and may accelerate a transition to electric cars.”

Norway, which has the highest penetration of electric cars in the world, has set a target of only allowing sales of 100% electric or plug-in hybrid cars by 2025.

Other countries have floated the idea of banning cars powered by an internal combustion engine to meet air quality and climate change goals, but have not yet passed concrete targets.

The Netherlands has mooted a 2025 ban for diesel and petrol cars, and some federal states in Germany are keen on a 2030 phase-out.

India, where scores of cities are blighted by dangerous air pollution, is mulling the idea of no longer selling petrol or diesel cars by 2030, and said it wants to introduce electric cars in “a very big way”.

The UK has an aspiration of all new cars being electric or ultra low emission by 2040, but has been criticised by campaigners and politicans for being slow to act on air pollution.

Sadiq Khan, the mayor of London, said: “I welcome the strong leadership the French government has shown by making the decision to end the sale of petrol and diesel cars by 2040.

“This radical step shames the timid and insufficient response of our own government to the health threat posed by poor air quality.”

France’s announcement came as Bloomberg New Energy Finance predicted electric cars would come to dominate the automotive market more quickly and dramatically than previously thought.

Electric vehicles will make up 54% of all light-duty vehicle sales by 2040, up from the 35% share Bloomberg was forecasting just last year, according to a new report by the research group.

Bloomberg said such a widespread uptake of electric vehicles would globally reduce oil demand by 8m barrels a day and increase electricity consumption by 5% to charge all the new cars.

But Tony Seba, a Stanford University economist who has published research predicting electric cars will even more rapidly take over from conventional cars, said of France’s plan: “Banning sales of diesel and gasoline vehicles by 2040 is a bit like banning sales of horses for road transportation by 2040: there won’t be any to ban.”

French car manufacturers Peugeot, Citroën and Renault ranked first, second and third on a 2016 list of large car manufacturers with the lowest carbon emissions, the European Environment Agency said.

Just 0.6% of new car registrations across the EU last year were for pure electric vehicles, compared with 1.1% of new cars sold in France.

French-Japanese carmaker Renault-Nissan has been an enthusiastic early advocate for the vehicles, taking 14.6% of the EU market share for battery-powered vehicles. The firm has built 425,000 of the more than 2m electric cars sold globally.

France’s reliance on nuclear power stations for 80% of its electricity supply means that a shift to electric vehicles rather than oil-powered ones would dramatically cut its remaining carbon emissions.
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2019/mar/09/queer-eye-tan-france-the-word-gay-was-never-mentioned-in-my-parents-home" labels="How to be a boy: a masculinity special, Queer Eye" title="Queer Eye's Tan France: ‘The word gay was never mentioned in my parents’ home’" >
T
an France comes into the room, sits to my right and immediately bounces back up and asks to swap chairs. He wants me, he explains, to see his good side. So we switch, and he sits and crosses his legs. “My jaw is squarer this side. I didn’t actually think about it before the show. Then I realised, oh, I really don’t like that side,” he says.

The show he’s referring to is Queer Eye, Netflix’s reality TV smash hit of last year, in which five gay men give someone, usually a man, a whole-life makeover, from style (where France comes in) to interiors, grooming and cooking. As the self-styled Fab Five spend a week doing their subject up, they also get to what Queer Eye considers the heart of the matter: rooting out issues of poor self-esteem hidden beneath bad hair, cargo pants and Crocs, and trying to mend them. Since rebooting as a Netflix show (it first screened in 2003, under the name Queer Eye For The Straight Guy), it has become a global phenomenon, winning three Emmys and transforming the lives of its hosts as well as its subjects, or “heroes” as the show calls them.

France’s life has perhaps changed the most. He’s gone from anonymous wholesale clothing businessman to a global star in under 12 months, thanks to a show he never imagined being a part of. “I wasn’t qualified. I’d never been on TV before. It made no sense to give this complete novice this high-profile show,” he says. Before Queer Eye, he had no gay friends, and a private Instagram account. Now he has 2.1 million followers and is writing a memoir. “The show has given me more than I’ll ever know, and not just financially or in terms of fame,” France says. “It put me in a position to represent my community in a way that I had never seen. And, I’m not just talking about the gay community, I’m talking about the Asian community.” (France’s parents grew up in Pakistan; he is from Doncaster.) He is now the most famous – and in fact the only – out gay Muslim man on western television.

***

We meet in a corporate hotel suite that could do with a little Queer Eyeing, though France himself needs no intervention. Neat and muscular, his style is understated, with a cartoonish salt-and-pepper quiff and Bambi eyes. Lip balm is reapplied several times; his legs remain crossed throughout our conversation. He is polite and poised, his accent remaining distinctly South Yorkshire even though he has lived in Salt Lake City, Utah for six years.

When France first meets Queer Eye participants, he tells me, he asks for a hug, then makes a promise. “I don’t say, ‘Tell me your deepest, darkest secret.’ I say, ‘You can ask me my deepest, darkest secret. Ask me anything.’” Straight men usually want to know about gay sex. “How it all works, something vulgar like that,” France says with an eye roll.

But in an episode in the new series, one guy asked France something different. “He said, ‘How are you so confident and comfortable in your own skin, when I’m almost positive you’ve had a lifetime of people judging you. You’re brown, you’re gay, you just don’t blend into a crowd. How is it you still put a smile on your face?’”

How did France answer? “Over the last 15 years, I’ve worked hard to build a career that makes me feel really confident,” he says. “I’ve done as much as possible to make sure I’m in a position that I’m successful.” France, to borrow Queer Eye parlance, has become his very best self through the world of work.

His parents came to England as children, and France grew up in Doncaster with two older brothers and a sister; the family lived next door to his uncle on his father’s side. His parents ran taxi offices, post offices and convenience stores, at different points; his grandfather had a factory in Bury that produced denim for Disney. France went to the mosque every day and did not socialise outside his community; in his bedroom, he played with Barbie dolls and listened to Kylie Minogue’s I Should Be So Lucky.

He says he encountered racism early on in life, and resolved to deal with it without drama. “I knew that having an adverse reaction was not going to achieve anything. Me calling them something or swearing back would achieve nothing. I knew if they were willing to talk to me, I could say, ‘What is your problem with Pakis? Who do you think we are?’”

He also began to understand another point of difference. In primary school, there was a teacher in assembly who crossed her legs, and who fascinated six-year-old France. “I thought, ‘Ooh, that’s elegant, I want to sit like that.’” So he started crossing his legs and found he liked it – but abruptly stopped when a teenage male cousin tapped him on the leg and told him boys don’t sit like that.

France normally avoids swearing but talking about the crossed legs episode riles him. “At the time it was a case of, ‘It’s not appropriate for you.’ Nowadays I’m like, fuck appropriate. If a boy wants to sit a certain way, let him.”

He tells the rest of his childhood story in such a straightforward way that it is hard to detect any tension between his emerging sexuality and his faith. “Here’s the thing: the word ‘gay’ was never mentioned in the household,” he explains. “I don’t ever remember a gay character on TV, except maybe from Are You Being Served? But I was too young to understand what that was about.”

His father, who died when France was 13, once bought him a Barbie doll’s house and dolls – he thinks out of competitiveness with his brother next door, who had bought something similar for his daughter. But the young Tan understood that he should police himself. “I was frightfully aware that if everybody said I was obsessed with this, it might lead to negative consequences. My dad might have learned it ‘isn’t right’ for his Pakistani son. So I didn’t play with the doll’s house when other people were around.”

At 13, France was able to put a name to his feelings, when he saw a boy at school take off his T-shirt during PE, and fancied him. “I knew I was gay, I just didn’t know the word. There was never a time I was attracted to women.” How did fancying a boy make him feel? “You know, weirdly fine. I thought about this a lot. Was I scared? Was I panicking? And I wasn’t. I was always so matter-of-fact about everything. I wasn’t a dramatic child. I remember thinking, ‘OK, that’s a thing. I’m not going to try to change it. I don’t feel wrong.’ I don’t remember any adverse feelings except, oh shit, you probably need to figure out how to hide it. We didn’t have out people in the Pakistani community, so I knew it was something hidden and not discussed. I also knew there had to be more, because there were plenty of gay men in the white community.”

He is similarly matter-of-fact about coming out, a process he began at 16, when he went to study fashion at Doncaster College, and met a boyfriend in his part-time BT call centre job. He told friends, then siblings, then his mother. The rest of the family were shocked, but he accepts that they needed time to adjust. “They had planned a whole heterosexual life for me,” he says, “and it was just shocking to hear that plan was never going to come to fruition.”

On Queer Eye, coming out is usually more dramatic. One of the show’s most emotional episodes in season one follows AJ, a 32-year-old black man, on a journey to self-acceptance. AJ has a boyfriend and gay friends, but he doesn’t want to wear anything too feminine or come across as “too gay”. His father died before he got a chance to come out to him. Karamo Brown, the show’s go-to shrink (though everyone takes turns), describes why it’s hard to be gay in the black community, schooling AJ in self-love. The episode ends with AJ, in his renovated bedroom and much better shoes, coming out to his stepmother. Even by Queer Eye’s standards, it is exceptionally moving.

The series as a whole is engineered to make you blub, whether you’re watching or taking part. (Online, you can find as many gifs of Antoni Porowski, the show’s cook and resident hunk, crying, as you can with his top off.) But France has never cried on camera. “I physically can’t. I don’t know what it is. I sit there thinking, c’mon. It’s the one thing I really dislike about myself.” AJ’s episode was the exception, moving him so much behind the scenes that he asked for time out. “None of my tears made it into the cut,” he says. “But I was crying so hard at one point, I had to take a break. I could not do it any more.”

In another notable episode, France finds common ground with Neal, an Indian-American computer programmer who wants to make his mother proud. “I totally get what it’s like, as a Pakistani, to have your mum be proud of you,” France says to him. “It takes a lot for them to say it.” France’s particular skill is to make a considered and emotional connection with his subjects, expressed through his careful choice of clothes for them. Such as with Skyler, a trans man for whom a suit fitting is a difficult experience. “Nothing makes me feel more of a guy than when I’m in a suit,” France tells Skyler. “So I want to find a way to get you in a suit that makes complete sense for you.”

When Queer Eye returns this month, there will be some minor tweaks: it will be set in Kansas rather than Atlanta; there are also more female heroes. France, whose background is in womenswear, is glad to have this chance to show off his skill set. “I was desperate for it because I get to have a lot more fun with womenswear.”

And the women, he finds, are more forthcoming with their stories. “It takes longer to chip away at who our male heroes are,” he says. “They don’t give away a lot immediately. Women are just more comfortable saying, ‘This is what I’m going through right now.’ Men are taught to shut it down and ‘man up’: don’t talk about the things that are hurting or hindering them.” Each of the Fab Five has a different way of doing this, he says: he asks for honesty – and not just about the clothes he chooses. “I say, ‘This will only work if you are completely open with me. I need you to tell me everything that you’re feeling, even if that doesn’t make sense for what we are doing right now. If you’re not feeling happy about your marriage but we’re talking about a sweater, tell me. I need you to be as honest as possible.’”

***

The young France held no ambitions to go into entertainment. He started out in retail as a manager for high street brand Bershka. A visit to Salt Lake City led to a meeting with the owner of a Mormon modesty clothing manufacturer, who offered him a regional manager job there. “I learned every facet of retail. I got contacts for factories, learned how to buy, ship and distribute.” He worked in Utah for two and a half years, before his visa ran out.

Back in the UK, France temped and in the evenings built his own modesty brand, Kingdom &amp; State. He launched a niche business in the US, he says, because he didn’t have the funds to compete with big brands such as Topshop or H&amp;M. Also, he saw a gap in the market for a young, fashionable clothing range that met Mormon guidelines on modesty: floaty dresses to the knee, loose-fitting casual tops and high-waisted bikinis. “I wanted to create a brand that you couldn’t tell was modest clothing for Mormons,” France says. “These girls were cute and wanted to be fashionable. I wanted to create a London look for them that just so happened to cover the areas of their bodies they had to cover as Mormon women. And that’s where it took off really well [in Utah], really quickly.”

France travelled back and forth to Salt Lake City, where he worked with fashion influencers the Skalla family (“Think the Mormon Kardashians”). At one point, the family were in talks about their own reality show; it never happened, but executives who met France with them passed his name to someone at Netflix who was casting for Queer Eye.

On a work trip in January 2008, he met Rob France, a paediatric nurse and former Mormon whose family ran a cowboy ranch in Wyoming. There was an instant connection, with plenty of common ground in their conservative upbringings. France was especially chuffed to meet someone who didn’t drink. (“I didn’t realise there were white people who didn’t drink until I turned up in Salt Lake City,” he says.) They maintained a long-distance relationship, marrying in the US after the Defence of Marriage Act was overturned in 2013. “It wasn’t hard work at all,” France says of the long-distance relationship. “It was the constant, the easiest thing in my life.”

Six years ago, France (his birth name is Tanweer Safdar) got a green card and moved to Salt Lake City, where the couple live. “I still have the biggest crush on him,” France says of his husband. “Every time I see him, I get this feeling like I can’t believe he’s mine.”

It was Rob who encouraged him when Netflix invited him to audition for Queer Eye. “My husband said, ‘You’ve been moaning for years and years that you have no gay friends. There’s going to be a room of gay men and you’re the most sociable person I know: just go.’”

Netflix flew the 40 finalists to Los Angeles for a weekend. France hit it off with four others right away; by day two, they’d created their own Fab Five text group. That initial chemistry became key to the show’s success.

In June last year, France opened up to his castmate Jonathan Van Ness, on Getting Curious, a popular podcast hosted by the show’s grooming expert. Van Ness quizzed his friend about his experiences of being gay and Muslim, and his current relationship with his family. They did not come to his wedding, France says, but since the show aired, have begun to acknowledge his husband by name.

But when I ask France about this, he shuts down. “I… we don’t talk about that,” he says. His religion, I’m told, is also out of bounds. “Just because I am on a TV show does not mean people have access to every facet of my life,” he explains. “I never got into this as if it were my reality show.”

What he will say is that being on television has given him pause for thought. “I didn’t want my family to feel the pressure of people around them thinking, ‘This is your son and he’s going around being very openly gay, control him better.’” He spoke to his family after the show first aired. “I asked if they were unhappy with how I behaved. Thankfully they didn’t see a difference. They said, ‘You giggled a little bit more, you cross your legs, your hand is a little camper than it is at home. But it was always there, you just control it differently.’”

He faces a very specific set of pressures, I suggest. “I represent many marginalised communities,” he agrees. “There’s the pressure of how to act as a man. There is also the pressure of how you are as an Asian man, and how you are perceived and how you should behave. How you are representing yourself as an immigrant in the US – what you need to do to be the best immigrant you can be.”

France uncrosses his legs and reaches for the pot of lip balm. He tells me he sometimes feels judged by the gay community for not being out and proud enough. “You’re not a good gay if you’re not representing at every moment,” he says. “But only you get to decide how to present yourself to the world. And I get to be the version of gay I want.”

• Queer Eye series three is available on Netflix from 15 March.

Comments on this piece are premoderated to ensure the discussion remains on the topics raised by the article. Please be aware that there may be a short delay in comments appearing on the site.

If you would like a comment on this piece to be considered for inclusion on Weekend magazine’s letters page in print, please email weekend@theguardian.com, including your name and address (not for publication).
</doc>
<doc source="Guardian" link="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/tourdefrance" labels="" title="Tour de France" >

</doc>
</corpus>